<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2021-07-04T12:03:07+02:00</updated><id>https://juan.pallares.me/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Juan Pallarès Garbí</title><subtitle>Landing page.</subtitle><author><name>Juan Pallarès</name><email>juan@pallares.me</email></author><entry xml:lang="es"><title type="html">Calculadora de sueldo neto</title><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/calculadora-de-sueldo-neto/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Calculadora de sueldo neto" /><published>2021-07-04T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-07-04T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://juan.pallares.me/calculadora-de-sueldo-neto</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://juan.pallares.me/calculadora-de-sueldo-neto/">&lt;p&gt;Imagina que tienes una oferta de trabajo, un nuevo sueldo bruto anual que suena tentador, pero ¿Cúal es el neto mensual? ¿Cuál es la subida? Imagina que puedes comparar tu sueldo actual con el futuro simplemente arrastrando un slider, te traigo la solución:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;:moneybag: &lt;a href=&quot;https://tusueldoneto.pallares.me&quot; target=&quot;\_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Calculadora de sueldo neto&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Si eres como yo, para calcular el sueldo neto a partir del bruto recurrías al &lt;a href=&quot;https://cincodias.elpais.com/herramientas/calculadora-sueldo-neto/&quot; target=&quot;\_blank&quot;&gt;primer resultado de Google&lt;/a&gt;. Sin parar de hacer scroll arriba y abajo, refrescando la página que por cierto, es poco usable desde el móvil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Y si querías hilar fino, te creas un Excel con la típica tabla de tramos y te lo calculas manual:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/tramos.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tramos IPRF Estatales&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;¿Ya está, no? Pues no no…para calcular bien el sueldo neto de verdad hay muchos más detalles a tener en cuenta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Un día quise derrotar ese dragón y entender lo mejor posible como se calcula. Mientras investigaba he ido desarrollando esta &lt;a href=&quot;https://tusueldoneto.pallares.me&quot; target=&quot;\_blank&quot;&gt;calculadora de sueldo neto&lt;/a&gt; para validar lo que iba aprendiendo. Le faltan muchos casos y la UX es abominable pero he priorizado que sea cómodo de usar &lt;del&gt;y soy nefasto haciendo UX&lt;/del&gt;. Agárrate que vienen curvas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conocimientos-básicos-primero&quot;&gt;Conocimientos básicos primero&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hay un especie de leyenda urbana que dice: &lt;em&gt;“Si te suben el sueldo y cambias de tramo puedes acabar cobrando menos”.&lt;/em&gt; La he escuchado varias veces y explica muy bien que poca educación financiera hay en las escuelas, supongo que es más importante aprender que una persona separó los mares y multiplicó los panes…bueno, que me lío.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Es imposible que una subida de tu sueldo implique ganar menos en neto&lt;/strong&gt;. Los tramos son acumulables. Ejemplo, imaginemos que Paco cobra 24.000 cucas brutas al año:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/tramosExplicados.png&quot; alt=&quot;Tramos explicados&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Los primeros 12.450€ tienen 19% de retención.
Lo que va entre 12.450€ y 20.200€, es decir, los siguientes 7.750 machacantes tienen el 24% de retención.
Finalmente, la diferencia entre 24.000€ y 20.200€ =&amp;gt; 3.800€ le retienen el 30%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Siempre la primera parte del salario va a tener un retención mas baja y sube progresivamente en cada tramo. He intentado mostrar esto mediante gráficos en la &lt;a href=&quot;https://tusueldoneto.pallares.me&quot; target=&quot;\_blank&quot;&gt;calculadora&lt;/a&gt;, pruébala.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;irpf-estatal-y-autónomico&quot;&gt;IRPF Estatal y Autónomico&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Las calculadoras online normalmente solo te muestran unos tramos de IRPF. Esos tramos son los estatales y aplican a todos excepto vascos y navarros. Lo que no solemos tener en cuenta es que &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.businessinsider.es/tablas-irpf-comunidades-autonomas-cuanto-pagas-renta-625415&quot;&gt;cada autonomía tiene sus tramos&lt;/a&gt;, y en TODAS son diferentes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/dosTramos.png&quot; alt=&quot;Tramos del estado y catalanes&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;La tabla Estatal típica solo aplica a españoles no residentes, si resides en territorio español, se usa la tabla de tu comunidad y la estatal (&lt;strong&gt;con la mitad del porcentaje en cada tramo&lt;/strong&gt;).
Siguiendo el ejemplo de Paco, tendríamos el siguiente IRPF:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Estatal - 1.626,90€&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Autonómico - 1.846,49€&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Total - 3.473,39€ (14,47%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Si estas haciendo los cálculos por tu lado y no te cuadran los números es normal, mira el siguiente punto.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;deducciones-y-gastos&quot;&gt;Deducciones y gastos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Primero de todo, hay un mínimo de gastos de 2.000€, todos los calculos deben hacerse restando incialmente este valor del bruto, en el caso de Paquito 22.000€ es la cifra con la que se empieza a calcular el IPRF.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Posiblemente te suene la cifra 5.550€. Es el mínimo deducible. El caso más común persona soltera sin hijos etc. tiene ese mínimo deducible. Para deducirlo se aplican los tramos también. Es decir, para saber cuanto nos podemos deducir si vivimos en Cataluña tenemos que aplicar los tramos del estado y de la autonomía a la cifra a deducir. Ejemplo:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5.550€ está tanto en el primer tramo del Estado (hasta 12.450€) como de Cataluña (hasta 17.707,02€), por lo tanto se aplica el tipo del primer tramo:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Estado 9,5% - 527,25€&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cataluña 12% - 666,00€&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A los impuestos totales del estado se les resta la deducción calculada, igual con la autonomía.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Este es el caso estándar, las deducciones aumentan por cada hijo, por cada ancestro dependiente, etc. He recogido algunos de estos casos en la &lt;a href=&quot;https://tusueldoneto.pallares.me&quot; target=&quot;\_blank&quot;&gt;calculadora de sueldo neto&lt;/a&gt;, pero me quedan varios por añadir.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imaginemos que Paco tiene gemelos, 2 hijos de menores de 3 años. Pues las deducciones aumentan hasta quedar:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Estado 4,66% - 1035,50€&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cataluña 5,2% - 1308,0€&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;El sueldo neto mensual con 12 pagas resultante es 1679,4€, que comparado con el sueldo sin hijos (1583,55€) resulta en casi 100€ más al mes por tener dos hijos menores de 3 años, no se si llega para los pañales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;seguridad-social&quot;&gt;Seguridad Social&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Una vez tienes el IRPF puedes pensar que ya lo tienes para calcular el neto, craso error. También cotizas a la seguridad social y eso también se quita del bruto. Esto debería ser facil, es el 6,35% pero con un matiz, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.campmanyabogados.com/blog/bases-cotizacion&quot;&gt;hay un mínimo y un máximo&lt;/a&gt;. El máximo se alcanza con 48.841€ brutos anuales, todos los sueldos a partir de ahí pagan lo mismo. El mínimo* es 12.600€ brutos anuales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Paco le queda un pago a Seguridad Social de 1.524,00€&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;la-fórmula-tada&quot;&gt;La fórmula :tada:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A grandes rasgos la fórmula es la siguiente:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Salario neto = salario bruto - IRPF Estatal - IRPF Autonomico - Seguridad Social&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Con los matices ya comentados:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Los gastos y las deducciones modifican el IRPF final.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hay mínimo y máximo de Seguridad Social.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Espero haber aclarado un poco como funciona este cálculo, es importanto conocer esta información, la pela es la pela.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;siguientes-pasos&quot;&gt;Siguientes pasos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Añadir los deducciones que faltan.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Añadir tickets restaurant, guardería, etc. como cotizan.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mejorar la UX.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;fuentes&quot;&gt;Fuentes&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.businessinsider.es/tablas-irpf-comunidades-autonomas-cuanto-pagas-renta-625415&quot;&gt;Tablas de IRPF por comunidades autónomas&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ekuatio.com/como-se-calcula-el-porcentaje-de-irpf-en-la-nomina/&quot;&gt;Como se cálcula el porcantaje de IRPF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www2.agenciatributaria.gob.es/wlpl/PRET-R170/index.zul&quot;&gt;Cálculo de rentenciones&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.finect.com/usuario/Josetrecet/articulos/hijos-declaracion-renta&quot;&gt;Cuánto puedes desgravarte en la renta por tus hijos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Juan Pallarès</name><email>juan@pallares.me</email></author><category term="sueldo" /><category term="salario" /><category term="neto" /><category term="bruto" /><category term="salary" /><category term="calculator" /><category term="net" /><summary type="html">Cómo funciona realmente el cálculo del IRPF, seguridad social, etc.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Book - The Psychology of Money Timeless Lessons on Wealth, Greed, and Happiness - Morgan Hausel</title><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/the-psychology-of-money/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Book - The Psychology of Money Timeless Lessons on Wealth, Greed, and Happiness - Morgan Hausel" /><published>2021-04-24T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-04-24T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://juan.pallares.me/the-psychology-of-money</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://juan.pallares.me/the-psychology-of-money/">&lt;p&gt;I’ve read several &lt;a href=&quot;https://juan.pallares.me/books/&quot;&gt;books&lt;/a&gt; lately but the one I liked more and want to review is: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.es/Housel-M-Psychology-Money-Morgan/dp/0857197681&quot;&gt;“The Psychology of Money” by Morgan Hausel&lt;/a&gt;. It’s so interesting that I couldn’t stop &lt;a href=&quot;https://juan.pallares.me/books/the-psychology-of-money-timeless-lessons-on-wealth-greed-and-happiness/&quot;&gt;highlighting sentences&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aim of the book is “use short stories to convince you that soft skills are more important than the technical side of money”. I’ll add that the book talks about the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FIRE_movement&quot;&gt;FIRE movement&lt;/a&gt; without metioning it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s divided in 20 different learnings. I’ll go over them and quote the parts that resonated with me the most:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-no-ones-crazy&quot;&gt;1. No One’s Crazy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;you-personal-experiences-with-money-make-up-maybe-00000001-of-whats-happened-in-the-world-but-maube-80-of-how-you-think-the-world-works&quot;&gt;You personal experiences with money make up maybe 0.0000001% of what’s happened in the world, but maube 80% of how you think the world works&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People from different generations, raised by different parents who earned different incomes and held different values, in different parts of the world, born into different economies, experiencing different job markets with different incentives and different degrees of luck, learn very different lessons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The economists wrote: “Our findings suggest that individual investors’ willingness to bear risk depends on personal history.” Not intelligence, or education, or sophistication&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-luck--risk&quot;&gt;2. Luck &amp;amp; Risk&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;nothing-is-as-good-or-bad-as-it-seems&quot;&gt;Nothing is as good or bad as it seems&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The line between “inspiringly bold” and “foolishly reckless” can be a millimeter thick and only visible with hindsight. Risk and luck are doppelgangers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cover of Forbes magazine does not celebrate poor investors who made good decisions but happened to experience the unfortunate side of risk. But it almost certainly celebrates rich investors who made OK or even reckless decisions and happened to get lucky. Both flipped the same coin that happened to land on a different side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bill Gates once said, “Success is a lousy teacher. It seduces smart people into thinking they can’t lose.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-never-enough&quot;&gt;3. Never enough&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;when-rich-people-do-crazy-things&quot;&gt;When rich people do crazy things&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a party given by a billionaire on Shelter Island, Kurt Vonnegut informs his pal, Joseph Heller, that their host, a hedge fund manager, had made more money in a single day than Heller had earned from his wildly popular novel Catch-22 over its whole history. Heller responds, “Yes, but I have something he will never have … &lt;strong&gt;enough&lt;/strong&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make money they didn’t have and didn’t need, they risked what they did have and did need. And that’s foolish. It is just plain foolish. If you risk something that is important to you for something that is unimportant to you, it just does not make any sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-confounding-compounding&quot;&gt;4. Confounding Compounding&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;815-billions-of-buffets-845-billion-net-worth-came-after-his-65th-birthday&quot;&gt;$81.5 billions of Buffet’s $84.5 billion net worth came after his 65th birthday&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not “growth” or “brains” or “insight.” The ability to stick around for a long time, without wiping out or being forced to give up, is what makes the biggest difference. This should be the cornerstone of your strategy, whether it’s in investing or your career or a business you own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t need tremendous force to create tremendous results. If something compounds—if a little growth serves as the fuel for future growth—a small starting base can lead to results so extraordinary they seem to defy logic. It can be so logic-defying that you underestimate what’s possible, where growth comes from, and what it can lead to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-getting-wealthy-vs-staying-wealthy&quot;&gt;5. Getting Wealthy vs. Staying Wealthy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;good-investing-is-not-necessarily-about-making-good-decisions-its-about-consistently-not-screwing-up&quot;&gt;Good investing is not necessarily about making good decisions. It’s about consistently not screwing up&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can spend years trying to figure out how Buffett achieved his investment returns: how he found the best companies, the cheapest stocks, the best managers. That’s hard. Less hard but equally important is pointing out what he didn’t do. He didn’t get carried away with debt. He didn’t panic and sell during the 14 recessions he’s lived through. He didn’t sully his business reputation. He didn’t attach himself to one strategy, one world view, or one passing trend. He didn’t rely on others’ money (managing investments through a public company meant investors couldn’t withdraw their capital). He didn’t burn himself out and quit or retire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;6-tails-you-win&quot;&gt;6. Tails, You Win&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;you-can-be-wrong-half-the-time-and-still-make-a-fortune&quot;&gt;You can be wrong half the time and still make a fortune&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The great investors bought vast quantities of art,” the firm writes.¹⁹ “A subset of the collections turned out to be great investments, and they were held for a sufficiently long period of time to allow the portfolio return to converge upon the return of the best elements in the portfolio. That’s all that happens.” The great art dealers operated like index funds. They bought everything they could. And they bought it in portfolios, not individual pieces they happened to like. Then they sat and waited for a few winners to emerge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;J.P. Morgan Asset Management once published the distribution of returns for the Russell 3000 Index—a big, broad, collection of public companies—since 1980.²¹ Forty percent of all Russell 3000 stock components lost at least 70% of their value and never recovered over this period. Effectively all of the index’s overall returns came from 7% of component companies that outperformed by at least two standard deviations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Napoleon’s definition of a military genius was, “The man who can do the average thing when all those around him are going crazy.” It’s the same in investing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;7-freedom&quot;&gt;7. Freedom&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;controlling-your-time-is-the-highest-dividend-money-pays&quot;&gt;Controlling your time is the highest dividend money pays&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The highest form of wealth is the ability to wake up every morning and say, “I can do whatever I want today.” People want to become wealthier to make them happier. Happiness is a complicated subject because everyone’s different. But if there’s a common denominator in happiness—a universal fuel of joy—it’s that people want to control their lives. The ability to do what you want, when you want, with who you want, for as long as you want, is priceless. It is the highest dividend money pays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his book 30 Lessons for Living, gerontologist Karl Pillemer interviewed a thousand elderly Americans looking for the most important lessons they learned from decades of life experience. He wrote: No one—not a single person out of a thousand—said that to be happy you should try to work as hard as you can to make money to buy the things you want. No one—not a single person—said it’s important to be at least as wealthy as the people around you, and if you have more than they do it’s real success. No one—not a single person—said you should choose your work based on your desired future earning power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What they did value were things like quality friendships, being part of something bigger than themselves, and spending quality, unstructured time with their children. “Your kids don’t want your money (or what your money buys) anywhere near as much as they want you. Specifically, they want you with them,” Pillemer writes. Take it from those who have lived through everything: Controlling your time is the highest dividend money pays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;8-man-in-the-car-paradox&quot;&gt;8. Man in the Car Paradox&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;no-one-is-impressed-with-your-possessions-as-much-as-you-are&quot;&gt;No one is impressed with your possessions as much as you are&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You might think you want an expensive car, a fancy watch, and a huge house. But I’m telling you, you don’t. What you want is respect and admiration from other people, and you think having expensive stuff will bring it. It almost never does—especially from the people you want to respect and admire you.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;9-wealth-is-what-you-dont-see&quot;&gt;9. Wealth is What You Don’t See&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;spending-money-to-show-people-how-much-money-you-have-is-the-fastest-way-to-have-less-money&quot;&gt;Spending money to show people how much money you have is the fastest way to have less money&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only way to be wealthy is to not spend the money that you do have. It’s not just the only way to accumulate wealth; it’s the very definition of wealth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But wealth is hidden. It’s income not spent. Wealth is an option not yet taken to buy something later. Its value lies in offering you options, flexibility, and growth to one day purchase more stuff than you could right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exercise is like being rich. You think, “I did the work and I now deserve to treat myself to a big meal.” Wealth is turning down that treat meal and actually burning net calories. It’s hard, and requires self-control. But it creates a gap between what you could do and what you choose to do that accrues to you over time. The problem for many of us is that it is easy to find rich role models. It’s harder to find wealthy ones because by definition their success is more hidden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;10-save-money&quot;&gt;10. Save Money&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-only-factor-you-can-control-generates-one-of-the-only-things-that-matter-how-wonderful&quot;&gt;The only factor you can control generates one of the only things that matter. How wonderful&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you define savings as the gap between your ego and your income you realize why many people with decent incomes save so little. It’s a daily struggle against instincts to extend your peacock feathers to their outermost limits and keep up with others doing the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t need a specific reason to save.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;11-reasonable--rational&quot;&gt;11. Reasonable &amp;gt; Rational&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;aiming-to-be-mostly-reasonable-works-better-than-trying-to-be-coldly-rational&quot;&gt;Aiming to be mostly reasonable works better than trying to be coldly rational&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rational investor makes decisions based on numeric facts. A reasonable investor makes them in a conference room surrounded by co-workers you want to think highly of you, with a spouse you don’t want to let down, or judged against the silly but realistic competitors that are your brother-in-law, your neighbor, and your own personal doubts. Investing has a social component that’s often ignored when viewed through a strictly financial lens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are few financial variables more correlated to performance than commitment to a strategy during its lean years—both the amount of performance and the odds of capturing it over a given period of time. The historical odds of making money in U.S. markets are 50/50 over one-day periods, 68% in one-year periods, 88% in 10-year periods, and (so far) 100% in 20-year periods. Anything that keeps you in the game has a quantifiable advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;12-surprise&quot;&gt;12. Surprise!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;history-is-the-study-of-hange-ironically-used-as-a-map-of-the-future&quot;&gt;History is the study of hange, ironically used as a map of the future&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The further back in history you look, the more general your takeaways should be. General things like people’s relationship to greed and fear, how they behave under stress, and how they respond to incentives tend to be stable in time. The history of money is useful for that kind of stuff. But specific trends, specific trades, specific sectors, specific causal relationships about markets, and what people should do with their money are always an example of evolution in progress. Historians are not prophets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;13-room-for-error&quot;&gt;13. Room for Error&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-most-important-part-of-every-plan-is-planning-on-your-plan-not-going-according-to-plan&quot;&gt;The most important part of every plan is planning on your plan not going according to plan&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Benjamin Graham is known for his concept of margin of safety. He wrote about it extensively and in mathematical detail. But my favorite summary of the theory came when he mentioned in an interview that “the purpose of the margin of safety is to render the forecast unnecessary.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Room for error lets you endure a range of potential outcomes, and endurance lets you stick around long enough to let the odds of benefiting from a low-probability outcome fall in your favor. The biggest gains occur infrequently, either because they don’t happen often or because they take time to compound. So the person with enough room for error in part of their strategy (cash) to let them endure hardship in another (stocks) has an edge over the person who gets wiped out, game over, insert more tokens, when they’re wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most important part of every plan is planning on your plan not going according to plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;14-youll-change&quot;&gt;14. You’ll Change&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;long-term-planning-is-harder-than-it-seems-because-peoples-goals-and-desires-change-over-time&quot;&gt;Long-term planning is harder than it seems because people’s goals and desires change over time&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An underpinning of psychology is that people are poor forecasters of their future selves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compounding works best when you can give a plan years or decades to grow. This is true for not only savings but careers and relationships. Endurance is key. And when you consider our tendency to change who we are over time, balance at every point in your life becomes a strategy to avoid future regret and encourage endurance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sunk costs—anchoring decisions to past efforts that can’t be refunded—are a devil in a world where people change over time. They make our future selves prisoners to our past, different, selves. It’s the equivalent of a stranger making major life decisions for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;15-nothings-free&quot;&gt;15. Nothing’s Free&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;everything-has-a-price-but-not-all-prices-appear-on-labels&quot;&gt;Everything has a price, but not all prices appear on labels&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like everything else worthwhile, successful investing demands a price. But its currency is not dollars and cents. It’s volatility, fear, doubt, uncertainty, and regret—all of which are easy to overlook until you’re dealing with them in real time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people in investing choose the third option. Like a car thief—though well-meaning and law-abiding—they form tricks and strategies to get the return without paying the price. They trade in and out. They attempt to sell before the next recession and buy before the next boom. Most investors with even a little experience know that volatility is real and common. Many then take what seems like the next logical step: trying to avoid it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;sounds trivial, but thinking of market volatility as a fee rather than a fine is an important part of developing the kind of mindset that lets you stick around long enough for investing gains to work in your favor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The volatility/uncertainty fee—the price of returns—is the cost of admission to get returns greater than low-fee parks like cash and bonds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Morningstar once looked at the performance of tactical mutual funds, whose strategy is to switch between stocks and bonds at opportune times, capturing market returns with lower downside risk.⁵⁰ They want the returns without paying the price. The study focused on the mid-2010 through late 2011 period, when U.S. stock markets went wild on fears of a new recession and the S&amp;amp;P 500 declined more than 20%. This is the exact kind of environment the tactical funds are supposed to work in. It was their moment to shine. There were, by Morningstar’s count, 112 tactical mutual funds during this period. Only nine had better risk-adjusted returns than a simple 60/40 stock-bond fund. Less than a quarter of the tactical funds had smaller maximum drawdowns than the leave-it-alone index. Morningstar wrote: “With a few exceptions, [tactical funds] gained less, were more volatile, or were subject to just as much downside risk” as the hands-off fund.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;16-you--me&quot;&gt;16. You &amp;amp; Me&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;beware-taking-financial-cues-from-people-playing-a-different-game-than-you-are&quot;&gt;Beware taking financial cues from people playing a different game than you are&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bubbles form when the momentum of short-term returns attracts enough money that the makeup of investors shifts from mostly long term to mostly short term. That process feeds on itself. As traders push up short-term returns, they attract even more traders. Before long—and it often doesn’t take long—the dominant market price-setters with the most authority are those with shorter time horizons. Bubbles aren’t so much about valuations rising. That’s just a symptom of something else: time horizons shrinking as more short-term traders enter the playing field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to grasp that other investors have different goals than we do, because an anchor of psychology is not realizing that rational people can see the world through a different lens than your own. Rising prices persuade all investors in ways the best marketers envy. They are a drug that can turn value-conscious investors into dewy-eyed optimists, detached from their own reality by the actions of someone playing a different game than they are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A takeaway here is that few things matter more with money than understanding your own time horizon and not being persuaded by the actions and behaviors of people playing different games than you are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;17-the-seduction-of-pessimism&quot;&gt;17. The Seduction of Pessimism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;optimism-sounds-like-a-sales-pitch-pessimism-sounds-like-someone-trying-to-help-you&quot;&gt;Optimism sounds like a sales pitch. Pessimism sounds like someone trying to help you&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pessimism just sounds smarter and more plausible than optimism. Tell someone that everything will be great and they’re likely to either shrug you off or offer a skeptical eye. Tell someone they’re in danger and you have their undivided attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;18-when-youll-believe-anything&quot;&gt;18. When You’ll Believe Anything&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;appealing-functions-and-why-stories-are-more-powerful-than-statistics&quot;&gt;Appealing functions, and why stories are more powerful than statistics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many things in life that we think are true because we desperately want them to be true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take Bernie Madoff. In hindsight his Ponzi scheme should have been obvious. He reported returns that never varied, they were audited by a relatively unknown accounting firm, and he refused to release much information on how the returns were achieved. Yet Madoff raised billions of dollars from some of the most sophisticated investors in the world. He told a good story, and people wanted to believe it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bigger the gap between what you want to be true and what you need to be true to have an acceptable outcome, the more you are protecting yourself from falling victim to an appealing financial fiction. When&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;19-all-together-now&quot;&gt;19. All Together Now&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-weve-learned-about-the-psychology-of-your-own-money&quot;&gt;What we’ve learned about the psychology of your own money&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This chapter is just a summary of all the previous points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Less ego, more wealth. Saving money is the gap between your ego and your income, and wealth is what you don’t see. So wealth is created by suppressing what you could buy today in order to have more stuff or more options in the future. No matter how much you earn, you will never build wealth unless you can put a lid on how much fun you can have with your money right now, today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Achieving some level of independence does not rely on earning a doctor’s income. It’s mostly a matter of keeping your expectations in check and living below your means. Independence, at any income level, is driven by your savings rate. And past a certain level of income your savings rate is driven by your ability to keep your lifestyle expectations from running away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;20-confessions&quot;&gt;20. Confessions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the final chapter, Morgan goes over what he and his family do with money. How do they manage it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We own our house without a mortgage, which is the worst financial decision we’ve ever made but the best money decision we’ve ever made. Mortgage interest rates were absurdly low when we bought our house. Any rational advisor would recommend taking advantage of cheap money and investing extra savings in higher-return assets, like stocks. But our goal isn’t to be coldly rational; just psychologically reasonable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every investor should pick a strategy that has the highest odds of successfully meeting their goals. And I think for most investors, dollar-cost averaging into a low-cost index fund will provide the highest odds of long-term success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t need to be more complicated than that for us. I like it simple. &lt;strong&gt;One of my deeply held investing beliefs is that there is little correlation between investment effort and investment results.&lt;/strong&gt; The reason is because the world is driven by tails—a few variables account for the majority of returns. No matter how hard you try at investing you won’t do well if you miss the two or three things that move the needle in your strategy. The reverse is true. Simple investment strategies can work great as long as they capture the few things that are important to that strategy’s success. &lt;strong&gt;My investing strategy doesn’t rely on picking the right sector, or timing the next recession. It relies on a high savings rate, patience, and optimism that the global economy will create value over the next several decades. I spend virtually all of my investing effort thinking about those three things—especially the first two, which I can control.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do you think? Do you agree with the author? Does psychology play an important role when talking about money?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Juan Pallarès</name><email>juan@pallares.me</email></author><category term="books" /><category term="psychology" /><category term="money" /><category term="FIRE" /><category term="hapiness" /><category term="wealth" /><category term="greed" /><summary type="html">Your savings are the gap between your ego and your income.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="es"><title type="html">Lebron James tiene sobrepeso - Mide mejor tu evolución física</title><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/lebron-james-tiene-sobrepeso-mide-mejor-evolucion-fisica/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lebron James tiene sobrepeso - Mide mejor tu evolución física" /><published>2021-02-27T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-02-27T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://juan.pallares.me/lebron-james-tiene-sobrepeso-mide-mejor-evolucion-fisica</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://juan.pallares.me/lebron-james-tiene-sobrepeso-mide-mejor-evolucion-fisica/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/lebronjames.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Lebron James mostrando músculo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Con 2,06m y 113kg, el IMC (Índice de Masa Corporal) del cuatro veces campeón de la NBA indica que tiene sobrepeso. Personalmente no le veo sobrepeso por ningún sitio, sobrepeso de éxitos deportivos si me apuras.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/IMCLebron.png&quot; alt=&quot;IMC Lebron James&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;En todas las revisiones de salud anuales típicas del trabajo me han dado el valor de IMC. ¿Veis esta medida creíble? ¿Útil? Para mi es demasiado general y puede llegar a confundirte en algunos casos. Después de esta introducción que coquetea con el clickbait, voy a explicar cómo creo que es mejor medir la evolución física.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;no-quieres-bajar-peso-quieres-bajar-grasa&quot;&gt;No quieres bajar peso, quieres bajar grasa&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Es muy común pesarse y si se va bajando de peso asumir que estamos en el buen camino. Grave error. &lt;strong&gt;Te interesa perder grasa pero no músculo&lt;/strong&gt;, o al menos perder el mínimo posible. Si haces un dieta estricta con poca proteína y casi sin entrenar fuerza es la receta perfecta para perder mucho músculo y grasa. Además el músculo es muy fácil perderlo, es caro de mantener. Tu cuerpo si nota que no lo usas te lo quita. La grasa tarda mucho más en irse, son tus reservas en caso de ausencia de comida, no las cosumirá hasta que le obligues de verdad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Esto lo se porque lo he experimentado yo mismo. Desde el 2014 me voy pesando semanalmente (hay temporadas que se me pasa pero en general lo hago) y fué ese primer año que bajé bastante de peso y para mi era un exitazo&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/201480kg.png&quot; alt=&quot;80kg septiembre 2014&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3 años después si solo me fijo en el peso estoy igual. Pero realmente estaba en un estado de forma mucho mejor, ¿cómo puedo saberlo?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/201780kg.png&quot; alt=&quot;80kg marzo 2017&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;como-mido-la-grasa&quot;&gt;Como mido la grasa?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Medir la grasa de forma precisa es bastante difícil&lt;/strong&gt;. Las básculas que dan el porcentaje de grasa tienen mucho margen de error, es solo una aproximación. Puedes probar también con un adipómetro pero es un proceso tedioso y también poco preciso. Hay formas precisa de medirla pero es con máquinas especializadas y por un elevador precio. ¿Qué uso yo? algo mucho más sencillo, &lt;strong&gt;mido la cintura a la altura del ombligo y el pecho a la altura del pezón&lt;/strong&gt;. Ya esta, eso es todo. Acumulamos mucha grasa en el abdomen, si tenemos menos cintura que pecho, estamos en la buena dirección. Veamos los pesos anteriores acompañados de las medidas:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/201480kgCompleto.png&quot; alt=&quot;80kg septiembre 2014 con medidas&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/201780kgCompleto.png&quot; alt=&quot;80kg marzo 2017 con medidas&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ignora las medidas extras (biceps, butlock, thigh), en 2017 tenía más pecho (2,5cm) y menos cintura (4,5cm), estaba mucho mejor. &lt;strong&gt;Para tener un solo número de referencia de mi evolución física, hago la resta entre pecho y cintura&lt;/strong&gt; para calcular los “Johans”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fórmula&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Pecho - Cintura = Johans&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ejemplo:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;103,5 - 83,5 = 20&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cuánto más alto son los Johans mejor, más forma de V. No sabía como llamarlo y se quedo con este nickname de la infancia 🤣.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Es muy importante pesarse y medirse en las mismas condiciones siempre.&lt;/strong&gt; Yo suelo hacerlo el sábado o el domingo justo después de levantarme. Por favor, no es pongais a tomar medidas después de una comilona, un super entreno, etc. Os estáreis autoengañando. Tampoco va bien pesarse diariamente, el peso oscila mucho según como de hidratamos estamos, tránsito intestinal, etc. &lt;strong&gt;Te interesa la evolución general.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Una vez ya tienes controladas esas medidas, si quieres dar un paso más puedes medir otras partes. La clave es tener una referencia clara donde medir para que siempre midas en el mismo lugar, en el caso de cintura y pectoral es fácil. Para medir el muslo ya no lo es tanto, ojo con eso. No te pierdas en el detalle, las relevantes son esas dos, las otras son un extra. Por ejemplo, tengo últimamente el objetivo de ganar músculo en las piernas, en este caso si tiene valor medirlas para ver evolución.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Un muy buen complemento a las medidas/peso es una foto. El espejo no miente&lt;/strong&gt;. Una foto en el mismo lugar y condiciones (la puedes hacer justo después de medirte) sin camiseta te puede ayudar a mucho a ver evolución visual. Guardas todas las fotos en el mismo lugar (en mi caso álbum de Google Photos) y luego comparar es fácil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bondades-del-tracking&quot;&gt;Bondades del Tracking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://juan.pallares.me/atomic-habits-james-clear/&quot;&gt;Hacer tracking de un hábito puede ayudarte a mantenerlo&lt;/a&gt;. En este caso además, puede motivarte y llevarte en la buena dirección. Quizá no pierdes peso porque estas ganando algo de músculo, pero te obsesionas por no ver bajar ese número y dejas de comer todo lo que deberías, si haces un tracking correcto no caerás en ese error.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Me encanta tener datos históricos, luego puedes hacer gráficos muy interesantes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/graficoPesoCintura.png&quot; alt=&quot;Grafico evolucion peso-cintura&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;En este gráfico comparo la evolución del peso y de la cintura. Se puede apreciar como en 2014 bajé peso pero no lo hice del todo bien, en 2017 decidí tomar el control de la alimentación (leer &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.es/Fitness-revolucionario-Lecciones-ancestrales-Singulares/dp/8441540195/ref=sr_1_1?__mk_es_ES=%C3%85M%C3%85%C5%BD%C3%95%C3%91&amp;amp;crid=F387RQSNTRQP&amp;amp;dchild=1&amp;amp;keywords=fitness+revolucionario&amp;amp;qid=1610232623&amp;amp;sprefix=fitness+revo,aps,169&amp;amp;sr=8-1&quot;&gt;Fitness Revolucionario&lt;/a&gt; esa Navidad fué clave) y bajé bastante de peso (sobretodo grasa) aunque ese mismo verano tuve una apendicitis que ya me remató y quedé un poco esquelético. Pude remontar y he venido manteniendo una cintura baja comparada a tiempos pre 2017. Idealmente, me gustaría subir peso sin subir cintura (o que suba muy poco) eso indicaría que estoy ganando sobretodo músculo, lo que me lleva a la conclusión.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusión&quot;&gt;Conclusión&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Si me preguntan &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;- ¿Cúal es tu peso ideal?&lt;/code&gt; mi respuesta sería &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;- No me importa mucho, pero quisiera tener 10% de grasa o menos&lt;/code&gt;.
Si me preguntan por el IMC pues puedo decir que mejor que el de Lebron y luego recomendarles este artículo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TL;DR Te interesa perder grasa, no peso&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;posts-recomendados&quot;&gt;Posts recomendados&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recomiendo estos posts concretos y blogs en general para ir más al detalle:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fitnessrevolucionario.com/perdida-de-grasa/&quot;&gt;Pérdida de grasa&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fitnessrevolucionario.com/2012/02/26/fuerza-la-base-de-todo/&quot;&gt;Fuerza, la base de todo&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nerdfitness.com/blog/body-fat-percentage/&quot;&gt;Body fat percentage&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nerdfitness.com/blog/strength-training-101/&quot;&gt;Strength Training 101&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Juan Pallarès</name><email>juan@pallares.me</email></author><category term="health" /><category term="salud" /><category term="sport" /><category term="fitness" /><category term="imc" /><category term="bmi" /><category term="training" /><category term="tracking" /><summary type="html">Mide mejor tu evolución física fijándote en lo que realmente importa.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Serverless common issues and errors</title><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/serverless-common-issues-and-errors/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Serverless common issues and errors" /><published>2021-01-23T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-01-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://juan.pallares.me/serverless-common-issues-and-errors</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://juan.pallares.me/serverless-common-issues-and-errors/">&lt;p&gt;At my job, we have had recurring issues with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.serverless.com/&quot;&gt;serverless&lt;/a&gt; that have slowed down us frequently. This guide aims to avoid that by compiling the main pain points we have experienced. Keep in mind we use AWS and Gitlab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;avoid-gitlab-protected-variables&quot;&gt;Avoid gitlab protected variables&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When configuring Serverless to be deployed from Gitlab CI/CD. &lt;strong&gt;Remember to not set AWS env variables as protected&lt;/strong&gt; (default option) since it will make the deployment fail and &lt;strong&gt;it won’t give you a meaningful error&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/gitlabProtectedVariables.png&quot; alt=&quot;Gitlab protected variables&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;serverless-offline-plugins-order-is-important&quot;&gt;Serverless offline plugins order is important&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plugins order in serverless.yml matters. Rule of thumb, &lt;strong&gt;serverless offline should be always one of the latest&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/PluginsOrder.png&quot; alt=&quot;Plugins Order&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;serverless-custom-domain&quot;&gt;Serverless custom domain&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To configure the deployment to sandbox and to production AWS in custom domain you can use the plugin &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/serverless-domain-manager&quot;&gt;serverless-domain-manager&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Keep in mind, before being able to deploy you have to call (only once per domain)&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sls create_domain --aws-profile LAT-serverless-cheetah-bff --stage production&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key point is specifying the stage when deploying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;serverless deploy --stage staging&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;using-aws-credentials-locally&quot;&gt;Using AWS credentials locally&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check the file in ~/.aws. There you should configure different credentials depending on the IAM user/AWS account. If no profile is called, the default will be used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/AWSaccessKey.png&quot; alt=&quot;AWS Access Key&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then later you can use them like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sls deploy --stage production --aws-profile LAT-serverless-cheetah-bff&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;serverless-dynamodb-locally&quot;&gt;Serverless DynamoDB Locally&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two plugins are needed &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/99x/serverless-dynamodb-local&quot;&gt;serverless-dynamodb-local&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/serverless-dynamodb-client&quot;&gt;serverless-dynamodb-client&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;strong&gt;After installing the packages the normal way. You have to install it to serverless&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sls dynamodb install&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then to make it work we used to terminals. In one we run &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sls dynamodb start --migrate&lt;/code&gt;, in the second one we run &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sls offline&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;serverless-dotenv---environment-variables&quot;&gt;Serverless Dotenv - Environment variables&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To use environment variables locally, &lt;strong&gt;do not use dotenv package&lt;/strong&gt;. Use &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.serverless.com/plugins/serverless-dotenv-plugin&quot;&gt;serverless-dotenv-plugin&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;import-issues---failure-xxxxxxdefault-is-not-a-constructor&quot;&gt;Import issues - Failure: xxxxxx.default is not a constructor&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only way we could fix this issue was doing require instead of import. Most probably an issue with not properly configured &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;tsconfig.json&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the problematic imports use:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;const pLimit = require('p-limit');&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;instead of&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;import pLimit from 'p-limit';&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;include-json-files-in-build&quot;&gt;Include JSON files in build&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If using typescript and JSON files, you will need to include this files so they are copied to the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.build&lt;/code&gt; folder in the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;serverless.yml&lt;/code&gt; file:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;package:
    include:
        - localizations/\*.json
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you experienced any other issue? My main concern is that the errors messages are not clear enough.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Juan Pallarès</name><email>juan@pallares.me</email></author><category term="serverless" /><category term="issues" /><category term="common" /><category term="errors" /><summary type="html">protected variables, custom domains, plugins order, using it locally...</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="es"><title type="html">Balance 2020</title><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/balance-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Balance 2020" /><published>2021-01-03T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-01-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://juan.pallares.me/balance-2020</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://juan.pallares.me/balance-2020/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;mirando-el-lado-positivo&quot;&gt;Mirando el lado positivo&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Es común reflexionar al final del año de como ha ido todo, hacer un balance. Por lo general, con la pandemia ha sido un año horroroso pero aún así hay que intentar sacar siempre lo positivo. Ahí van algunas reflexiones aleatorias:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Soy más social de lo que me pensaba, el confinamiento y el trabajo remoto me ha hecho extrañar mucho la oficina y las relaciones sociales que se crean allí.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Por otro lado, cuando te vas adaptando y no estas confinado, el trabajo remoto da mucha flexibilidad y lo empiezas a apreciar/disfrutar.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Me cuesta una barbaridad entrenar en casa. El tipo de entremientos que me gustan son estilo crossfit o directamente barra y kg. Sin pesos y con la única compañia de la pareja y/o vecino ha sido difícil. Aún así he seguido entrenando y trackeando el progreso. Además he probado el plan de entrenamiento 5/3/1 y lo he incorporado junto al crossfit.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Empecé este año a invertir de forma indexada, justo un año que la economía se ha hundido pero por suerte he acabado con un 10% de rentabilidad, nada mal. Ya dedicaré un post a esto y las causas principales, seguramente cuando haga el rebalanceo anual.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;He vuelto a adquirir el hábito de la lectura, &lt;a href=&quot;https://juan.pallares.me/books/&quot;&gt;varios libros leídos&lt;/a&gt; más uno in progress (no hago una entrada sobre todos).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;También he vuelto a escribir en este blog. 17 nuevas entradas este año, empezando en abril. Sin target claro, temas variadísimos, la única meta: escribir con frecuencia.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Es obvio pero no deja de sorpredener la cantidad de dinero ahorrado cuando no puedes salir de casa y el único gasto es comer. Ayuda a poner en perspectiva la importancia de según que gastos.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;las-entradas-más-vistas&quot;&gt;Las entradas más vistas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No tengo ningún objetivo definido a nivel de número de visitas, tráfico del blog, etc. pero si me gusta mirar estadísticas. Vamos a repasar los reports de Google Analytics:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/mostVisitedPages.png&quot; alt=&quot;Most visited pages&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aparte de la pagina principal, las dos entrada más visitadas en 2020 son:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://juan.pallares.me/configure-jekyll-multi-language-without-plugin/&quot;&gt;Configure Jekyll to be multi-language without plugins&lt;/a&gt; y su &lt;a href=&quot;https://juan.pallares.me/configura-jekyll-multi-idioma-sin-plugin/&quot;&gt;version en castellano&lt;/a&gt; es la cuarta. Esto me lo podía medio imaginar, no hay una forma fácil/clara de hacer jekyll multidioma y mucha gente interesada en hacerlo.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://juan.pallares.me/no-funciona-intellisense-en-sql-server/&quot;&gt;No funciona Intellisense en SQL Server Management Studio 2008&lt;/a&gt;. Esta si que sorprende más. &lt;strong&gt;Es una entrada del 2012!&lt;/strong&gt; y &lt;a href=&quot;https://juan.pallares.me/moving-to-jekyll/&quot;&gt;la migré del antiguo blog en Blogger&lt;/a&gt; de casualidad. Obviamente las visitas llegan todas via Google (nadie llega a las quinta página) y deduzco que la causa de tantas visitas es que el título tiene muy buen SEO y es un problema que necesita solución aún en 2020. Nunca imaginé que una entrada tan chorra estaría como la segunda más visitada.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Si ignoramos books, que es un apartado más que una entrada llegamos a &lt;a href=&quot;https://juan.pallares.me/raspberry-pi-autodownloader/&quot;&gt;Raspberry Pi autodownloader&lt;/a&gt;. Esta entrada con mejor título sería más visitada seguramente pero bueno aún así tiene el tercer puesto siendo una entrada de 2017.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;desde-donde-llegan-las-visitas&quot;&gt;Desde donde llegan las visitas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suelo poner un link a cada nueva entrada en Twitter y en LinkedIn. Aún así, la mayoría de visitas vienen via organic search, es decir, búsquedas en Google.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/usersOrigin.png&quot; alt=&quot;Visitors source&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Por último, como curiosidad, parece que la inmensa mayoría de visitas vienen de España seguidos por USA. Un saludo para los lectores chinos! 🤣&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/countryOfOrigin.png&quot; alt=&quot;Visitors country of origin&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Juan Pallarès</name><email>juan@pallares.me</email></author><category term="year" /><category term="analysis" /><category term="popular posts" /><summary type="html">Lo más leído del año</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Book - Atomic Habits - James Clear</title><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/atomic-habits-james-clear/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Book - Atomic Habits - James Clear" /><published>2020-12-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-12-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://juan.pallares.me/atomic-habits-james-clear</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://juan.pallares.me/atomic-habits-james-clear/">&lt;p&gt;2021 is starting soon and with it the usual new year resolutions. &lt;em&gt;I’m going to eat healthier&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;I’m going to the gym this year for sure!&lt;/em&gt;. Once March arrives no resolution has survived. Why is it so difficult to create healthy habits? New habits in general?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.es/Atomic-Habits-Proven-Build-Break/dp/1847941834&quot;&gt;Atomic Habits&lt;/a&gt; is the answer. A book that even if most things that are mentioned can be obvious I couldn’t stop highlighting interesting quotes. It took me a month to read but could have been days. It starts every chapter with a story that captures your attention and it is used as an example of the concept that is going to be explained and then closed with a summary, something my engineer/order freak mind loves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;compound-interest&quot;&gt;Compound interest&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Compound Interest concept is mainly used in economic terms, &lt;a href=&quot;http://pallares.me/why-i-became-a-bogglehead/&quot;&gt;when investing long-term&lt;/a&gt; is one of the keys for having great benefits. But the concept can be applied to almost everything and in this book it’s applied to self-improvement, acquiring good habits. That’s why with tiny changes you get remarkable results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/compoundinterest.png&quot; alt=&quot;Compound Interest Diagram&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cue---craving---response---reward&quot;&gt;Cue -&amp;gt; Craving -&amp;gt; Response -&amp;gt; Reward&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are 4 steps involved in any habit:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;cue&lt;/strong&gt; is about &lt;strong&gt;noticing&lt;/strong&gt; the reward.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;craving&lt;/strong&gt; is about &lt;strong&gt;wanting&lt;/strong&gt; the reward.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;response&lt;/strong&gt; is about &lt;strong&gt;obtaining&lt;/strong&gt; the reward.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We chase &lt;strong&gt;rewards&lt;/strong&gt; because they serve two purposes: (1) they &lt;strong&gt;satisfy&lt;/strong&gt; us and (2) they &lt;strong&gt;teach&lt;/strong&gt; us.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To improve the way we manage habits, we need to work with these 4 steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-is-it-so-difficult-to-change-our-habits&quot;&gt;Why is it so difficult to change our habits?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Changing our habits is challenging for two reasons: (1) we try to change the wrong thing and (2) we try to change our habits in the wrong way. If you want better results, then forget about setting goals. Focus on your system instead. Focus on your identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outcomes are about what you get. Processes are about what you do. Identity is about what you believe. We usually say, &lt;em&gt;“I’ll do sport every day”&lt;/em&gt; instead it should be &lt;em&gt;“I’m a fit person”&lt;/em&gt;. The focus is who we wish to become.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/LayersOfBehaviorChange.png&quot; alt=&quot;Layers of Behavior Change Diagram&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of acting from the outside to the inside. We have to create our identity and it will change the outer layers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/IdentityBasedHabits.png&quot; alt=&quot;Identity-Based Habits Diagram&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we have an identity, it will be very conflicting for us to act against it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-create-a-good-habit---4-laws-of-behavioral-change&quot;&gt;How to create a Good Habit - 4 Laws of behavioral change&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For creating a good habit, we have to use the 4 Laws of behavioral change.
&lt;strong&gt;Make it obvious, attractive, easy and satisfying.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cardinal Rule of Behavior Change: What is rewarded is repeated. What is punished is avoided. You learn what to do in the future based on what you were rewarded for doing (or punished for doing) in the past. Positive emotions cultivate habits. Negative emotions destroy them.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Add a little bit of immediate pleasure to the habits that pay off in the long-run and a little bit of immediate pain to ones that don’t.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I’m going to copy-paste the final version of the summary that James Clear creates after every chapter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1st Law: Make it &lt;strong&gt;obvious&lt;/strong&gt;.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1.1 Fill out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/jamesclear/Atomic+Habits/The+Habits+Scorecard.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Habits Scorecard&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Write down your current habits to become aware of them.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1.2 Use &lt;strong&gt;implementation intentions&lt;/strong&gt;: “I will [BEHAVIOR] at [TIME] in [LOCATION].”&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1.3 Use &lt;strong&gt;habit stacking&lt;/strong&gt;: “After [CURRENT HABIT], I will [NEW HABIT].”&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1.4 Design your &lt;strong&gt;environment&lt;/strong&gt;. Make the cues of good habits obvious and visible.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2nd Law: Make it &lt;strong&gt;attractive&lt;/strong&gt;.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2.1 Use &lt;strong&gt;temptation bundling&lt;/strong&gt;. Pair an action you want to do with an action you need to do.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2.2 Join a &lt;strong&gt;culture&lt;/strong&gt; where your desired behavior is the normal behavior.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2.3 Create a &lt;strong&gt;motivation ritual&lt;/strong&gt;. Do something you enjoy immediately before a difficult habit.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;3rd Law: Make it &lt;strong&gt;easy&lt;/strong&gt;.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;3.1 &lt;strong&gt;Reduce friction&lt;/strong&gt;. Decrease the number of steps between you and your good habits.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;3.2 Prime the &lt;strong&gt;environment&lt;/strong&gt;. Prepare your environment to make future actions easier.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;3.3 &lt;strong&gt;Master the decisive moment&lt;/strong&gt;. Optimize the small choices that deliver outsized impact.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;3.4 Use the &lt;strong&gt;Two-Minute Rule&lt;/strong&gt;. Downscale your habits until they can be done in two minutes or less.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;3.5 &lt;strong&gt;Automate&lt;/strong&gt; your habits. Invest in technology and onetime purchases that lock in future behavior.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;4th Law: Make it &lt;strong&gt;satisfying&lt;/strong&gt;.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;4.1 Use &lt;strong&gt;reinforcement&lt;/strong&gt;. Give yourself an immediate reward when you complete your habit.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;4.2 Make “doing nothing” enjoyable. When avoiding a bad habit, design a way to see the benefits.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;4.3 Use a &lt;strong&gt;habit tracker&lt;/strong&gt;. Keep track of your habit streak and “don’t break the chain.”.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;4.4 &lt;strong&gt;Never miss twice&lt;/strong&gt;. When you forget to do a habit, make sure you get back on track immediately.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the book, it goes over all these laws and explains with examples how to do it and why it’s useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;quitting-bad-habits&quot;&gt;Quitting bad Habits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also explains how to quit bad habits, as you guessed is doing the opposite actions you do for acquiring good habits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inversion of the 1st Law: Make it &lt;strong&gt;invisible&lt;/strong&gt;.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1.5 &lt;strong&gt;Reduce exposure&lt;/strong&gt;. Remove the cues of your bad habits from your environment.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inversion of the 2nd Law: Make it &lt;strong&gt;unattractive&lt;/strong&gt;.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2.4 &lt;strong&gt;Reframe your mind-set&lt;/strong&gt;. Highlight the benefits of avoiding your bad habits.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inversion of the 3rd Law: Make it &lt;strong&gt;difficult&lt;/strong&gt;.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;3.6 &lt;strong&gt;Increase friction&lt;/strong&gt;. Increase the number of steps between you and your bad habits.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;3.7 Use a &lt;strong&gt;commitment device&lt;/strong&gt;. Restrict your future choices to the ones that benefit you.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inversion of the 4th Law: Make it &lt;strong&gt;unsatisfying&lt;/strong&gt;.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;4.5 Get an &lt;strong&gt;accountability partner&lt;/strong&gt;. Ask someone to watch your behavior.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;4.6 Create a &lt;strong&gt;habit contract&lt;/strong&gt;. Make the costs of your bad habits public and painful.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;powerful-concepts&quot;&gt;Powerful concepts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I’m gonna go over some quotes that I liked specially from the book. &lt;a href=&quot;https://juan.pallares.me/books/atomic-habits-tiny-changes-remarkable-results/&quot;&gt;Find all the quotes here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;no-freedom-will-i-become-a-robot&quot;&gt;No freedom? Will I become a robot?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people can be concerned with all these habits, it seems to be too much planning, no room for improvising? being original?:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Such questions set up a false dichotomy. They make you think that you have to choose between building habits and attaining freedom. In reality, the two complement each other. Habits do not restrict freedom. They create it. In fact, the people who don’t have their habits handled are often the ones with the least amount of freedom. Without good financial habits, you will always be struggling for the next dollar. Without good health habits, you will always seem to be short on energy. Without good learning habits, you will always feel like you’re behind the curve.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tremendous-self-control-or-less-temptations&quot;&gt;Tremendous self-control or less temptations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I never have pastries, ice-cream or other sugar-added foods at home, why? if they are there I can’t resist eating them for long. I try to be the less time possible in tempting situations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;When scientists analyze people who appear to have tremendous self-control, it turns out those individuals aren’t all that different from those who are struggling. Instead, “disciplined” people are better at structuring their lives in a way that does not require heroic willpower and self-control. In other words, they spend less time in tempting situations.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;similar-concepts-to-gtd&quot;&gt;Similar concepts to GTD&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently read the &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Getting Things Done book&lt;/a&gt; and I found some ideas linked from both books. One of the benefits of GTD is getting clarity, you know what to do next, in Atomic Habits is mentioned that many people believe they lack motivation when what they really lack is clarity. For example, making decisions about simple tasks like when should I work out, where do I go to write, when do I pay the bills provokes that you have less time for freedom. Also, we often say yes to little requests because we are not clear enough about what we need to be doing instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another similar concept is doing it perfectly or not doing it. I also consider it “Analysis paralysis”. Both books enforce starting simple and get better with time. In the habits world, it’s really important to accumulate reps, the more you do the more you forge your identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It is easy to get bogged down trying to find the optimal plan for change: the fastest way to lose weight, the best program to build muscle, the perfect idea for a side hustle. We are so focused on figuring out the best approach that we never get around to taking action. As Voltaire once wrote, “The best is the enemy of the good.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;personal-experience&quot;&gt;Personal experience&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I already did some of the actions suggested. I usually go to the gym in the early morning and I tend to leave everything ready (clothes, bag, etc.) the night before so there is no friction/excuses in the morning. I tend to plan my training routine, so there is commitment and clarity, I avoid the “What should I do now?”. I also followed the rule of “Never miss twice” even without knowing about it. I’m known by my friends as a gym rat so I guess it’s my identity already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also limit myself to one chapter per day from Netflix (this one is hard) or read for at least 30 minutes before sleeping, trying to increase the time and situations for reading, but step by step.
Even this blog post you are reading is part of a new habit I’m trying to build. &lt;del&gt;I want to write often&lt;/del&gt; I want to be a writer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something I tried to implement is using less social media. I used to go over Instagram and Twitter feeds too often. It was super easy having it on the phone ready to be checked and opened and also with the notification in case you happen to ignore it for some time. I discovered myself at the toilet checking the phone while brushing my teeth, that can’t be right. Hardcore solution, deleting both apps from the phone. Having them only on the iPad made it uncomfortable and I checked it once or twice per day. After some days like that, I evolved to use the web version of both apps, which are more slow and difficult to use (there is still friction) and I use them less frequently than before but I can use them when I’m away from the iPad. Something positive of Instagram web version, no ads :).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another bad habits on my radar:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The way I sit down which is clearly wrong and created back pain.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Eating super fast.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll try to use the learnings of the book to improve there. What is your experience with habits/resolutions? What would you like to start/stop doing?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Juan Pallarès</name><email>juan@pallares.me</email></author><category term="books" /><category term="amotic" /><category term="habits" /><category term="productivity" /><summary type="html">Tiny changes - Remarkable results</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="es"><title type="html">Necesitas un gestor de contraseñas</title><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/necesitas-un-gestor-de-contrasenas/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Necesitas un gestor de contraseñas" /><published>2020-12-12T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-12-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://juan.pallares.me/necesitas-un-gestor-de-contrasenas</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://juan.pallares.me/necesitas-un-gestor-de-contrasenas/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;problema&quot;&gt;Problema&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Es muy común tener una o dos contraseñas para todo. Para el mail, para Netflix, para Amazon, para el usuario del ordenador. Incluso algunos se vienen arriba y usan la misma contraseña pero van cambiando algo al final, indetectable! deben pensar. Cuando avisas que eso es muy poco seguro la respuesta es:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pero si tengo muchas se me olvidan!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Estoy de acuerdo, son díficiles de recordar tantas contraseñas y más cuando nos piden que tengan números, símbolos, mayúsculas, sangre de uniconrnio, etc. Y no hablemos de los &lt;a href=&quot;https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/Captcha&quot;&gt;CAPTCHA&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/captcha.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;meme CAPTCHA&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;El problema con reutilizar la contraseña es muy sencillo de entender. Imagina esta situación:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hace mucho tiempo te registraste en “foro pepito” para preguntar algo, te contestaron y ya nunca más volviste a entrar.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Al cabo de un tiempo, un ataque consigue las contraseñas de todos los usuarios de “foro pepito”. A “foro pepito” nunca le preocupó la seguridad de sus usuarios.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;En el registro del foro piden email, por lo que lo hackers lo siguiente que hacen es intentar entrar en todos las cuentas más famosas con ese correo y contraseña robada.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ya has perdido todas las cuentas que compartían contraseña. Si solo cambias un número al final o algo muy obvio, es muy probable que también lo prueben.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;solución&quot;&gt;Solución&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Posiblemente pienses que con guardar las contraseñas en el navegador es suficiente, pero no es un método igual de seguro. Además, solo estarán en un dispositivo, te tocará escribirlas en el móvil o en otro ordenador.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Usa un gestor de contraseñas&lt;/strong&gt;. Tendrás que acordate de una sola contraseña y el resto las puedes autogenerar largas y complicadas porque no tendrás que escribirlas, el gestor lo hará por ti. No sabes lo cómodo que se convierte navegar hasta que lo usas. En el móvil además si tienes lector de huellas es una gozada.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Además, los hay gratuítos y que funcionan muy bien. En mi caso, estoy usando &lt;a href=&quot;https://bitwarden.com/&quot;&gt;Bitwarden&lt;/a&gt;. Lo tengo instalado en todos mis dispositivos, se sincroniza, me autorellena usuario y contraseña de las páginas y tiene generador de contraseñas.
He probado varios más (Lastpass, 1password…). Usé &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dashlane.com/&quot;&gt;Dashlane&lt;/a&gt; durante dos años y es francamente mejor que Bitwarden, pero se paga. Te notifica cuando ha habido ataques en paginas donde tu tienes cuenta, tiene VPN y se integra mejor con los navegadores. Además estan ganando tanta fuerza que hicieron el famoso anuncio de la Superbowl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/B5lslSPfhkg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mi sugerencia, prueba con uno gratuíto y si ves que con el tiempo se te queda pequeño, haz el upgrade. Todos suelen permitir exportar y importar todos los datos para cambiar fácilmente de gestor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cómo-es-una-buena-contraseña&quot;&gt;Cómo es una buena contraseña&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LARGA&lt;/strong&gt;, conforme más larga, más segura. Por ejemplo, MiPerroTobyLadraMucho es muchísimo más segura que S0yH4cker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/tiempo-password.png&quot; alt=&quot;Tabla de tiempos de crackeo de contraseñas&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Y, por favor, no uses tu cumpleaños, tu nombre, tu DNI o otros datos que se pueden obtener fácilmente. Tampoco uses las que usa todo el mundo:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/Spain-Most-Used-Passwords.png&quot; alt=&quot;contraseñas mas usadas de España&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.safetydetectives.com/blog/the-most-hacked-passwords-in-the-world/&quot;&gt;Fuente&lt;/a&gt; y &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.osi.es/es/contrasenas&quot;&gt;Fuente&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Juan Pallarès</name><email>juan@pallares.me</email></author><category term="password" /><category term="manager" /><category term="dashlane" /><category term="bitwarden" /><summary type="html">Navega más seguro y recuerda solo una contraseña.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Book - Factfulness - Hans Rosling, Ola Rosling, Anna Rosling</title><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/factfulness/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Book - Factfulness - Hans Rosling, Ola Rosling, Anna Rosling" /><published>2020-09-27T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-09-27T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://juan.pallares.me/factfulness</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://juan.pallares.me/factfulness/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-gapminder-test&quot;&gt;The Gapminder Test&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I start commenting on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/-/es/Hans-Rosling/dp/1250107814&quot;&gt;Factfulness&lt;/a&gt; I would like you to do &lt;a href=&quot;https://forms.gapminder.org/s3/test-2018&quot;&gt;the gapminder online test&lt;/a&gt;. The book starts the same way, asking you to answer the questionnaire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How did you perform? If it was bad, do not worry. World leaders who should have more context about these trends perform below than a monkey would do (what the author uses to refer to answering randomly the test). The world is better than we think, why do we have such negative thoughts about it?.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Factfulness is one of Bill Gates favorite books. He thinks it’s so important to read it that he decided to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodnet.org/articles/bill-gates-gifts-graduates-his-favorite-book-on-positivity&quot;&gt;give it away to all 2018 American graduates&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, I added all the quotes I found interesting &lt;a href=&quot;https://juan.pallares.me/books/factfulness/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Let’s deep dive into Factulness, a book so interesting I read it just in some days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;10-biases&quot;&gt;10 biases&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facts over feelings. That’s the book in three words. Hans shows publicly available data, usually ignored, in eye-catchy graphics to demonstrate how pessimistic we are. Why are we this way?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We, as humans, have 10 different instincts that prevent us from analyzing the world factfully. Is important to know them and to master the ability to disabling them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-the-gap-instinct&quot;&gt;1. The &lt;strong&gt;Gap&lt;/strong&gt; Instinct.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reality is often not polarized at all. Usually, the majority is right there in the middle, where the gap is supposed to be. We tend to divide the countries in developed and non-developed. The author divides them into 4 levels ordered by income per person. Guess which levels are the more crowded? The ones in the middle, 2 and 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-the-negativity-instinct&quot;&gt;2. The &lt;strong&gt;Negativity&lt;/strong&gt; Instinct.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information about bad news is much more likely to reach us. When things are getting better we often don’t hear about them. This gives us a too-negative impression of the world. Things can be bad and improving. Example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The PIN code of the world is 1-1-1-4. That’s how to remember the map. From left to right, the number of billions, as a PIN code. Americas: 1, Europe: 1, Africa: 1, Asia: 4. (I have rounded the numbers.) Like all PIN codes, this one will change. By the end of this century, the UN expects there to have been almost no change in the Americas and Europe but 3 billion more people in Africa and 1 billion more in Asia. By 2100 the new PIN code of the world will be 1-1-4-5. More than 80 percent of the world’s population will live in Africa and Asia.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/world_pin_code.png&quot; alt=&quot;world pin code&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Think of the world as a premature baby in an incubator. The baby’s health status is extremely bad and her breathing, heart rate, and other important signs are tracked constantly so that changes for better or worse can quickly be seen. After a week, she is getting a lot better. On all the main measures, she is improving, but she still has to stay in the incubator because her health is still critical. Does it make sense to say that the infant’s situation is improving? Yes. Absolutely. Does it make sense to say it is bad? Yes, absolutely. Does saying “things are improving” imply that everything is fine, and we should all relax and not worry? No, not at all. Is it helpful to have to choose between bad and improving? Definitely not. It’s both. It’s both bad and better. Better, and bad, at the same time.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-the-straight-line-instinct&quot;&gt;3. The &lt;strong&gt;Straight Line&lt;/strong&gt; Instinct.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Curves (in data graphics) come in different shapes. Don’t assume it will continue straight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-the-fear-instinct&quot;&gt;4. The &lt;strong&gt;Fear&lt;/strong&gt; Instinct.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frightening things get our attention. Remember these are not necessarily the riskiest. Our natural fears (genetic) make us overestimate these risks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;5-the-size-instinct&quot;&gt;5. The &lt;strong&gt;Size&lt;/strong&gt; Instinct.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a lonely number seems impressive. Compare it with another relevant number. Get things in proportion. Example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I had for some time been appalled by the systematic blaming of climate change on China and India based on total emissions per nation. It was like claiming that obesity was worse in China than in the United States because the total bodyweight of the Chinese population was higher than that of the US population.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;6-the-generalization-instinct&quot;&gt;6. The &lt;strong&gt;Generalization&lt;/strong&gt; Instinct.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generalization can’t be stopped but we can check if the use is correct. Look for differences within groups, similarities across groups and differences across groups. Example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It makes no sense to talk about “African countries” and “Africa’s problems” and yet people do, all the time. It leads to ridiculous outcomes like Ebola in Liberia and Sierra Leone affecting tourism in Kenya, a 100-hour drive across the continent. That is farther than London to Tehran.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;7-the-destiny-instinct&quot;&gt;7. The &lt;strong&gt;Destiny&lt;/strong&gt; Instinct.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slow change is still change. Slow changes gradually add up to big changes. Don’t think something (country, culture, etc.) remains constant because the change is small.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;8-the-single-perspective-instinct&quot;&gt;8. The &lt;strong&gt;Single Perspective&lt;/strong&gt; Instinct.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Get a toolbox, not a hammer. Single perspective can limit your imagination. Look at problems from different angles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;9-the-blame-instinct&quot;&gt;9. The &lt;strong&gt;Blame&lt;/strong&gt; Instinct.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blaming an individual often steals the focus from other possible explanations and blocks our ability to prevent similar problems in the future. Resist finding a scapegoat and notice when one is being used,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;10-the-urgency-instinct&quot;&gt;10. The &lt;strong&gt;Urgency&lt;/strong&gt; Instinct.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rarely a decision is urgent. Take a breath. Insist on data. Be careful of taking drastic actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;world-future---economic-shift&quot;&gt;World future - Economic shift&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my favorite parts of the book is when the population growth forecast are analyzed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If the UN forecasts for population growth are correct, and if incomes in Asia and Africa keep growing as now, then the center of gravity of the world market will shift over the next 20 years from the Atlantic to the Indian Ocean. Today, the people living in rich countries around the North Atlantic, who represent 11 percent of the world population, make up 60 percent of the Level 4 consumer market. Already by 2027, if incomes keep growing worldwide as they are doing now, then that figure will have shrunk to 50 percent. By 2040, 60 percent of Level 4 consumers will live outside the West. Yes, &lt;strong&gt;I think the Western domination of the world economy will soon be over&lt;/strong&gt;. People in North America and Europe need to understand that most of the world population lives in Asia. In terms of economic muscles “we” are becoming the 20 percent, not the 80 percent. But many of “us” can’t fit these numbers into our nostalgic minds. Not only do we misjudge how big our war monuments should be in Vietnam, we also misjudge our importance in the future global marketplace. Many of us forget to behave properly with those who will control the future trade deals.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is some food for thought. How easily we ignore all other countries while we are on top but…for how long? A couple more quotes in the same direction:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In sales and marketing, if you run a big business in Europe or the United States, you and your employees need to understand that the world market of the future will be growing primarily in Asia and Africa, not at home.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In making investment decisions, you need to shake off any naïve views of Africa shaped by the colonial past (and maintained by today’s media) and understand that Ghana, Nigeria, and Kenya are where some of the best investment opportunities can be found today.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fake-news&quot;&gt;Fake news&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowadays is common to receive all kind of fake news, rumors, clickbait. For this reason, I see even more value in reading this book. I’m pretty sure that with a population that knew more about all this instincts and how to tackle them, some presidential elections would have gone differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;width:100%;height:0;padding-bottom:93%;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://giphy.com/embed/26tknCqiJrBQG6bxC&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; style=&quot;position:absolute&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;giphy-embed&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://giphy.com/gifs/election2016-election-2016-presidential-debate-26tknCqiJrBQG6bxC&quot;&gt;via GIPHY&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Easy to read. Interesting, funny, and revealing experiences from the author around the world. Great summaries after every chapter. Do you love data? 100% recommended. Better to read it in a tablet than in a e-reader because of the graphics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Juan Pallarès</name><email>juan@pallares.me</email></author><category term="books" /><category term="factfulness" /><category term="facts" /><category term="fake news" /><category term="clickbait" /><summary type="html">Ten reasons we're wrong about the world and why things are better than you think</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Book - Getting Things Done. The Art of Stress-free Productivity - David Allen</title><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/getting-things-done/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Book - Getting Things Done. The Art of Stress-free Productivity - David Allen" /><published>2020-08-29T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-08-29T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://juan.pallares.me/getting-things-done</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://juan.pallares.me/getting-things-done/">&lt;p&gt;Do you have a TODO list? Have you ever used one? Do you remember that time you had so many things to do and the moment you wrote all down in a list you felt much more in control and relaxed? You can learn how to properly manage all your professional and personal life in the last book I read &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.es/Getting-Things-Done-Arts-Stresss/dp/0349408947/ref=sr_1_1?__mk_es_ES=%C3%85M%C3%85%C5%BD%C3%95%C3%91&amp;amp;dchild=1&amp;amp;keywords=getting+things+done&amp;amp;qid=1598698866&amp;amp;sr=8-1&quot;&gt;Getting Things Done The Art of Stress-free Productivity by David Allen&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to admit, the book feels old. It talks a lot about filers (who uses that?), trays with physical documents, bills and a lot of hand-writing. Well, it was 1st published in 2001 and, even if I read a more modern edition, the feeling is there. Having said that, in my opinion, the main learnings are timeless and universal. I will quote a quote (Inception) from the book that explains this better: 
&lt;em&gt;As to methods there may be a million and then some, but principles are few. The man who grasps principles can successfully select his own methods. The man who tries methods, ignoring principles, is sure to have trouble.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I added the quotes I picked while reading in &lt;a href=&quot;https://juan.pallares.me/books/getting-things-done/&quot;&gt;this section&lt;/a&gt;. Let me go in detail about the parts I liked more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/inception-meme.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Inception meme&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;write-everything-down&quot;&gt;Write everything down&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the key concept of the book. Write down every task, idea, concept that crosses your mind and you feel can/could be important. Our brain is meant to have ideas not  to keep all these reminders there. It will generate stress. Implementing this tecnique you will have three benefits:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Less stress.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Being present. Not trying to remember what you wanted to do.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Actually remembering things because they are written down.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-steps-capture---clarify---organize---reflect---engage&quot;&gt;5 steps. Capture - Clarify - Organize - Reflect - Engage&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/gtd-clarify-flow.png&quot; alt=&quot;Diagram of GTD flow, how to process tasks&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Capture.&lt;/strong&gt;
As mentioned before, capture everything. While reading this post has your mind wandered off into something not related? maybe it’s a pending task that you have not yet captured.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clarify.&lt;/strong&gt;
Is it really a task? What should be done?. At this moment you have more time to think about the tasks you captured.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Organize.&lt;/strong&gt;
Notice in this step the task can evolve to project (multi-task), can be done at that moment (less than two minutes), can be delegated or postponed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reflect.&lt;/strong&gt;
This should be done at least once a week (weekly Review). Analyze all your pending tasks, projects, etc and refine them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Engage.&lt;/strong&gt;
Do the tasks at the moment they have to be done. Call the mechanic!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;organize-tasks-depending-on-the-context&quot;&gt;Organize tasks depending on the context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The big secret to efficient creative and productive thinking and action is to put the right things in your focus at the right time. 
I loved the idea of organizing tasks depending on the context. Possible contexts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;At the computer.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;At the phone.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;At the job.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On a plane.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Doing chores.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Low energy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;…
Grouping them will help you tackle more in less time and increase focus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-the-next-action&quot;&gt;What is the next action?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often tasks get stuck because they are too vague. Can you spot the difference between “Fix car” and “Call XXXX to make an appointment to fix car tires”?.  It’s ok to add tasks/ideas in the capture phase a little bit vague. But once they are refined they should be clear actionable tasks.
The question forces clarity, accountability, productivity, and empowerment. 
This can be applied to meetings too. Once a meeting is coming to an end, “What’s the next action?” is a powerful question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;technology-double-sided-sword&quot;&gt;Technology double-sided sword&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Technology sure can help keep track on all information. But it’s so easy to use that it can evolve in what the author calls “write-only syndrome”:
&lt;em&gt;All they’re doing is capturing information—not actually accessing and using it intelligently. Some consciousness needs to be applied to keep one’s potentially huge digital library functional, versus a black hole of data easily dumped in there with a couple of keystrokes.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t feel overwhelmed with all the techniques. Applying just some parts is already a victory and a productivity improvement. I started using &lt;a href=&quot;https://todoist.com/&quot;&gt;Todoist&lt;/a&gt; and created some projects, tags depending on the context and filters to see tasks in the order and prioriy I want. I’m still far from being a pro GTDer but I’m liking it so far. David Allen recommends reading the book again or at least skimming through it after some time promising it will feel like a new book. I’ll sure try in a year or two. Are you using GTD methodology? Any recommended tools/experience?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Juan Pallarès</name><email>juan@pallares.me</email></author><category term="books" /><category term="productivity" /><category term="GTD" /><category term="TODO" /><category term="Todoist" /><category term="growth" /><category term="career" /><summary type="html">Great tips from one of the best books about productivity.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="es"><title type="html">Copia de seguridad de tu Mac (Time Machine) en una carpeta compartida de Windows</title><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/time-machine-en-carpeta-compartida-de-windows/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Copia de seguridad de tu Mac (Time Machine) en una carpeta compartida de Windows" /><published>2020-07-19T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-07-19T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://juan.pallares.me/time-machine-en-carpeta-compartida-de-windows</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://juan.pallares.me/time-machine-en-carpeta-compartida-de-windows/">&lt;p&gt;MacOS tiene un sistema de backup llamado &lt;a href=&quot;https://support.apple.com/es-es/HT201250&quot;&gt;Time Machine&lt;/a&gt; que funciona muy al estilo Apple, rápido y fácil pero siempre que tengas su hardware (Time Capsule) o un disco externo que tendrías que ir conectando. Si tienes un PC Windows a modo de servidor (como yo) y espacio libre, puedes utilizarlo como Time Capsule. El setup es un poco más difícil pero una vez hecho se harán las copias de seguridad en background mientras trabajas/procastinas tranquilo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/windows_shared_drive.png&quot; alt=&quot;Windows shared drive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He utilizado &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imore.com/how-use-time-machine-backup-your-mac-windows-shared-folder&quot;&gt;esta guía&lt;/a&gt; la cúal lo explica genial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-crea-una-carpeta-compartida-en-windows-como-time-capsule&quot;&gt;1 Crea una carpeta compartida en Windows como Time Capsule&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Esto debería ser fácil y seguramente ya tienes alguna compartida. En tú máquina Windows selecciona la carpeta disco a compartir: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Botón derecho &amp;gt; Propiedades &amp;gt; Pestaña Compartir&lt;/code&gt;. Recuerda darte permisos administrador a ti mismo. En mi caso he compartido un disco entero pero puedes compartir solo una carpeta dentro del disco si lo prefieres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/share_folder.png&quot; alt=&quot;Permisos carpeta&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-conecta-desde-mac-a-esta-carpeta-compartida&quot;&gt;2 Conecta desde Mac a esta carpeta compartida&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Desde el Finder: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ir &amp;gt; Conecta a Servidor&lt;/code&gt;. O más facil/pro &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Cmd + K&lt;/code&gt;. Como dirección debes poner &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;smb://servidor/carpeta&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/connect_server.png&quot; alt=&quot;Conecta a servidor&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Te pedirá usuario y contraseña y aquí pondras tus credenciales de Windows (justo las que les has dado permiso en el paso anterior). &lt;strong&gt;Marca la opción de recordar y así no tendrás que volver a introducirlos&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-crea-una-imagen-sparsebundle&quot;&gt;3 Crea una imagen sparsebundle&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Esta imagen será del tipo HFS+ que es la que necesita Mac para usarla como backup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Abre la Disk Utility y ve al menú &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Archivo &amp;gt; Nueva Imagen &amp;gt; Imagen en Blanco&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Renombrala como te parezca.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Escoge la carpeta compartida de Windows a la que te conectaste anteriorment como destino.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Renombra también el sparsebundle.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Escoge el tamaño, idealmente igual o más que el tamaño de disco de tu Mac.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Valida que el tipo de Formato es Mac OS Extended (Journaled)&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cuando grabes puede llegar a tardar horas en crear la imagen, dependiendo del tamaño&lt;/strong&gt;. Paciencia y déjalo trabajando. Quizá tenerlo conectado por red sea buena idea para acelerar el proceso.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-haz-que-se-monte-automáticamente&quot;&gt;4 Haz que se monte automáticamente&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Para que cada vez que reinicies el disco se monte, tienes que configurarlo como Login Item, el único problema es que solo funcionará para tu usuario.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Preferencias del Sistema &amp;gt; Usuarios y Grupos&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Escoges tu usuario y entras a la pestaña Login Items.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Añades la carpeta montada y el fichero.dmg&lt;/strong&gt; que hemos creado.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Esta parte me ha dado problemas, en cada login me pedía los credenciales aunque marcara que los guardara en KeyChain. Valida que no tengas varios logins sobre el mismo disco en KeyChain, cuando he eliminado duplicados me ha funcionado.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/login_items.png&quot; alt=&quot;Login Items&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-configura-timemachine-para-usar-esa-imagen&quot;&gt;5 Configura TimeMachine para usar esa imagen&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Por último, tenemos que comprobar que Time Machine puede ver esta imagen y usarla. En &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Preferencias del Sistema &amp;gt; Time Machine&lt;/code&gt; valida que la disco configurado es el sparsebundle que hemos creado.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/TimeMachine_disk.png&quot; alt=&quot;Disco Time Machine&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Para poder añadirlo sino aparece, con el disco montado, ejecuta el comando:
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ls /Volumes&lt;/code&gt;
y luego con el nombre de la imagen creada en el paso 3, en mi caso lo había nombrado sparsebundle, ejecuta:
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sudo tmutil setdestination /Volumes/sparsebundle&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/timemachine_image_name.png&quot; alt=&quot;Time Machine image name&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Puede que también tengas que utilizar &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sudo tmutil enable&lt;/code&gt; si no tienes Time Machine activado.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;6-disfruta&quot;&gt;6 Disfruta&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;La primera copia de seguridad será larga pero luego solo los archivos que han cambiado se guaradarán y todo se hará automáticamente en background.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Juan Pallarès</name><email>juan@pallares.me</email></author><category term="MacOS" /><category term="Windows" /><category term="timemachine" /><category term="shared" /><category term="drive" /><summary type="html">Configura una carpeta compartido de Windows como Time Machine poder hacer copias de seguridad de tu Mac.</summary></entry></feed>