<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2020-09-29T20:15:46+02:00</updated><id>https://juan.pallares.me/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Juan Pallarès Garbí</title><subtitle>Landing page.</subtitle><author><name>Juan Pallarès</name><email>juan@pallares.me</email></author><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Book - Factfulness - Hans Rosling, Ola Rosling, Anna Rosling</title><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/factfulness/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Book - Factfulness - Hans Rosling, Ola Rosling, Anna Rosling" /><published>2020-09-27T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-09-27T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://juan.pallares.me/factfulness</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://juan.pallares.me/factfulness/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-gapminder-test&quot;&gt;The Gapminder Test&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I start commenting on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/-/es/Hans-Rosling/dp/1250107814&quot;&gt;Factfulness&lt;/a&gt; I would like you to do &lt;a href=&quot;https://forms.gapminder.org/s3/test-2018&quot;&gt;the gapminder online test&lt;/a&gt;. The book starts the same way, asking you to answer the questionnaire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How did you perform? If it was bad, do not worry. World leaders who should have more context about these trends perform below than a monkey would do (what the author uses to refer to answering randomly the test). The world is better than we think, why do we have such negative thoughts about it?.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Factfulness is one of Bill Gates favorite books. He thinks it’s so important to read it that he decided to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodnet.org/articles/bill-gates-gifts-graduates-his-favorite-book-on-positivity&quot;&gt;give it away to all 2018 American graduates&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, I added all the quotes I found interesting &lt;a href=&quot;https://juan.pallares.me/books/factfulness/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Let’s deep dive into Factulness, a book so interesting I read it just in some days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;10-biases&quot;&gt;10 biases&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facts over feelings. That’s the book in three words. Hans shows publicly available data, usually ignored, in eye-catchy graphics to demonstrate how pessimistic we are. Why are we this way?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We, as humans, have 10 different instincts that prevent us from analyzing the world factfully. Is important to know them and to master the ability to disabling them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-the-gap-instinct&quot;&gt;1. The &lt;strong&gt;Gap&lt;/strong&gt; Instinct.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reality is often not polarized at all. Usually, the majority is right there in the middle, where the gap is supposed to be. We tend to divide the countries in developed and non-developed. The author divides them into 4 levels ordered by income per person. Guess which levels are the more crowded? The ones in the middle, 2 and 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-the-negativity-instinct&quot;&gt;2. The &lt;strong&gt;Negativity&lt;/strong&gt; Instinct.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information about bad news is much more likely to reach us. When things are getting better we often don’t hear about them. This gives us a too-negative impression of the world. Things can be bad and improving. Example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The PIN code of the world is 1-1-1-4. That’s how to remember the map. From left to right, the number of billions, as a PIN code. Americas: 1, Europe: 1, Africa: 1, Asia: 4. (I have rounded the numbers.) Like all PIN codes, this one will change. By the end of this century, the UN expects there to have been almost no change in the Americas and Europe but 3 billion more people in Africa and 1 billion more in Asia. By 2100 the new PIN code of the world will be 1-1-4-5. More than 80 percent of the world’s population will live in Africa and Asia.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/world_pin_code.png&quot; alt=&quot;world pin code&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Think of the world as a premature baby in an incubator. The baby’s health status is extremely bad and her breathing, heart rate, and other important signs are tracked constantly so that changes for better or worse can quickly be seen. After a week, she is getting a lot better. On all the main measures, she is improving, but she still has to stay in the incubator because her health is still critical. Does it make sense to say that the infant’s situation is improving? Yes. Absolutely. Does it make sense to say it is bad? Yes, absolutely. Does saying “things are improving” imply that everything is fine, and we should all relax and not worry? No, not at all. Is it helpful to have to choose between bad and improving? Definitely not. It’s both. It’s both bad and better. Better, and bad, at the same time.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-the-straight-line-instinct&quot;&gt;3. The &lt;strong&gt;Straight Line&lt;/strong&gt; Instinct.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Curves (in data graphics) come in different shapes. Don’t assume it will continue straight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-the-fear-instinct&quot;&gt;4. The &lt;strong&gt;Fear&lt;/strong&gt; Instinct.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frightening things get our attention. Remember these are not necessarily the riskiest. Our natural fears (genetic) make us overestimate these risks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;5-the-size-instinct&quot;&gt;5. The &lt;strong&gt;Size&lt;/strong&gt; Instinct.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a lonely number seems impressive. Compare it with another relevant number. Get things in proportion. Example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I had for some time been appalled by the systematic blaming of climate change on China and India based on total emissions per nation. It was like claiming that obesity was worse in China than in the United States because the total bodyweight of the Chinese population was higher than that of the US population.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;6-the-generalization-instinct&quot;&gt;6. The &lt;strong&gt;Generalization&lt;/strong&gt; Instinct.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generalization can’t be stopped but we can check if the use is correct. Look for differences within groups, similarities across groups and differences across groups. Example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It makes no sense to talk about “African countries” and “Africa’s problems” and yet people do, all the time. It leads to ridiculous outcomes like Ebola in Liberia and Sierra Leone affecting tourism in Kenya, a 100-hour drive across the continent. That is farther than London to Tehran.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;7-the-destiny-instinct&quot;&gt;7. The &lt;strong&gt;Destiny&lt;/strong&gt; Instinct.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slow change is still change. Slow changes gradually add up to big changes. Don’t think something (country, culture, etc.) remains constant because the change is small.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;8-the-single-perspective-instinct&quot;&gt;8. The &lt;strong&gt;Single Perspective&lt;/strong&gt; Instinct.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Get a toolbox, not a hammer. Single perspective can limit your imagination. Look at problems from different angles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;9-the-blame-instinct&quot;&gt;9. The &lt;strong&gt;Blame&lt;/strong&gt; Instinct.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blaming an individual often steals the focus from other possible explanations and blocks our ability to prevent similar problems in the future. Resist finding a scapegoat and notice when one is being used,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;10-the-urgency-instinct&quot;&gt;10. The &lt;strong&gt;Urgency&lt;/strong&gt; Instinct.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rarely a decision is urgent. Take a breath. Insist on data. Be careful of taking drastic actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;world-future---economic-shift&quot;&gt;World future - Economic shift&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my favorite parts of the book is when the population growth forecast are analyzed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If the UN forecasts for population growth are correct, and if incomes in Asia and Africa keep growing as now, then the center of gravity of the world market will shift over the next 20 years from the Atlantic to the Indian Ocean. Today, the people living in rich countries around the North Atlantic, who represent 11 percent of the world population, make up 60 percent of the Level 4 consumer market. Already by 2027, if incomes keep growing worldwide as they are doing now, then that figure will have shrunk to 50 percent. By 2040, 60 percent of Level 4 consumers will live outside the West. Yes, &lt;strong&gt;I think the Western domination of the world economy will soon be over&lt;/strong&gt;. People in North America and Europe need to understand that most of the world population lives in Asia. In terms of economic muscles “we” are becoming the 20 percent, not the 80 percent. But many of “us” can’t fit these numbers into our nostalgic minds. Not only do we misjudge how big our war monuments should be in Vietnam, we also misjudge our importance in the future global marketplace. Many of us forget to behave properly with those who will control the future trade deals.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is some food for thought. How easily we ignore all other countries while we are on top but…for how long? A couple more quotes in the same direction:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In sales and marketing, if you run a big business in Europe or the United States, you and your employees need to understand that the world market of the future will be growing primarily in Asia and Africa, not at home.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In making investment decisions, you need to shake off any naïve views of Africa shaped by the colonial past (and maintained by today’s media) and understand that Ghana, Nigeria, and Kenya are where some of the best investment opportunities can be found today.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fake-news&quot;&gt;Fake news&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowadays is common to receive all kind of fake news, rumors, clickbait. For this reason, I see even more value in reading this book. I’m pretty sure that with a population that knew more about all this instincts and how to tackle them, some presidential elections would have gone differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;width:100%;height:0;padding-bottom:93%;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://giphy.com/embed/26tknCqiJrBQG6bxC&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; style=&quot;position:absolute&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;giphy-embed&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://giphy.com/gifs/election2016-election-2016-presidential-debate-26tknCqiJrBQG6bxC&quot;&gt;via GIPHY&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Easy to read. Interesting, funny, and revealing experiences from the author around the world. Great summaries after every chapter. Do you love data? 100% recommended. Better to read it in a tablet than in a e-reader because of the graphics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Juan Pallarès</name><email>juan@pallares.me</email></author><category term="books" /><category term="factfulness" /><category term="facts" /><category term="fake news" /><category term="clickbait" /><summary type="html">Ten reasons we're wrong about the world and why things are better than you think</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Book - Getting Things Done. The Art of Stress-free Productivity - David Allen</title><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/getting-things-done/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Book - Getting Things Done. The Art of Stress-free Productivity - David Allen" /><published>2020-08-29T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-08-29T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://juan.pallares.me/getting-things-done</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://juan.pallares.me/getting-things-done/">&lt;p&gt;Do you have a TODO list? Have you ever used one? Do you remember that time you had so many things to do and the moment you wrote all down in a list you felt much more in control and relaxed? You can learn how to properly manage all your professional and personal life in the last book I read &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.es/Getting-Things-Done-Arts-Stresss/dp/0349408947/ref=sr_1_1?__mk_es_ES=%C3%85M%C3%85%C5%BD%C3%95%C3%91&amp;amp;dchild=1&amp;amp;keywords=getting+things+done&amp;amp;qid=1598698866&amp;amp;sr=8-1&quot;&gt;Getting Things Done The Art of Stress-free Productivity by David Allen&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to admit, the book feels old. It talks a lot about filers (who uses that?), trays with physical documents, bills and a lot of hand-writing. Well, it was 1st published in 2001 and, even if I read a more modern edition, the feeling is there. Having said that, in my opinion, the main learnings are timeless and universal. I will quote a quote (Inception) from the book that explains this better: 
&lt;em&gt;As to methods there may be a million and then some, but principles are few. The man who grasps principles can successfully select his own methods. The man who tries methods, ignoring principles, is sure to have trouble.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I added the quotes I picked while reading in &lt;a href=&quot;https://juan.pallares.me/books/getting-things-done/&quot;&gt;this section&lt;/a&gt;. Let me go in detail about the parts I liked more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/inception-meme.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Inception meme&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;write-everything-down&quot;&gt;Write everything down&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the key concept of the book. Write down every task, idea, concept that crosses your mind and you feel can/could be important. Our brain is meant to have ideas not  to keep all these reminders there. It will generate stress. Implementing this tecnique you will have three benefits:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Less stress.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Being present. Not trying to remember what you wanted to do.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Actually remembering things because they are written down.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-steps-capture---clarify---organize---reflect---engage&quot;&gt;5 steps. Capture - Clarify - Organize - Reflect - Engage&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/gtd-clarify-flow.png&quot; alt=&quot;Diagram of GTD flow, how to process tasks&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Capture.&lt;/strong&gt;
As mentioned before, capture everything. While reading this post has your mind wandered off into something not related? maybe it’s a pending task that you have not yet captured.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clarify.&lt;/strong&gt;
Is it really a task? What should be done?. At this moment you have more time to think about the tasks you captured.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Organize.&lt;/strong&gt;
Notice in this step the task can evolve to project (multi-task), can be done at that moment (less than two minutes), can be delegated or postponed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reflect.&lt;/strong&gt;
This should be done at least once a week (weekly Review). Analyze all your pending tasks, projects, etc and refine them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Engage.&lt;/strong&gt;
Do the tasks at the moment they have to be done. Call the mechanic!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;organize-tasks-depending-on-the-context&quot;&gt;Organize tasks depending on the context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The big secret to efficient creative and productive thinking and action is to put the right things in your focus at the right time. 
I loved the idea of organizing tasks depending on the context. Possible contexts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;At the computer.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;At the phone.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;At the job.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On a plane.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Doing chores.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Low energy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;…
Grouping them will help you tackle more in less time and increase focus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-the-next-action&quot;&gt;What is the next action?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often tasks get stuck because they are too vague. Can you spot the difference between “Fix car” and “Call XXXX to make an appointment to fix car tires”?.  It’s ok to add tasks/ideas in the capture phase a little bit vague. But once they are refined they should be clear actionable tasks.
The question forces clarity, accountability, productivity, and empowerment. 
This can be applied to meetings too. Once a meeting is coming to an end, “What’s the next action?” is a powerful question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;technology-double-sided-sword&quot;&gt;Technology double-sided sword&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Technology sure can help keep track on all information. But it’s so easy to use that it can evolve in what the author calls “write-only syndrome”:
&lt;em&gt;All they’re doing is capturing information—not actually accessing and using it intelligently. Some consciousness needs to be applied to keep one’s potentially huge digital library functional, versus a black hole of data easily dumped in there with a couple of keystrokes.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t feel overwhelmed with all the techniques. Applying just some parts is already a victory and a productivity improvement. I started using &lt;a href=&quot;https://todoist.com/&quot;&gt;Todoist&lt;/a&gt; and created some projects, tags depending on the context and filters to see tasks in the order and prioriy I want. I’m still far from being a pro GTDer but I’m liking it so far. David Allen recommends reading the book again or at least skimming through it after some time promising it will feel like a new book. I’ll sure try in a year or two. Are you using GTD methodology? Any recommended tools/experience?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Juan Pallarès</name><email>juan@pallares.me</email></author><category term="books" /><category term="productivity" /><category term="GTD" /><category term="TODO" /><category term="Todoist" /><category term="growth" /><category term="career" /><summary type="html">Great tips from one of the best books about productivity.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="es"><title type="html">Copia de seguridad de tu Mac (Time Machine) en una carpeta compartida de Windows</title><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/time-machine-en-carpeta-compartida-de-windows/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Copia de seguridad de tu Mac (Time Machine) en una carpeta compartida de Windows" /><published>2020-07-19T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-07-19T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://juan.pallares.me/time-machine-en-carpeta-compartida-de-windows</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://juan.pallares.me/time-machine-en-carpeta-compartida-de-windows/">&lt;p&gt;MacOS tiene un sistema de backup llamado &lt;a href=&quot;https://support.apple.com/es-es/HT201250&quot;&gt;Time Machine&lt;/a&gt; que funciona muy al estilo Apple, rápido y fácil pero siempre que tengas su hardware (Time Capsule) o un disco externo que tendrías que ir conectando. Si tienes un PC Windows a modo de servidor (como yo) y espacio libre, puedes utilizarlo como Time Capsule. El setup es un poco más difícil pero una vez hecho se harán las copias de seguridad en background mientras trabajas/procastinas tranquilo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/windows_shared_drive.png&quot; alt=&quot;Windows shared drive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He utilizado &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imore.com/how-use-time-machine-backup-your-mac-windows-shared-folder&quot;&gt;esta guía&lt;/a&gt; la cúal lo explica genial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-crea-una-carpeta-compartida-en-windows-como-time-capsule&quot;&gt;1 Crea una carpeta compartida en Windows como Time Capsule&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Esto debería ser fácil y seguramente ya tienes alguna compartida. En tú máquina Windows selecciona la carpeta disco a compartir: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Botón derecho &amp;gt; Propiedades &amp;gt; Pestaña Compartir&lt;/code&gt;. Recuerda darte permisos administrador a ti mismo. En mi caso he compartido un disco entero pero puedes compartir solo una carpeta dentro del disco si lo prefieres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/share_folder.png&quot; alt=&quot;Permisos carpeta&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-conecta-desde-mac-a-esta-carpeta-compartida&quot;&gt;2 Conecta desde Mac a esta carpeta compartida&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Desde el Finder: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ir &amp;gt; Conecta a Servidor&lt;/code&gt;. O más facil/pro &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Cmd + K&lt;/code&gt;. Como dirección debes poner &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;smb://servidor/carpeta&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/connect_server.png&quot; alt=&quot;Conecta a servidor&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Te pedirá usuario y contraseña y aquí pondras tus credenciales de Windows (justo las que les has dado permiso en el paso anterior). &lt;strong&gt;Marca la opción de recordar y así no tendrás que volver a introducirlos&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-crea-una-imagen-sparsebundle&quot;&gt;3 Crea una imagen sparsebundle&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Esta imagen será del tipo HFS+ que es la que necesita Mac para usarla como backup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Abre la Disk Utility y ve al menú &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Archivo &amp;gt; Nueva Imagen &amp;gt; Imagen en Blanco&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Renombrala como te parezca.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Escoge la carpeta compartida de Windows a la que te conectaste anteriorment como destino.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Renombra también el sparsebundle.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Escoge el tamaño, idealmente igual o más que el tamaño de disco de tu Mac.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Valida que el tipo de Formato es Mac OS Extended (Journaled)&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cuando grabes puede llegar a tardar horas en crear la imagen, dependiendo del tamaño&lt;/strong&gt;. Paciencia y déjalo trabajando. Quizá tenerlo conectado por red sea buena idea para acelerar el proceso.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-haz-que-se-monte-automáticamente&quot;&gt;4 Haz que se monte automáticamente&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Para que cada vez que reinicies el disco se monte, tienes que configurarlo como Login Item, el único problema es que solo funcionará para tu usuario.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Preferencias del Sistema &amp;gt; Usuarios y Grupos&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Escoges tu usuario y entras a la pestaña Login Items.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Añades la carpeta montada y el fichero.dmg&lt;/strong&gt; que hemos creado.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Esta parte me ha dado problemas, en cada login me pedía los credenciales aunque marcara que los guardara en KeyChain. Valida que no tengas varios logins sobre el mismo disco en KeyChain, cuando he eliminado duplicados me ha funcionado.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/login_items.png&quot; alt=&quot;Login Items&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-configura-timemachine-para-usar-esa-imagen&quot;&gt;5 Configura TimeMachine para usar esa imagen&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Por último, tenemos que comprobar que Time Machine puede ver esta imagen y usarla. En &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Preferencias del Sistema &amp;gt; Time Machine&lt;/code&gt; valida que la disco configurado es el sparsebundle que hemos creado.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/TimeMachine_disk.png&quot; alt=&quot;Disco Time Machine&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Para poder añadirlo sino aparece, con el disco montado, ejecuta el comando:
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ls /Volumes&lt;/code&gt;
y luego con el nombre de la imagen creada en el paso 3, en mi caso lo había nombrado sparsebundle, ejecuta:
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sudo tmutil setdestination /Volumes/sparsebundle&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/timemachine_image_name.png&quot; alt=&quot;Time Machine image name&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Puede que también tengas que utilizar &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sudo tmutil enable&lt;/code&gt; si no tienes Time Machine activado.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;6-disfruta&quot;&gt;6 Disfruta&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;La primera copia de seguridad será larga pero luego solo los archivos que han cambiado se guaradarán y todo se hará automáticamente en background.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Juan Pallarès</name><email>juan@pallares.me</email></author><category term="MacOS" /><category term="Windows" /><category term="timemachine" /><category term="shared" /><category term="drive" /><summary type="html">Configura una carpeta compartido de Windows como Time Machine poder hacer copias de seguridad de tu Mac.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="es"><title type="html">Que no te engañen con tu seguro de moto o coche</title><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/que-no-te-enganen-con-tu-seguro-de-moto-coche/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Que no te engañen con tu seguro de moto o coche" /><published>2020-07-05T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-07-05T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://juan.pallares.me/que-no-te-enganen-con-tu-seguro-de-moto-coche</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://juan.pallares.me/que-no-te-enganen-con-tu-seguro-de-moto-coche/">&lt;p&gt;¿Cuánto pagas por tu seguro? Si no lo sabes, revísalo. ¿Y el año anterior? ¿Y el previo? Te ha ido subiendo cada año? No te preocupes, no estás solo. Las aseguradoras por lo general te suben el precio cada año aunque no tengas ningún parte. Aunque envejezcas y estadísticamente salgas de la franjas más peligrosas. Da lo mismo, el precio subirá igual que el sol sale cada mañana.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Por qué hacen esto? Opino que aprovechan varios factores:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;El seguro es obligatorio.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;La gente no tiene un gran control de sus finanzas y no notan esa subida. No se dan ni cuenta.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;El más importante. &lt;strong&gt;Da pereza cambiar, igual que da pereza cambiar de banco, de compañía de teléfono, etc. Esto lo aprovechan sin piedad.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mi-caso&quot;&gt;Mi caso&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;En 2010 compré una moto 125cc que venía con seguro incluído, otro truco ya que te tienen atado y no te sueltan por los anteriores motivos. Cuando pasó el primer año, renovado automáticamente por la nada despreciable cantidad de &lt;strong&gt;242,05€&lt;/strong&gt; (no es que me acuerde, tengo el mail) con Allianz. Yo sabía que podía obtener el mismo seguro (terceros con asistencia) por &lt;strong&gt;menos de 200€ y así fue&lt;/strong&gt;. Devolví el recibo y contacté con una correduría para que me buscaran el presupuesto más bajo y me dieran de baja de la otra aseguradora. Además todo por mail, llámame asocial o llámame práctico.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;la-solución&quot;&gt;La solución&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Desde entonces, &lt;strong&gt;un par de meses antes de que caduque el seguro tengo una alarma de Google Calendar CADUCA SEGURO&lt;/strong&gt; y en ese momento decido si quiero tragar este año con la subida o cambio de compañía? si decido cambiar envío un mensaje así a la correduría que he venido usando estos años: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.peris.es/&quot;&gt;Peris&lt;/a&gt;, en concreto a &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:correduria@peris.es,motos@peris.es&quot;&gt;correduria@peris.es y motos@peris.es&lt;/a&gt;. Este es un ejemplo con mi actual moto, una 300cc:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Hola,

He gestionado varias veces el seguro con vosotros, soy Juan Pallarès Garbí con DNI XXXXXXXX y fecha de nacimiento 1985, 34 años en breve. Carné de conducir A2 con fecha de expedición XX/XX/XXXX (adjunto).

Mi moto es Honda Forza 300cc comprada en Octubre 2013 con matrícula XXXXXXX. Con permiso de circulación XXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXX (adjunto) y también adjunto tarjeta inspección técnica.

Mi actual póliza es con Mapfre a terceros con asistencia en carretera. Número de póliza XXXXXXXXXXXXXX
Llevo dos años con ellos, cobrando los siguientes recibos
2017 - 141,07€
2018 - 150,93€
Esta póliza caduca a 23 de Octubre 2019.

Me puede pasar un listado de posible pólizas que pueda contratar?
Comuníqueme si falta algún dato o documento

Saludos
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fíjate en las subidas que se van produciendo y la próxima iba a ser 160€. Lo sé porque esta vez quise darles una oportunidad, llamé a Mapfre y les expliqué educadamente que o me bajaban el precio o me iba…da igual, seguían empecinados en que “han subido los costes”. Llamé a otras aseguradoras, estilo Línea Directa, casi una hora al teléfono para ofrecerme algo más caro de lo que tenía. &lt;em&gt;“Por qué pensaste que habrían cambiado?”&lt;/em&gt; Me dije y volví a mi mail anual a Peris. Te responden con un mail donde adjuntan un presupuesto de este estilo:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/presupuesto_peris.png&quot; alt=&quot;Captura presupuesto Peris&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;132€ de coste, unos 30€ de ahorro.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;vale-la-pena&quot;&gt;Vale la pena?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Como te pones Juan por 30€!”&lt;/em&gt; Que es como si os oyera decirme. Eso ha sido solo un año, imagina el Juan incauto del pasado que sigue con el seguro de 242€ que aumenta año tras año. Y además que si nos le dais valor a 30€ os paso mi número de cuenta que yo si les daré todo el amor que merecen :smile:.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Opino que vale la pena, ya no solo económicamente sino también para no sentir que te están tomando el pelo. Todo se puede gestionar por mail y es enviar un par de mail una vez al año. Se ha dado el caso que he estado en la aseguradora AXA, he ido a Mapfre y luego he vuelto AXA. AXA podría haberme tenido como cliente todo el tiempo si hubiera accedido a darme un precio de mercado, no lo hacen. También he estado estos años en Generali y Allianz, siempre al mejor postor, cúal mercenario.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Después de leer todo esto, seguirás con tu actual compañía? Me encantaría que compartieras tu experiencia conmigo.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Juan Pallarès</name><email>juan@pallares.me</email></author><summary type="html">Paga el mínimo posible cada año</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Configure Jekyll to be multi-language without plugins</title><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/configure-jekyll-multi-language-without-plugin/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Configure Jekyll to be multi-language without plugins" /><published>2020-06-28T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-06-28T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://juan.pallares.me/configure-jekyll-multi-language-without-plugin</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://juan.pallares.me/configure-jekyll-multi-language-without-plugin/">&lt;p&gt;Almost 6 years ago I migrated from &lt;a href=&quot;https://juan.pallares.me/moving-to-jekyll/&quot;&gt;Blogger to Jekyll + Github Pages&lt;/a&gt; and I can’t be happier with the change. Still, something I wanted long ago is to make it multi-language. I have entries in mind that I have not written because the clear target is Spain and the average English level in my country is not high. This last weekend I finally comitted to it and here I present my m̵a̵s̵t̵e̵r̵-̵p̵i̵e̵c̵e̵ quick-fix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;requirements&quot;&gt;Requirements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No plugins.&lt;/strong&gt; Github Pages is not compatible with many &lt;a href=&quot;https://pages.github.com/versions/&quot;&gt;plugins&lt;/a&gt;. For example, I was unable to use &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kurtsson/jekyll-multiple-languages-plugin&quot;&gt;jekyll-multiple-languages-plugin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Compatible with Minimal Mistakes&lt;/strong&gt;. My &lt;a href=&quot;https://mmistakes.github.io/minimal-mistakes/&quot;&gt;Jekyll’s theme&lt;/a&gt; that I’m delighted with.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Show the entry if it is only in one language&lt;/strong&gt;. I have many old posts in Spanish or English that I will not translate, it has no value.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Link for language change in each entry&lt;/strong&gt;. If there are two languages ​​or more (I don’t think I will ever write in Catalan or Italian :smile:) a link to change language ​​will be displayed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Global Link language change&lt;/strong&gt;. This functionality has been dropped. The pagination plugin &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/docs/pagination/&quot;&gt;jekyll-paginate&lt;/a&gt; does not allow more than one page. Sure there are ways to do it, but I did not want to spend the time, it did not compensate me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/pagination_jekyll.png&quot; alt=&quot;jekyll-paginate disclaimer&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;implementation&quot;&gt;Implementation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Judging from Google’s results, many warriors have gone but few have returned victorious. There is no standard way to do it and I have used what was best for my requrements from each site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;configure-_configyaml&quot;&gt;Configure _config.yaml&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the _config.yml we set the language of the site adding the line &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;lang: en&lt;/code&gt;. Then we create a file inside the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_data&lt;/code&gt; folder, that I have called&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt; i18n&lt;/code&gt;, with the following content:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;in:
  label: English
  icon: 🇬🇧
  read_it_in: &quot;Read it in&quot;
it is:
  label: Spanish
  icon: 🇪🇸
  read_it_in: &quot;Read it on&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will allow us to access content according to the language as we will see later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;adapt-the-front-matter-of-the-posts&quot;&gt;Adapt the &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/docs/front-matter/&quot;&gt;Front Matter&lt;/a&gt; of the posts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In each post, specify your language &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;lang&lt;/code&gt; and unique identifier&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt; ref&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;-
title: RDP to Windows machine with PIN login
tags: [RDP, Windows, PIN, MicrosoftAccount, login, hacks]
excerpt: Don't lose the precious hour I lost
lang: in
ref: rdp
---
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If two posts share the same &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ref&lt;/code&gt; they are the same post in different languages. I’ve seen people grouping the posts by folders according to the language, I have not considered it necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;filter-by-language&quot;&gt;Filter by language&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My main page is a pagination of all blog entries. Now we want all of them to be displayed, but if they are in more than one language, they should be shown in English.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before it showed all the posts that came from the paginator:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;{% for post in paginator.posts%}
  {% include archive-single.html%}
{% endfor%}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then what I have done is to group by the field &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ref&lt;/code&gt;. This way you can know if there is more than one language for each entry since the group will have more than 1 item. If that’s the case, I take only the post that has the same language as the page (English in my case), otherwise I show the post regardless of the language:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;{% assign items_grouped = paginator.posts | group_by: 'ref'%}
{% for group in items_grouped%}
    {% if group.items.size&amp;gt; 1%}
        {% assign post = group.items | where: &quot;lang&quot;, page.lang | first%}
    {% else%}
        {% assign post = group.items [0]%}
    {% endif%}
    {% include archive-single.html%}
{% endfor%}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That beautiful code is &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/docs/liquid/&quot;&gt;Liquid&lt;/a&gt;, it may already be in the TOP 5 of my most hated languages. Keep in mind that I do the identation for clarity, it is not necessary. In order to display Liquid code in Jekill (escape it) you have to use &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;raw&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/show_liquid.png&quot; alt=&quot;Escape liquid code with raw tag&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;filter-by-language-1&quot;&gt;Filter by language&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the previous code, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;archive-single.html&lt;/code&gt; is called and this is what we are going to edit now. We will add a flag emoji with the language in case there is a translation of the post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;{% assign versions = site.posts | where: &quot;ref&quot;, post.ref | sort: 'lang'%}
{% if versions.size&amp;gt; 1%}
    {% for version in versions%}
        {% if version.lang! = site.lang%}
            &amp;lt;a href=&quot;{{ version.url }}&quot;&amp;gt;{{site.data.i18n [version.lang] .icon}} &amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
        {% endif%}
    {% endfor%}
{% endif%}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is again a similar concept to the previous one, the difference is that we now access the flag emoji that we put in the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_data/i18n.yml&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;link-to-other-languages-within-the-blog&quot;&gt;Link to other languages ​​within the blog&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And going from outside to inside, finally we have to edit &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;single.html&lt;/code&gt; which is the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;layout&lt;/code&gt; of my blog entries. Add where you think is most appropriate:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;{% if page.bookauthor == null and page.permalink == null%}
    {% assign versions = site.posts | where: &quot;ref&quot;, page.ref | sort: 'lang'%}
    {% if versions.size&amp;gt; 1%}
        {% for version in versions%}
            {% if version.lang! = page.lang%}
                &amp;lt;a href=&quot;{{ version.url }}&quot; class=&quot;{{ version.lang }}&quot;&amp;gt;{{ site.data.i18n[version.lang].read_it_in] }} {{ site.data.i18n[version.lang].icon }} &amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
            {% endif%}
        {% endfor%}
    {% endif%}
{% endif%}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;if&lt;/code&gt; I prevent other layouts from being affected and then practically the same. The difference is that I look for a different language than the current one and I show a text located next to the flag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;outcome&quot;&gt;Outcome&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are browsing on it right now. Feel free to swap between English and Spanish version. You can also see the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jpallares/minimal-mistakes&quot;&gt;code on Github&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dodge-the-black-hole&quot;&gt;Dodge the black hole&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All engineers who have a blog/landing page suffer what I call the black hole. This is dedicating all the time to improve the blog technically, now I use Gatsby, now I deploy in Vercel, wow! now I have Github Actions … but not writing any content. This multi-language update was the ideal breeding ground to start a technology change that would never have ended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.gifer.com/GVXn.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Black hole gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily I clearly defined the minimum requirements and now I have a basic multi-language blog instead of a last-tech half-baked project. &lt;strong&gt;Deliver value, that should be the focus&lt;/strong&gt;. It has helped me by forcing myself to a weekly blog post. What productivity-hacks do you have?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Juan Pallarès</name><email>juan@pallares.me</email></author><summary type="html">Basic multi-language hosted on Github Pages</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="es"><title type="html">Configura Jekyll para ser multi idioma sin plugins</title><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/configura-jekyll-multi-idioma-sin-plugin/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Configura Jekyll para ser multi idioma sin plugins" /><published>2020-06-28T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-06-28T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://juan.pallares.me/configura-jekyll-multi-idioma-sin-plugin</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://juan.pallares.me/configura-jekyll-multi-idioma-sin-plugin/">&lt;p&gt;Han pasado casi 6 años desde que migré de &lt;a href=&quot;https://juan.pallares.me/moving-to-jekyll/&quot;&gt;Blogger a Jekyll + Github Pages&lt;/a&gt; y no puedo estar más contento con el cambio. Aún así, algo que quería hace tiempo es convertirlo en multi-idioma. Tengo entradas en mente que no he escrito porque el target claro es España y como bien sabemos el nivel de inglés no es alto. Este último fin de semana me he decidio y aquí os presento mi o̵b̵r̵a̵ chapuza.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;requisitos&quot;&gt;Requisitos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sin plugins.&lt;/strong&gt; Github Pages no es compatible con muchos &lt;a href=&quot;https://pages.github.com/versions/&quot;&gt;plugins&lt;/a&gt;. Por ejemplo, no he podido usar &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kurtsson/jekyll-multiple-languages-plugin&quot;&gt;jekyll-multiple-languages-plugin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Compatible con Minimal Mistakes&lt;/strong&gt;. Mi &lt;a href=&quot;https://mmistakes.github.io/minimal-mistakes/&quot;&gt;tema de Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; con el cual estoy encantado.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mostrar la entrada si solo esta en un idioma&lt;/strong&gt;. Tengo muchísimos post antiguos en castellano o en inglés que no traduciré, no tiene valor.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Link para cambio de idioma en cada entrada&lt;/strong&gt;. Si hay dos idiomas o más (no creo que llegue a escribir en catalán o italiano :smile:) que se muestre un link para cambiar de idioma.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Link global cambio de idioma&lt;/strong&gt;. Esta funcionalidad se ha caído. El plugin de paginación &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/docs/pagination/&quot;&gt;jekyll-paginate&lt;/a&gt; no permite más de una página. Seguro hay formas de hacerlo, pero no he querido dedicar el tiempo, no me compensaba.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/pagination_jekyll.png&quot; alt=&quot;jekyll-paginate disclaimer&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;implementación&quot;&gt;Implementación&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A juzgar por los resultados de Google, muchos guerreros han ido pero pocos han vuelto victoriosos. No hay una manera estándar de hacerlo y he cogido lo que mejor me venía de cada sitio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;configura-_configyaml&quot;&gt;Configura _config.yaml&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;En el _config.yml seteamos el lenguage del site añadiendo la linea &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;lang: en&lt;/code&gt;. Y luego creamos un fichero dentro de la carpeta &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_data&lt;/code&gt;que yo he llamado &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;i18n&lt;/code&gt; con el siguiente contenido:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;en:
  label: English
  icon: 🇬🇧
  read_it_in: &quot;Read it in&quot;
es:
  label: Español
  icon: 🇪🇸
  read_it_in: &quot;Léelo en&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Esto nos permitirá acceder a contenido según el idioma como veremos más adelante.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;adapta-el-front-matter-de-los-posts&quot;&gt;Adapta el &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/docs/front-matter/&quot;&gt;Front Matter&lt;/a&gt; de los posts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Especifica en cada post su idioma &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;lang&lt;/code&gt; y identificador único &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ref&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;--
title: RDP to Windows machine with PIN login
tags: [RDP, Windows, PIN, MicrosoftAccount, login, hacks]
excerpt: Don't lose the precious hour I lost
lang: en
ref: rdp
---
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Si dos posts comparten el mismo &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ref&lt;/code&gt; son el mismo post en diferentes idiomas. Algunos agrupan los posts por carpetas según el idioma, no lo he considerado necesario.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;filtra-por-idioma&quot;&gt;Filtra por idioma&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mi página principal es una paginacioón de todas las entradas del blog. Ahora queremos que se muestren todos pero si están en más de un idioma que se muestren en inglés.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Antes mostraba todos los posts que venian del paginator:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;{% for post in paginator.posts %}
  {% include archive-single.html %}
{% endfor %}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Después lo que he hecho ha sido agrupar por el campo &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ref&lt;/code&gt;. De esta manera puede saber si hay más de un idioma para cada entrada ya que el grupo tendrá más de 1 item. Si ese es el caso, cojo solo el post que tiene el mismo idioma que la página (Inglés en mi caso), de lo contrario muestro el post independientemente del idioma:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;{% assign items_grouped = paginator.posts | group_by: 'ref' %}
{% for group in items_grouped %}
    {% if group.items.size &amp;gt; 1 %}
        {% assign post = group.items | where: &quot;lang&quot;,page.lang | first %}
    {% else %}
        {% assign post = group.items[0] %}
    {% endif %}
    {% include archive-single.html %}
{% endfor %}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ese código tan bonito es &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/docs/liquid/&quot;&gt;Liquid&lt;/a&gt;, puede que ya esté en el TOP 5 de mis lenguajes más odiados. Tened en cuenta que el sangrado lo hago yo por claridad, no es necesario. Para poder mostrar código Liquid en Jekill, escaparlo, hay que usar &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;raw&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/show_liquid.png&quot; alt=&quot;Escape liquid code with raw tag&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;filtra-por-idioma-1&quot;&gt;Filtra por idioma&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Desde el código anterior se llama a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;archive-single.html&lt;/code&gt; y ese código es el que vamos a editar ahora para añadir una bandera con el idioma en caso que haya una traducción del post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;{% assign versions=site.posts | where:&quot;ref&quot;, post.ref | sort: 'lang' %}
{% if versions.size &amp;gt; 1 %}
    {% for version in versions %}
        {% if version.lang != site.lang %}
            &amp;lt;a href=&quot;{{ version.url }}&quot; &amp;gt;{{ site.data.i18n[version.lang].icon }} &amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
        {% endif %}
    {% endfor %}
{% endif %}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vuelve a ser un concepto similar al anterior, la diferencia es que ahora accedemos al emoji de bandera que pusimos en el fichero &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_data/i18n.yml&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;link-a-otros-idiomas-dentro-del-blog&quot;&gt;Link a otros idiomas dentro del blog&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Y yendo de fuera hacia a dentro nos queda editar &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;single.html&lt;/code&gt; que es el &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;layout&lt;/code&gt; de mis entradas. Añade donde creas más oportuno esto:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;{% if page.bookauthor == null and page.permalink == null %}
    {% assign versions=site.posts | where:&quot;ref&quot;, page.ref | sort: 'lang' %}
    {% if versions.size &amp;gt; 1 %}
        {% for version in versions %}
            {% if version.lang != page.lang %}
                &amp;lt;a href=&quot;{{ version.url }}&quot; class=&quot;{{ version.lang }}&quot;&amp;gt;{{ site.data.i18n[version.lang].read_it_in] }} {{ site.data.i18n[version.lang].icon }} &amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
            {% endif %}
        {% endfor %}
    {% endif %}
{% endif %}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;En el primer &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;if&lt;/code&gt; evito que otros layouts se vean afectados y luego prácticamente igual. La diferencia es que busco el lenguaje diferente al actual y muestro un texto localizado al lado de la bandera.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;resultado&quot;&gt;Resultado&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Estás navegando sobre él ahora mismo. También puedes ver el &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jpallares/minimal-mistakes&quot;&gt;código en Github&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;esquivar-el-agujero-negro&quot;&gt;Esquivar el agujero negro&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Todos los ingenieros que tenemos un blog/landing page sufrimos lo que llamo el agujero negro. Esto es dedicar todo el tiempo a mejorar el blog técnicamente, ahora uso Gatsby, ahora deploy en Vercel, ojo que ahora tengo Github Actions…pero no escribir nada de contenido. Este update a multi-idioma era el caldo de cultivo ideal para venirme arriba y empezar un cambio de tecnología que nunca habría acabado.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.gifer.com/GVXn.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Black hole gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Por suerte, me definí claramente los mínimos y ahora tengo un multi-idioma básico en lugar de un proyecto con las últimas tecnologías a medias. &lt;strong&gt;Entregar valor, ese debe ser el foco&lt;/strong&gt;. Me ha ayudado el auto-obligarme a una entreda semanal. Que productivity-hacks tienes?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Juan Pallarès</name><email>juan@pallares.me</email></author><summary type="html">Multi-idioma básico alojado en Github Pages</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">RDP to Windows machine with PIN login</title><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/RDP-to-windows-machine-with-PIN-login/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="RDP to Windows machine with PIN login" /><published>2020-06-19T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-06-19T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://juan.pallares.me/RDP-to-windows-machine-with-PIN-login</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://juan.pallares.me/RDP-to-windows-machine-with-PIN-login/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;tldr&quot;&gt;TL;DR&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Disable PIN login&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Remote connect with user@domain.com and password&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Renable PIN (I had to do it connected locally)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Remote connection will keep working with the previous credentials&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-problem&quot;&gt;The problem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a PC machine working as a server with Windows 10 installed. I almost never use it phisically, I always remote to it. For remoting I use integrated authentication, this is my Microsoft account (usually an account ending in @live.com, @outlook.com or even @hotmail.com if you are old like me). This account has a very long and complicated password that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dashlane.com/&quot;&gt;Dashlane&lt;/a&gt; remembers for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I loging phisically, I can’t use Dashlane to get my password that’s why I have enabled &lt;a href=&quot;https://petri.com/windows-10-use-a-pin-instead-of-a-password-to-sign-in&quot;&gt;PIN authentication&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/WindowsPIN.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Windows PIN Sing-in&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what’s the problem? &lt;strong&gt;When you try to remote with a machine that has never remoted before it won’t work&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-fix&quot;&gt;The fix&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has happened me twice and both times I lost too much time googling the fix. I thought let’s write a post about it so at least the third time I can look it here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s be clear, &lt;strong&gt;you don’t want to remote with the PIN&lt;/strong&gt;. I believe is not possible but even if it was I wouldn’t recommend it. So as I said in the quick steps in the TL;DR section, the trick is to disable temporarily the PIN. It seems it needs to remote login a first time with PIN disabled and then it will work afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Juan Pallarès</name><email>juan@pallares.me</email></author><category term="RDP" /><category term="Windows" /><category term="PIN" /><category term="MicrosoftAccount" /><category term="login" /><category term="hacks" /><summary type="html">Don't lose the precious hour I lost</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Book - The software developer’s life manual - John Z. Sonmez</title><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/soft-skills-the-software-developers-life-manual/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Book - The software developer's life manual - John Z. Sonmez" /><published>2020-06-16T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-06-16T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://juan.pallares.me/soft-skills-the-software-developers-life-manual</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://juan.pallares.me/soft-skills-the-software-developers-life-manual/">&lt;p&gt;I recently finished reading the book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.es/Soft-Skills-software-developers-manual/dp/1617292397&quot;&gt;Soft Skills: The software developer’s life manual - John Z. Sonmez&lt;/a&gt;. It is a really interesting and original book, different from what I’m used to read. I uploaded all the &lt;a href=&quot;https://juan.pallares.me/books/soft-skills-the-software-developer-s-life-manual/&quot;&gt;clippings&lt;/a&gt; I had about this book but I wanted to analyze it in a post. It gives you advice in very different areas of life like sport or personal finance. It is divided in 7 sections:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Career&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Marketing yourself&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Productivity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Financial&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fitness&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spirit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/softskillsbook.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Soft Skills: The software developer's life manual&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most interesting ones for me were the first 2. I’m not saying the rest of the book was boring (I wouldn’t have finished it) but for example I skimmed through the Fitness or Financial sections since I already read much more detailed books in this area. This is a feeling I got in general with the whole book, it feels like an introduction to every section, if you want to go deep into any of the areas you have to get books that focun on them. On the other hand, is really nice that it does not get lost into too much detail. It goes straight to the point in what matters to us software developers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something I loved about the book is that every chapter has a “Taking action” section with things to do to practice what you learnt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;main-takeaways&quot;&gt;Main takeaways&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to enumarate the main points I found interesenting. Of course this is just an opinion, for example there are full chapters about freelancing or startups which is something I’m not interesed in currently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;career&quot;&gt;Career&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It’s better to think of an employer as a customer for your business of developing software.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Set long term goals (vision), short term goals and track them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People skills, we need them more than we think. He makes a brief summary of the concepts in one of my favourite books &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.es/How-Win-Friends-Influence-People/dp/0091906350&quot;&gt;How to Win Friends and Influence People by Dale Carnegie&lt;/a&gt;.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Everybody wants to feel important.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Never criticize.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Think about what the other person wants.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Avoid arguments.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Interview tips, like trying to meet and connect with people working in the company you plan to get interviewed at.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Salary negotiation! It reminded me this &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kalzumeus.com/2012/01/23/salary-negotiation/&quot;&gt;great article&lt;/a&gt; also the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.es/Getting-Yes-Negotiating-Agreement-Without/dp/0140157352&quot;&gt;Getting to Yes&lt;/a&gt; book (this is negotiation in general). &lt;strong&gt;Key thing to remember, first one to says a number, loses&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pick and specialization, try to become an expert in an area but don’t become religious about technology.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Visibility.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Keep a daily log of your activities.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Offer to give presentations or trainigs.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Speak up.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Be seen.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fake it till you make it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hire a resume writer or at least take it very seriously.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;marketing-yourself&quot;&gt;Marketing yourself&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create a personal brand
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Create a logo, like sucessful brands do.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create a blog and write often (part of the reason I’m writing on this blog again is reading this chapter)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do presentations and trainings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t be afraid to look like an idiot. If you want to be successful at your efforts, you have to learn to stop caring about what people think. You have to learn how to not be afraid to look like an idiot.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;learning&quot;&gt;Learning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From this section I loved the concept of learning 20% of the concepts in an area should allow you to cover 80% of the daily usage. Also the concept of finding a mentor and becoming a mentor of someone: &lt;strong&gt;One of the greatest ways to learn—perhaps the only way to learn anything deeply—is to teach.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;productivity&quot;&gt;Productivity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Focus&lt;/strong&gt;. Nowadays we have too much distractions and we are machines very inefficient when multitasking.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quotas&lt;/strong&gt;. Stablish a minimum goal per period of time. For instance, I have the quota of creating a blog post per week.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Self-accountability&lt;/strong&gt;. Internal motivation is key to be productive. You should be able to do work without anybody telling you to.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Routine&lt;/strong&gt;. What you do every day defines and shapes who you are over time. If you want to achieve a goal you have to put in place a routine that slowly but surely moves you in the direction you’re trying to go.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Momentum&lt;/strong&gt;. It’s easier to steer a moving car. Yet, so many of us are sitting in the garages of our lives behind the wheel of a parked car, furiously cranking the steering wheel to the left and right trying to decide which direction we should go before we’ve even pulled out of the driveway. Once a car is moving, it has momentum. That momentum can carry you forward in the wrong direction, but it can be just as easily diverted with a turn of the steering wheel to the correct direction once you figure it out.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;financial&quot;&gt;Financial&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The author was really successful with agressive real-state investment (I’m more into &lt;a href=&quot;https://juan.pallares.me/why-i-became-a-bogglehead/&quot;&gt;index funds&lt;/a&gt;). But he also worked really around the clock with a remote work, phone applications, podcasts, pluralsight trainings. He was able to generate a lot of different sources of income unlike most people that only has his regular job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;spirit&quot;&gt;Spirit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found very interesting that John Sonmez has the habit of asking successful people for their favourite book, the one that created more impact. This way he created a really nice list. It’s also comforting to realize I had read already some of them and some missing ones are already waiting on the Kindle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.es/War-Art-Through-Creative-Battles/dp/1936891026&quot;&gt;The War of Art by Steven Pressfield&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.es/How-Win-Friends-Influence-People/dp/0091906350&quot;&gt;How to Win Friends and Influence People by Dale Carnegie&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.es/Think-Grow-Rich-Napoleon-Hill/dp/0449214923&quot;&gt;Think and Grow Rich by Napoleon Hill&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.es/Psycho-Cybernetics-Maxwell-Maltz/dp/0399176136&quot;&gt;Psycho-Cybernetics by Maxwell Maltz&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.es/Power-Positive-Thinking-English-ebook/dp/B07K2KMHYJ/ref=sr_1_1?__mk_es_ES=%C3%85M%C3%85%C5%BD%C3%95%C3%91&amp;amp;dchild=1&amp;amp;keywords=The+Power+of+Positive+Thinking&amp;amp;qid=1592312108&amp;amp;sr=8-1&quot;&gt;The Power of Positive Thinking by Norman Vincent Peale&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.es/Ayn-Rand-Set-Fountainhead-Shrugged/dp/0451947673/ref=sr_1_1?__mk_es_ES=%C3%85M%C3%85%C5%BD%C3%95%C3%91&amp;amp;dchild=1&amp;amp;keywords=Atlas+Shrugged&amp;amp;qid=1592312128&amp;amp;sr=8-1&quot;&gt;Atlas Shrugged by Ayn Rand&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.es/Code-Complete-Practical-Costruction-Professional/dp/0735619670/ref=sr_1_1?__mk_es_ES=%C3%85M%C3%85%C5%BD%C3%95%C3%91&amp;amp;dchild=1&amp;amp;keywords=Code+Complete&amp;amp;qid=1592312147&amp;amp;sr=8-1&quot;&gt;Code Complete by Steve McConnell&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.es/Clean-Code-Handbook-Software-Craftsmanship/dp/0132350882/ref=sr_1_2?__mk_es_ES=%C3%85M%C3%85%C5%BD%C3%95%C3%91&amp;amp;dchild=1&amp;amp;keywords=Code+Complete&amp;amp;qid=1592312159&amp;amp;sr=8-2&quot;&gt;Clean Code by Robert M. Martin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.es/First-Design-Patterns-Brain-Friendly/dp/0596007124/ref=sr_1_1?__mk_es_ES=%C3%85M%C3%85%C5%BD%C3%95%C3%91&amp;amp;dchild=1&amp;amp;keywords=Head+First+Design+Patterns&amp;amp;qid=1592312172&amp;amp;sr=8-1&quot;&gt;Head First Design Patterns by Eric Freeman&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.es/Millionaire-Real-Estate-Investor/dp/0071446370/ref=sr_1_1?__mk_es_ES=%C3%85M%C3%85%C5%BD%C3%95%C3%91&amp;amp;dchild=1&amp;amp;keywords=The+Millionaire+Real+Estate+Investor&amp;amp;qid=1592312186&amp;amp;sr=8-1&quot;&gt;The Millionaire Real Estate Investor by Gary Keller&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.es/Rich-Dad-Poor-Robert-Kiyosaki/dp/1612680194/ref=sr_1_1?__mk_es_ES=%C3%85M%C3%85%C5%BD%C3%95%C3%91&amp;amp;dchild=1&amp;amp;keywords=Rich+Dad%2C+Poor+Dad&amp;amp;qid=1592312208&amp;amp;sr=8-1&quot;&gt;Rich Dad, Poor Dad by Robert Kiyosaki&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.es/No-Hype-Options-Trading-Realities-Strategies-ebook/dp/B004HFRFO8/ref=sr_1_fkmr0_1?__mk_es_ES=%C3%85M%C3%85%C5%BD%C3%95%C3%91&amp;amp;dchild=1&amp;amp;keywords=No-Hype+Options+Trading%3A+Myths%2C+Realities%2C+and+Strategies+That+Re-+eally+Work&amp;amp;qid=1592312223&amp;amp;sr=8-1-fkmr0&quot;&gt;No-Hype Options Trading: Myths, Realities, and Strategies That Re- eally Work by Kerry Given&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To sum up, totally recommended book, it can have sections more interesting than others depending on the reader but in general is really great.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Juan Pallarès</name><email>juan@pallares.me</email></author><category term="books" /><category term="soft skills" /><category term="software developer" /><category term="career" /><category term="personal brand" /><category term="blog" /><summary type="html">Some comments about the last book I read</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Browse blocking ads and trackers</title><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/browse-blocking-ads-and-trackers/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Browse blocking ads and trackers" /><published>2020-06-08T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-06-08T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://juan.pallares.me/browse-blocking-ads-and-trackers</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://juan.pallares.me/browse-blocking-ads-and-trackers/">&lt;p&gt;For the last months I have been using Brave as my browser for all my devices. The idea of having a Chrome fork that blocks ads and trackers seemed perfect. But Brave is not reliable at all:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://davidgerard.co.uk/blockchain/2020/06/06/the-brave-web-browser-is-hijacking-links-and-inserting-affiliate-codes/&quot;&gt;The Brave web browser is hijacking links, and inserting affiliate codes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not directly affected since I don’t use criptocurrency but a browser that markets itself like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It begins with giving you back power. Get unmatched speed, security and privacy by blocking trackers&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can not do this actions. The power to choose my affiliate code is taken away :unamused:.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since &lt;a href=&quot;https://clark.com/technology/google-chrome-do-not-track/&quot;&gt;Chrome and all his tracking&lt;/a&gt; is a no-go. I looked for a browser that cared about privacy and could have Dashlane and uBlock add-ons installed and I decided to go back to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mozilla.org/es-ES/firefox&quot;&gt;Mozilla Firefox&lt;/a&gt;. It was my browser years ago before Chrome arrived but before I continue let’s see what happens when you don’t block anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;ads&quot;&gt;Ads&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an sports website I usually visit with a browser that has no blocking configured:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/marca_browser.png&quot; alt=&quot;marca.com no block&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost 50% of the website real-state are ads, apart from being annoying it also makes the loading slower and uses more data (concerning if you pay per MB like some data plans). If you are wondering if in a portable devices gets better, let me tell you it does not:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tablet&quot;&gt;Tablet:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/marca_ipad.png&quot; alt=&quot;marca.com iPad&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;phone&quot;&gt;Phone:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/marca_phone.png&quot; alt=&quot;marca.com phone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used this site because the ads are really big and painful and I have even seen full screen ad-popups with a blurry X to close.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;trackers&quot;&gt;Trackers&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only the ads should worry you, you are also being tracked, for example in the same page we have:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/trackers.png&quot; alt=&quot;marca.com trackers&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“But Juan you are starting to be paranoid! Why do you worry about it? I don’t have anything to hide”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also thought this way in the past, but once I read about the experience of an Egyptian guy during the Arab spring and how his “Facebook likes” were used against him and detained and sent to prison. Charge? Political dissidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me quote this &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2013/feb/11/riot-software-tracked-online-social-networks&quot;&gt;The Guardian Article&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Today, it’s so easy that mass-surveillance is feasible – and so-called “big data” makes it seem tempting and innocuous.
The “big data” theory works like this: by grabbing hundreds or thousands of datapoints on millions of people, we build a systematic picture of how everyday people act. By analysing these by machine for “outliers”, or suspicious activity, we can catch the bad guys – and it’s OK, because only at that stage is another human being looking through your personal info.
&lt;strong&gt;This is, by and large, fantasy. For one thing, any algorithm will generate hundreds if not thousands of false positives&lt;/strong&gt; (innocent people who hit a red flag). Given how rare, say, terrorism is, the vast majority of people bothered by these systems will be ordinary people facing previously unbelievable intrusion.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trust me, better to block as much as possible. There is an area between living in a mountain like a buddhist monk and browsing with no block at all, find it and start making more difficult for them to spy on you. I say “more difficult” because I want to emphasize, is impossible not being tracked, even if you did not have an smartphone and use only Internet only for work purposes, the people around you would do the tracking for you, for example with the photos you appear in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-solution&quot;&gt;The solution&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here you have the same web with Firefox and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/ublock-origin/&quot;&gt;uBlock Origin&lt;/a&gt; add-on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/marca_adfree.png&quot; alt=&quot;marca.com ad free&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It loads faster and you get to see just the real content and good news, Firefox and uBlock can also be installed in iOS and Android. You can specify how strictily Firefox should block tracking. Another step to prevent tracking is using &lt;a href=&quot;https://duckduckgo.com/&quot;&gt;DuckDuckGo&lt;/a&gt; as default search engine. It comes already as an option in Firefox.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-next-level&quot;&gt;The next level&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You want to go to the next level? What if I told about &lt;strong&gt;network-wide ad blocking and faster browsing&lt;/strong&gt;? Meet &lt;a href=&quot;https://pi-hole.net/&quot;&gt;Pi-Hole&lt;/a&gt; .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/f9Rrghj6TDckb5nZZR/giphy.gif&quot; alt=&quot;next level funny gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://juan.pallares.me/raspberry-pi-hole-vpn/&quot;&gt;As I mentioned in the past&lt;/a&gt;, if you have a Raspberry Pi lying around this is one of the best uses you can do of it. Is a very active project, they recently released the &lt;a href=&quot;https://pi-hole.net/2020/05/10/pi-hole-v5-0-is-here/&quot;&gt;v5.0&lt;/a&gt;. For the screenshots with all the ads above I had to disable temporarily the PiHole apart from using Edge browser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are you blocking any ads? What is the browser you use? Don’t tell me the google analytics script running on this page will tell me this and more :smirk:.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Juan Pallarès</name><email>juan@pallares.me</email></author><category term="adblock" /><category term="ad" /><category term="tracking" /><category term="browser" /><category term="brave" /><category term="firefox" /><category term="chrome" /><category term="pihole" /><category term="ublock origin" /><summary type="html">Why and how I browse blocking ads and trackers</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Acknowledge your privilege</title><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/acknowledge-your-privilege/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Acknowledge your privilege" /><published>2020-06-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-06-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://juan.pallares.me/acknowledge-your-privilege</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://juan.pallares.me/acknowledge-your-privilege/">&lt;p&gt;This last days going through my Twitter timeline was really shocking. I hated what I was watching and I couldn’t stop watching it. How is it possible that in year 2020 in the most important country of the world, a reference for a lot of developing countries, a policeman can kill a man that is totally surredendered and saying that he can’t breathe…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I honestly don’t know what to do or say. I’m a white man, heterosexual, from a middle-class family in a developed country, tall (at least for Spanish standards) and even blonde with blue eyes (more on why this can be a privilege later). If you are phisically like me you should acknowledge how privileged we are, minorities are in clear disadvantage to us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe this couple videos can explain much better what I try to say:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/4K5fbQ1-zps&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Mqrhn8khGLM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the US, years of slavery and discrimination to black people create a gap that is really difficult to overcome, I believe this is one the reasons provoking  the recent events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why did I mention blonde and blue eyes before? What is standard of beauty (or has been until recent years)? white, blonde, straight hair, green/blue eyes. 
Think about it. Why are blue and green contact lenses sold? Why so many people dyes his hair blonde and straightens it? Only one very specific race is considered beautiful and the rest have to adapt! Check out the media, is changing I agree but some years ago it was impossible to a see a non-white actor with a leading role, even at latin american countries with most non-white population the TV was all white people, well sure you could have the black servants. This is a problem, you are placing a lot of people below by birth. Come on, even the band aids have the color of white skin! How come Jesus is so white being from the Midle-East? Last time I checked people over there were darker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going back to my environment, software engineers. Check out the results of the latest &lt;a href=&quot;https://insights.stackoverflow.com/survey/2020#developer-profile-gender-all-respondents2&quot;&gt;Stackoverflow 2020 survey&lt;/a&gt; released some days ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/developers-race.png&quot; alt=&quot;Race and Ethnicity&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have a long way to arrive to equality everywhere. We (white) have it really easy, just acknowledge it, as a first step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;police-brutality&quot;&gt;Police brutality&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something I don’t want to miss is police brutality and the people that justifies it just because: &lt;em&gt;“Hey! they have been insulted and had objects thrown at them for hours, what would you do?!”&lt;/em&gt;. I don’t mind! They have to be able to put up with all of this and more, nothing justifies the atrocities seen in some videos. Somebody breaks the law? Just handcuff him and take him away. How can they be so violent with people just walking? It reminds me of recent events in Barcelona where we had also our take of police brutality. Again, I will quote someone that explains better what I mean:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;I’m perplexed by the replies defending police actions because of some “other side” doing something.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;If someone commits a crime, that doesn’t mean it’s okay for the police to start punching random peaceful people on the street. They don’t get to be “annoyed”, that’s their job.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Dan Abramov (@dan_abramov) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/dan_abramov/status/1267151390578749441?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;May 31, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple movies I saw recently that can help understand the problem, both based in true stories:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imdb.com/title/tt6285944/&quot;&gt;The Banker&lt;/a&gt; - In the 1960s two African-American entrepreneurs hire a working-class white man to pretend to be the head of their business empire while they pose as a janitor and chauffeur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imdb.com/title/tt4916630/?ref_=tt_sims_tt&quot;&gt;Just Mercy&lt;/a&gt; - World-renowned civil rights defense attorney Bryan Stevenson works to free a wrongly condemned death row prisoner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally I want to send all my support and love to the protesters #BlackLivesMatter&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Juan Pallarès</name><email>juan@pallares.me</email></author><category term="blacklivesmatter" /><category term="white" /><category term="privileges" /><category term="george" /><category term="floyd" /><summary type="html">My humble opinion about George Floyd killing and white privilege</summary></entry></feed>