<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2021-01-23T21:19:14+01:00</updated><id>https://juan.pallares.me/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Juan Pallarès Garbí</title><subtitle>Landing page.</subtitle><author><name>Juan Pallarès</name><email>juan@pallares.me</email></author><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">serverless common issues and errors</title><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/serverless-common-issues-and-errors/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="serverless common issues and errors" /><published>2021-01-23T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-01-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://juan.pallares.me/serverless-common-issues-and-errors</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://juan.pallares.me/serverless-common-issues-and-errors/">&lt;p&gt;At my job, we have had recurring issues with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.serverless.com/&quot;&gt;serverless&lt;/a&gt; that have slowed down us frequently. This guide aims to avoid that by compiling the main pain points we have experienced. Keep in mind we use AWS and Gitlab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;avoid-gitlab-protected-variables&quot;&gt;Avoid gitlab protected variables&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When configuring Serverless to be deployed from Gitlab CI/CD. &lt;strong&gt;Remember to not set AWS env variables as protected&lt;/strong&gt; (default option) since it will make the deployment fail and &lt;strong&gt;it won’t give you a meaningful error&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/gitlabProtectedVariables.png&quot; alt=&quot;Gitlab protected variables&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;serverless-offline-plugins-order-is-important&quot;&gt;Serverless offline plugins order is important&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plugins order in serverless.yml matters. Rule of thumb, &lt;strong&gt;serverless offline should be always one of the latest&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/PluginsOrder.png&quot; alt=&quot;Plugins Order&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;serverless-custom-domain&quot;&gt;Serverless custom domain&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To configure the deployment to sandbox and to production AWS in custom domain you can use the plugin &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/serverless-domain-manager&quot;&gt;serverless-domain-manager&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Keep in mind, before being able to deploy you have to call (only once per domain)&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sls create_domain --aws-profile LAT-serverless-cheetah-bff --stage production&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key point is specifying the stage when deploying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;serverless deploy --stage staging&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;using-aws-credentials-locally&quot;&gt;Using AWS credentials locally&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check the file in ~/.aws. There you should configure different credentials depending on the IAM user/AWS account. If no profile is called, the default will be used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/AWSaccessKey.png&quot; alt=&quot;AWS Access Key&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then later you can use them like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sls deploy --stage production --aws-profile LAT-serverless-cheetah-bff&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;serverless-dynamodb-locally&quot;&gt;Serverless DynamoDB Locally&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two plugins are needed &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/99x/serverless-dynamodb-local&quot;&gt;serverless-dynamodb-local&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/serverless-dynamodb-client&quot;&gt;serverless-dynamodb-client&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;strong&gt;After installing the packages the normal way. You have to install it to serverless&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sls dynamodb install&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then to make it work we used to terminals. In one we run &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sls dynamodb start --migrate&lt;/code&gt;, in the second one we run &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sls offline&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;serverless-dotenv---environment-variables&quot;&gt;Serverless Dotenv - Environment variables&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To use environment variables locally, &lt;strong&gt;do not use dotenv package&lt;/strong&gt;. Use &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.serverless.com/plugins/serverless-dotenv-plugin&quot;&gt;serverless-dotenv-plugin&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;import-issues---failure-xxxxxxdefault-is-not-a-constructor&quot;&gt;Import issues - Failure: xxxxxx.default is not a constructor&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only way we could fix this issue was doing require instead of import. Most probably an issue with not properly configured &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;tsconfig.json&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the problematic imports use:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;const pLimit = require('p-limit');&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;instead of&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;import pLimit from 'p-limit';&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;include-json-files-in-build&quot;&gt;Include JSON files in build&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If using typescript and JSON files, you will need to include this files so they are copied to the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.build&lt;/code&gt; folder in the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;serverless.yml&lt;/code&gt; file:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;package:
    include:
        - localizations/\*.json
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you experienced any other issue? My main concern is that the errors messages are not clear enough.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Juan Pallarès</name><email>juan@pallares.me</email></author><category term="serverless" /><category term="issues" /><category term="common" /><category term="errors" /><summary type="html">protected variables, custom domains, plugins order, using it locally...</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="es"><title type="html">Balance 2020</title><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/balance-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Balance 2020" /><published>2021-01-03T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-01-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://juan.pallares.me/balance-2020</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://juan.pallares.me/balance-2020/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;mirando-el-lado-positivo&quot;&gt;Mirando el lado positivo&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Es común reflexionar al final del año de como ha ido todo, hacer un balance. Por lo general, con la pandemia ha sido un año horroroso pero aún así hay que intentar sacar siempre lo positivo. Ahí van algunas reflexiones aleatorias:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Soy más social de lo que me pensaba, el confinamiento y el trabajo remoto me ha hecho extrañar mucho la oficina y las relaciones sociales que se crean allí.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Por otro lado, cuando te vas adaptando y no estas confinado, el trabajo remoto da mucha flexibilidad y lo empiezas a apreciar/disfrutar.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Me cuesta una barbaridad entrenar en casa. El tipo de entremientos que me gustan son estilo crossfit o directamente barra y kg. Sin pesos y con la única compañia de la pareja y/o vecino ha sido difícil. Aún así he seguido entrenando y trackeando el progreso. Además he probado el plan de entrenamiento 5/3/1 y lo he incorporado junto al crossfit.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Empecé este año a invertir de forma indexada, justo un año que la economía se ha hundido pero por suerte he acabado con un 10% de rentabilidad, nada mal. Ya dedicaré un post a esto y las causas principales, seguramente cuando haga el rebalanceo anual.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;He vuelto a adquirir el hábito de la lectura, &lt;a href=&quot;https://juan.pallares.me/books/&quot;&gt;varios libros leídos&lt;/a&gt; más uno in progress (no hago una entrada sobre todos).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;También he vuelto a escribir en este blog. 17 nuevas entradas este año, empezando en abril. Sin target claro, temas variadísimos, la única meta: escribir con frecuencia.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Es obvio pero no deja de sorpredener la cantidad de dinero ahorrado cuando no puedes salir de casa y el único gasto es comer. Ayuda a poner en perspectiva la importancia de según que gastos.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;las-entradas-más-vistas&quot;&gt;Las entradas más vistas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No tengo ningún objetivo definido a nivel de número de visitas, tráfico del blog, etc. pero si me gusta mirar estadísticas. Vamos a repasar los reports de Google Analytics:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/mostVisitedPages.png&quot; alt=&quot;Most visited pages&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aparte de la pagina principal, las dos entrada más visitadas en 2020 son:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://juan.pallares.me/configure-jekyll-multi-language-without-plugin/&quot;&gt;Configure Jekyll to be multi-language without plugins&lt;/a&gt; y su &lt;a href=&quot;https://juan.pallares.me/configura-jekyll-multi-idioma-sin-plugin/&quot;&gt;version en castellano&lt;/a&gt; es la cuarta. Esto me lo podía medio imaginar, no hay una forma fácil/clara de hacer jekyll multidioma y mucha gente interesada en hacerlo.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://juan.pallares.me/no-funciona-intellisense-en-sql-server/&quot;&gt;No funciona Intellisense en SQL Server Management Studio 2008&lt;/a&gt;. Esta si que sorprende más. &lt;strong&gt;Es una entrada del 2012!&lt;/strong&gt; y &lt;a href=&quot;https://juan.pallares.me/moving-to-jekyll/&quot;&gt;la migré del antiguo blog en Blogger&lt;/a&gt; de casualidad. Obviamente las visitas llegan todas via Google (nadie llega a las quinta página) y deduzco que la causa de tantas visitas es que el título tiene muy buen SEO y es un problema que necesita solución aún en 2020. Nunca imaginé que una entrada tan chorra estaría como la segunda más visitada.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Si ignoramos books, que es un apartado más que una entrada llegamos a &lt;a href=&quot;https://juan.pallares.me/raspberry-pi-autodownloader/&quot;&gt;Raspberry Pi autodownloader&lt;/a&gt;. Esta entrada con mejor título sería más visitada seguramente pero bueno aún así tiene el tercer puesto siendo una entrada de 2017.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;desde-donde-llegan-las-visitas&quot;&gt;Desde donde llegan las visitas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suelo poner un link a cada nueva entrada en Twitter y en LinkedIn. Aún así, la mayoría de visitas vienen via organic search, es decir, búsquedas en Google.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/usersOrigin.png&quot; alt=&quot;Visitors source&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Por último, como curiosidad, parece que la inmensa mayoría de visitas vienen de España seguidos por USA. Un saludo para los lectores chinos! 🤣&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/countryOfOrigin.png&quot; alt=&quot;Visitors country of origin&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Juan Pallarès</name><email>juan@pallares.me</email></author><category term="year" /><category term="analysis" /><category term="popular posts" /><summary type="html">Lo más leído del año</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Book - Atomic Habits - James Clear</title><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/atomic-habits-james-clear/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Book - Atomic Habits - James Clear" /><published>2020-12-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-12-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://juan.pallares.me/atomic-habits-james-clear</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://juan.pallares.me/atomic-habits-james-clear/">&lt;p&gt;2021 is starting soon and with it the usual new year resolutions. &lt;em&gt;I’m going to eat healthier&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;I’m going to the gym this year for sure!&lt;/em&gt;. Once March arrives no resolution has survived. Why is it so difficult to create healthy habits? New habits in general?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.es/Atomic-Habits-Proven-Build-Break/dp/1847941834&quot;&gt;Atomic Habits&lt;/a&gt; is the answer. A book that even if most things that are mentioned can be obvious I couldn’t stop highlighting interesting quotes. It took me a month to read but could have been days. It starts every chapter with a story that captures your attention and it is used as an example of the concept that is going to be explained and then closed with a summary, something my engineer/order freak mind loves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;compound-interest&quot;&gt;Compound interest&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Compound Interest concept is mainly used in economic terms, &lt;a href=&quot;http://pallares.me/why-i-became-a-bogglehead/&quot;&gt;when investing long-term&lt;/a&gt; is one of the keys for having great benefits. But the concept can be applied to almost everything and in this book it’s applied to self-improvement, acquiring good habits. That’s why with tiny changes you get remarkable results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/compoundinterest.png&quot; alt=&quot;Compound Interest Diagram&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cue---craving---response---reward&quot;&gt;Cue -&amp;gt; Craving -&amp;gt; Response -&amp;gt; Reward&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are 4 steps involved in any habit:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;cue&lt;/strong&gt; is about &lt;strong&gt;noticing&lt;/strong&gt; the reward.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;craving&lt;/strong&gt; is about &lt;strong&gt;wanting&lt;/strong&gt; the reward.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;response&lt;/strong&gt; is about &lt;strong&gt;obtaining&lt;/strong&gt; the reward.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We chase &lt;strong&gt;rewards&lt;/strong&gt; because they serve two purposes: (1) they &lt;strong&gt;satisfy&lt;/strong&gt; us and (2) they &lt;strong&gt;teach&lt;/strong&gt; us.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To improve the way we manage habits, we need to work with these 4 steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-is-it-so-difficult-to-change-our-habits&quot;&gt;Why is it so difficult to change our habits?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Changing our habits is challenging for two reasons: (1) we try to change the wrong thing and (2) we try to change our habits in the wrong way. If you want better results, then forget about setting goals. Focus on your system instead. Focus on your identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outcomes are about what you get. Processes are about what you do. Identity is about what you believe. We usually say, &lt;em&gt;“I’ll do sport every day”&lt;/em&gt; instead it should be &lt;em&gt;“I’m a fit person”&lt;/em&gt;. The focus is who we wish to become.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/LayersOfBehaviorChange.png&quot; alt=&quot;Layers of Behavior Change Diagram&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of acting from the outside to the inside. We have to create our identity and it will change the outer layers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/IdentityBasedHabits.png&quot; alt=&quot;Identity-Based Habits Diagram&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we have an identity, it will be very conflicting for us to act against it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-create-a-good-habit---4-laws-of-behavioral-change&quot;&gt;How to create a Good Habit - 4 Laws of behavioral change&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For creating a good habit, we have to use the 4 Laws of behavioral change.
&lt;strong&gt;Make it obvious, attractive, easy and satisfying.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cardinal Rule of Behavior Change: What is rewarded is repeated. What is punished is avoided. You learn what to do in the future based on what you were rewarded for doing (or punished for doing) in the past. Positive emotions cultivate habits. Negative emotions destroy them.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Add a little bit of immediate pleasure to the habits that pay off in the long-run and a little bit of immediate pain to ones that don’t.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I’m going to copy-paste the final version of the summary that James Clear creates after every chapter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1st Law: Make it &lt;strong&gt;obvious&lt;/strong&gt;.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1.1 Fill out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/jamesclear/Atomic+Habits/The+Habits+Scorecard.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Habits Scorecard&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Write down your current habits to become aware of them.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1.2 Use &lt;strong&gt;implementation intentions&lt;/strong&gt;: “I will [BEHAVIOR] at [TIME] in [LOCATION].”&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1.3 Use &lt;strong&gt;habit stacking&lt;/strong&gt;: “After [CURRENT HABIT], I will [NEW HABIT].”&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1.4 Design your &lt;strong&gt;environment&lt;/strong&gt;. Make the cues of good habits obvious and visible.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2nd Law: Make it &lt;strong&gt;attractive&lt;/strong&gt;.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2.1 Use &lt;strong&gt;temptation bundling&lt;/strong&gt;. Pair an action you want to do with an action you need to do.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2.2 Join a &lt;strong&gt;culture&lt;/strong&gt; where your desired behavior is the normal behavior.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2.3 Create a &lt;strong&gt;motivation ritual&lt;/strong&gt;. Do something you enjoy immediately before a difficult habit.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;3rd Law: Make it &lt;strong&gt;easy&lt;/strong&gt;.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;3.1 &lt;strong&gt;Reduce friction&lt;/strong&gt;. Decrease the number of steps between you and your good habits.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;3.2 Prime the &lt;strong&gt;environment&lt;/strong&gt;. Prepare your environment to make future actions easier.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;3.3 &lt;strong&gt;Master the decisive moment&lt;/strong&gt;. Optimize the small choices that deliver outsized impact.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;3.4 Use the &lt;strong&gt;Two-Minute Rule&lt;/strong&gt;. Downscale your habits until they can be done in two minutes or less.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;3.5 &lt;strong&gt;Automate&lt;/strong&gt; your habits. Invest in technology and onetime purchases that lock in future behavior.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;4th Law: Make it &lt;strong&gt;satisfying&lt;/strong&gt;.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;4.1 Use &lt;strong&gt;reinforcement&lt;/strong&gt;. Give yourself an immediate reward when you complete your habit.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;4.2 Make “doing nothing” enjoyable. When avoiding a bad habit, design a way to see the benefits.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;4.3 Use a &lt;strong&gt;habit tracker&lt;/strong&gt;. Keep track of your habit streak and “don’t break the chain.”.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;4.4 &lt;strong&gt;Never miss twice&lt;/strong&gt;. When you forget to do a habit, make sure you get back on track immediately.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the book, it goes over all these laws and explains with examples how to do it and why it’s useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;quitting-bad-habits&quot;&gt;Quitting bad Habits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also explains how to quit bad habits, as you guessed is doing the opposite actions you do for acquiring good habits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inversion of the 1st Law: Make it &lt;strong&gt;invisible&lt;/strong&gt;.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1.5 &lt;strong&gt;Reduce exposure&lt;/strong&gt;. Remove the cues of your bad habits from your environment.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inversion of the 2nd Law: Make it &lt;strong&gt;unattractive&lt;/strong&gt;.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2.4 &lt;strong&gt;Reframe your mind-set&lt;/strong&gt;. Highlight the benefits of avoiding your bad habits.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inversion of the 3rd Law: Make it &lt;strong&gt;difficult&lt;/strong&gt;.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;3.6 &lt;strong&gt;Increase friction&lt;/strong&gt;. Increase the number of steps between you and your bad habits.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;3.7 Use a &lt;strong&gt;commitment device&lt;/strong&gt;. Restrict your future choices to the ones that benefit you.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inversion of the 4th Law: Make it &lt;strong&gt;unsatisfying&lt;/strong&gt;.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;4.5 Get an &lt;strong&gt;accountability partner&lt;/strong&gt;. Ask someone to watch your behavior.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;4.6 Create a &lt;strong&gt;habit contract&lt;/strong&gt;. Make the costs of your bad habits public and painful.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;powerful-concepts&quot;&gt;Powerful concepts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I’m gonna go over some quotes that I liked specially from the book. &lt;a href=&quot;https://juan.pallares.me/books/atomic-habits-tiny-changes-remarkable-results/&quot;&gt;Find all the quotes here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;no-freedom-will-i-become-a-robot&quot;&gt;No freedom? Will I become a robot?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people can be concerned with all these habits, it seems to be too much planning, no room for improvising? being original?:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Such questions set up a false dichotomy. They make you think that you have to choose between building habits and attaining freedom. In reality, the two complement each other. Habits do not restrict freedom. They create it. In fact, the people who don’t have their habits handled are often the ones with the least amount of freedom. Without good financial habits, you will always be struggling for the next dollar. Without good health habits, you will always seem to be short on energy. Without good learning habits, you will always feel like you’re behind the curve.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tremendous-self-control-or-less-temptations&quot;&gt;Tremendous self-control or less temptations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I never have pastries, ice-cream or other sugar-added foods at home, why? if they are there I can’t resist eating them for long. I try to be the less time possible in tempting situations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;When scientists analyze people who appear to have tremendous self-control, it turns out those individuals aren’t all that different from those who are struggling. Instead, “disciplined” people are better at structuring their lives in a way that does not require heroic willpower and self-control. In other words, they spend less time in tempting situations.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;similar-concepts-to-gtd&quot;&gt;Similar concepts to GTD&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently read the &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Getting Things Done book&lt;/a&gt; and I found some ideas linked from both books. One of the benefits of GTD is getting clarity, you know what to do next, in Atomic Habits is mentioned that many people believe they lack motivation when what they really lack is clarity. For example, making decisions about simple tasks like when should I work out, where do I go to write, when do I pay the bills provokes that you have less time for freedom. Also, we often say yes to little requests because we are not clear enough about what we need to be doing instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another similar concept is doing it perfectly or not doing it. I also consider it “Analysis paralysis”. Both books enforce starting simple and get better with time. In the habits world, it’s really important to accumulate reps, the more you do the more you forge your identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It is easy to get bogged down trying to find the optimal plan for change: the fastest way to lose weight, the best program to build muscle, the perfect idea for a side hustle. We are so focused on figuring out the best approach that we never get around to taking action. As Voltaire once wrote, “The best is the enemy of the good.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;personal-experience&quot;&gt;Personal experience&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I already did some of the actions suggested. I usually go to the gym in the early morning and I tend to leave everything ready (clothes, bag, etc.) the night before so there is no friction/excuses in the morning. I tend to plan my training routine, so there is commitment and clarity, I avoid the “What should I do now?”. I also followed the rule of “Never miss twice” even without knowing about it. I’m known by my friends as a gym rat so I guess it’s my identity already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also limit myself to one chapter per day from Netflix (this one is hard) or read for at least 30 minutes before sleeping, trying to increase the time and situations for reading, but step by step.
Even this blog post you are reading is part of a new habit I’m trying to build. &lt;del&gt;I want to write often&lt;/del&gt; I want to be a writer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something I tried to implement is using less social media. I used to go over Instagram and Twitter feeds too often. It was super easy having it on the phone ready to be checked and opened and also with the notification in case you happen to ignore it for some time. I discovered myself at the toilet checking the phone while brushing my teeth, that can’t be right. Hardcore solution, deleting both apps from the phone. Having them only on the iPad made it uncomfortable and I checked it once or twice per day. After some days like that, I evolved to use the web version of both apps, which are more slow and difficult to use (there is still friction) and I use them less frequently than before but I can use them when I’m away from the iPad. Something positive of Instagram web version, no ads :).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another bad habits on my radar:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The way I sit down which is clearly wrong and created back pain.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Eating super fast.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll try to use the learnings of the book to improve there. What is your experience with habits/resolutions? What would you like to start/stop doing?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Juan Pallarès</name><email>juan@pallares.me</email></author><category term="books" /><category term="amotic" /><category term="habits" /><category term="productivity" /><summary type="html">Tiny changes - Remarkable results</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="es"><title type="html">Necesitas un gestor de contraseñas</title><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/necesitas-un-gestor-de-contrasenas/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Necesitas un gestor de contraseñas" /><published>2020-12-12T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-12-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://juan.pallares.me/necesitas-un-gestor-de-contrasenas</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://juan.pallares.me/necesitas-un-gestor-de-contrasenas/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;problema&quot;&gt;Problema&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Es muy común tener una o dos contraseñas para todo. Para el mail, para Netflix, para Amazon, para el usuario del ordenador. Incluso algunos se vienen arriba y usan la misma contraseña pero van cambiando algo al final, indetectable! deben pensar. Cuando avisas que eso es muy poco seguro la respuesta es:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pero si tengo muchas se me olvidan!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Estoy de acuerdo, son díficiles de recordar tantas contraseñas y más cuando nos piden que tengan números, símbolos, mayúsculas, sangre de uniconrnio, etc. Y no hablemos de los &lt;a href=&quot;https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/Captcha&quot;&gt;CAPTCHA&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/captcha.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;meme CAPTCHA&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;El problema con reutilizar la contraseña es muy sencillo de entender. Imagina esta situación:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hace mucho tiempo te registraste en “foro pepito” para preguntar algo, te contestaron y ya nunca más volviste a entrar.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Al cabo de un tiempo, un ataque consigue las contraseñas de todos los usuarios de “foro pepito”. A “foro pepito” nunca le preocupó la seguridad de sus usuarios.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;En el registro del foro piden email, por lo que lo hackers lo siguiente que hacen es intentar entrar en todos las cuentas más famosas con ese correo y contraseña robada.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ya has perdido todas las cuentas que compartían contraseña. Si solo cambias un número al final o algo muy obvio, es muy probable que también lo prueben.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;solución&quot;&gt;Solución&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Posiblemente pienses que con guardar las contraseñas en el navegador es suficiente, pero no es un método igual de seguro. Además, solo estarán en un dispositivo, te tocará escribirlas en el móvil o en otro ordenador.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Usa un gestor de contraseñas&lt;/strong&gt;. Tendrás que acordate de una sola contraseña y el resto las puedes autogenerar largas y complicadas porque no tendrás que escribirlas, el gestor lo hará por ti. No sabes lo cómodo que se convierte navegar hasta que lo usas. En el móvil además si tienes lector de huellas es una gozada.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Además, los hay gratuítos y que funcionan muy bien. En mi caso, estoy usando &lt;a href=&quot;https://bitwarden.com/&quot;&gt;Bitwarden&lt;/a&gt;. Lo tengo instalado en todos mis dispositivos, se sincroniza, me autorellena usuario y contraseña de las páginas y tiene generador de contraseñas.
He probado varios más (Lastpass, 1password…). Usé &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dashlane.com/&quot;&gt;Dashlane&lt;/a&gt; durante dos años y es francamente mejor que Bitwarden, pero se paga. Te notifica cuando ha habido ataques en paginas donde tu tienes cuenta, tiene VPN y se integra mejor con los navegadores. Además estan ganando tanta fuerza que hicieron el famoso anuncio de la Superbowl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/B5lslSPfhkg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mi sugerencia, prueba con uno gratuíto y si ves que con el tiempo se te queda pequeño, haz el upgrade. Todos suelen permitir exportar y importar todos los datos para cambiar fácilmente de gestor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cómo-es-una-buena-contraseña&quot;&gt;Cómo es una buena contraseña&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LARGA&lt;/strong&gt;, conforme más larga, más segura. Por ejemplo, MiPerroTobyLadraMucho es muchísimo más segura que S0yH4cker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/tiempo-password.png&quot; alt=&quot;Tabla de tiempos de crackeo de contraseñas&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Y, por favor, no uses tu cumpleaños, tu nombre, tu DNI o otros datos que se pueden obtener fácilmente. Tampoco uses las que usa todo el mundo:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/Spain-Most-Used-Passwords.png&quot; alt=&quot;contraseñas mas usadas de España&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.safetydetectives.com/blog/the-most-hacked-passwords-in-the-world/&quot;&gt;Fuente&lt;/a&gt; y &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.osi.es/es/contrasenas&quot;&gt;Fuente&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Juan Pallarès</name><email>juan@pallares.me</email></author><category term="password" /><category term="manager" /><category term="dashlane" /><category term="bitwarden" /><summary type="html">Navega más seguro y recuerda solo una contraseña.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Book - Factfulness - Hans Rosling, Ola Rosling, Anna Rosling</title><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/factfulness/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Book - Factfulness - Hans Rosling, Ola Rosling, Anna Rosling" /><published>2020-09-27T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-09-27T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://juan.pallares.me/factfulness</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://juan.pallares.me/factfulness/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-gapminder-test&quot;&gt;The Gapminder Test&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I start commenting on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/-/es/Hans-Rosling/dp/1250107814&quot;&gt;Factfulness&lt;/a&gt; I would like you to do &lt;a href=&quot;https://forms.gapminder.org/s3/test-2018&quot;&gt;the gapminder online test&lt;/a&gt;. The book starts the same way, asking you to answer the questionnaire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How did you perform? If it was bad, do not worry. World leaders who should have more context about these trends perform below than a monkey would do (what the author uses to refer to answering randomly the test). The world is better than we think, why do we have such negative thoughts about it?.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Factfulness is one of Bill Gates favorite books. He thinks it’s so important to read it that he decided to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodnet.org/articles/bill-gates-gifts-graduates-his-favorite-book-on-positivity&quot;&gt;give it away to all 2018 American graduates&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, I added all the quotes I found interesting &lt;a href=&quot;https://juan.pallares.me/books/factfulness/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Let’s deep dive into Factulness, a book so interesting I read it just in some days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;10-biases&quot;&gt;10 biases&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facts over feelings. That’s the book in three words. Hans shows publicly available data, usually ignored, in eye-catchy graphics to demonstrate how pessimistic we are. Why are we this way?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We, as humans, have 10 different instincts that prevent us from analyzing the world factfully. Is important to know them and to master the ability to disabling them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-the-gap-instinct&quot;&gt;1. The &lt;strong&gt;Gap&lt;/strong&gt; Instinct.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reality is often not polarized at all. Usually, the majority is right there in the middle, where the gap is supposed to be. We tend to divide the countries in developed and non-developed. The author divides them into 4 levels ordered by income per person. Guess which levels are the more crowded? The ones in the middle, 2 and 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-the-negativity-instinct&quot;&gt;2. The &lt;strong&gt;Negativity&lt;/strong&gt; Instinct.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information about bad news is much more likely to reach us. When things are getting better we often don’t hear about them. This gives us a too-negative impression of the world. Things can be bad and improving. Example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The PIN code of the world is 1-1-1-4. That’s how to remember the map. From left to right, the number of billions, as a PIN code. Americas: 1, Europe: 1, Africa: 1, Asia: 4. (I have rounded the numbers.) Like all PIN codes, this one will change. By the end of this century, the UN expects there to have been almost no change in the Americas and Europe but 3 billion more people in Africa and 1 billion more in Asia. By 2100 the new PIN code of the world will be 1-1-4-5. More than 80 percent of the world’s population will live in Africa and Asia.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/world_pin_code.png&quot; alt=&quot;world pin code&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Think of the world as a premature baby in an incubator. The baby’s health status is extremely bad and her breathing, heart rate, and other important signs are tracked constantly so that changes for better or worse can quickly be seen. After a week, she is getting a lot better. On all the main measures, she is improving, but she still has to stay in the incubator because her health is still critical. Does it make sense to say that the infant’s situation is improving? Yes. Absolutely. Does it make sense to say it is bad? Yes, absolutely. Does saying “things are improving” imply that everything is fine, and we should all relax and not worry? No, not at all. Is it helpful to have to choose between bad and improving? Definitely not. It’s both. It’s both bad and better. Better, and bad, at the same time.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-the-straight-line-instinct&quot;&gt;3. The &lt;strong&gt;Straight Line&lt;/strong&gt; Instinct.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Curves (in data graphics) come in different shapes. Don’t assume it will continue straight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-the-fear-instinct&quot;&gt;4. The &lt;strong&gt;Fear&lt;/strong&gt; Instinct.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frightening things get our attention. Remember these are not necessarily the riskiest. Our natural fears (genetic) make us overestimate these risks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;5-the-size-instinct&quot;&gt;5. The &lt;strong&gt;Size&lt;/strong&gt; Instinct.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a lonely number seems impressive. Compare it with another relevant number. Get things in proportion. Example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I had for some time been appalled by the systematic blaming of climate change on China and India based on total emissions per nation. It was like claiming that obesity was worse in China than in the United States because the total bodyweight of the Chinese population was higher than that of the US population.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;6-the-generalization-instinct&quot;&gt;6. The &lt;strong&gt;Generalization&lt;/strong&gt; Instinct.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generalization can’t be stopped but we can check if the use is correct. Look for differences within groups, similarities across groups and differences across groups. Example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It makes no sense to talk about “African countries” and “Africa’s problems” and yet people do, all the time. It leads to ridiculous outcomes like Ebola in Liberia and Sierra Leone affecting tourism in Kenya, a 100-hour drive across the continent. That is farther than London to Tehran.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;7-the-destiny-instinct&quot;&gt;7. The &lt;strong&gt;Destiny&lt;/strong&gt; Instinct.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slow change is still change. Slow changes gradually add up to big changes. Don’t think something (country, culture, etc.) remains constant because the change is small.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;8-the-single-perspective-instinct&quot;&gt;8. The &lt;strong&gt;Single Perspective&lt;/strong&gt; Instinct.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Get a toolbox, not a hammer. Single perspective can limit your imagination. Look at problems from different angles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;9-the-blame-instinct&quot;&gt;9. The &lt;strong&gt;Blame&lt;/strong&gt; Instinct.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blaming an individual often steals the focus from other possible explanations and blocks our ability to prevent similar problems in the future. Resist finding a scapegoat and notice when one is being used,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;10-the-urgency-instinct&quot;&gt;10. The &lt;strong&gt;Urgency&lt;/strong&gt; Instinct.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rarely a decision is urgent. Take a breath. Insist on data. Be careful of taking drastic actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;world-future---economic-shift&quot;&gt;World future - Economic shift&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my favorite parts of the book is when the population growth forecast are analyzed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If the UN forecasts for population growth are correct, and if incomes in Asia and Africa keep growing as now, then the center of gravity of the world market will shift over the next 20 years from the Atlantic to the Indian Ocean. Today, the people living in rich countries around the North Atlantic, who represent 11 percent of the world population, make up 60 percent of the Level 4 consumer market. Already by 2027, if incomes keep growing worldwide as they are doing now, then that figure will have shrunk to 50 percent. By 2040, 60 percent of Level 4 consumers will live outside the West. Yes, &lt;strong&gt;I think the Western domination of the world economy will soon be over&lt;/strong&gt;. People in North America and Europe need to understand that most of the world population lives in Asia. In terms of economic muscles “we” are becoming the 20 percent, not the 80 percent. But many of “us” can’t fit these numbers into our nostalgic minds. Not only do we misjudge how big our war monuments should be in Vietnam, we also misjudge our importance in the future global marketplace. Many of us forget to behave properly with those who will control the future trade deals.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is some food for thought. How easily we ignore all other countries while we are on top but…for how long? A couple more quotes in the same direction:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In sales and marketing, if you run a big business in Europe or the United States, you and your employees need to understand that the world market of the future will be growing primarily in Asia and Africa, not at home.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In making investment decisions, you need to shake off any naïve views of Africa shaped by the colonial past (and maintained by today’s media) and understand that Ghana, Nigeria, and Kenya are where some of the best investment opportunities can be found today.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fake-news&quot;&gt;Fake news&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowadays is common to receive all kind of fake news, rumors, clickbait. For this reason, I see even more value in reading this book. I’m pretty sure that with a population that knew more about all this instincts and how to tackle them, some presidential elections would have gone differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;width:100%;height:0;padding-bottom:93%;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://giphy.com/embed/26tknCqiJrBQG6bxC&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; style=&quot;position:absolute&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;giphy-embed&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://giphy.com/gifs/election2016-election-2016-presidential-debate-26tknCqiJrBQG6bxC&quot;&gt;via GIPHY&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Easy to read. Interesting, funny, and revealing experiences from the author around the world. Great summaries after every chapter. Do you love data? 100% recommended. Better to read it in a tablet than in a e-reader because of the graphics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Juan Pallarès</name><email>juan@pallares.me</email></author><category term="books" /><category term="factfulness" /><category term="facts" /><category term="fake news" /><category term="clickbait" /><summary type="html">Ten reasons we're wrong about the world and why things are better than you think</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Book - Getting Things Done. The Art of Stress-free Productivity - David Allen</title><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/getting-things-done/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Book - Getting Things Done. The Art of Stress-free Productivity - David Allen" /><published>2020-08-29T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-08-29T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://juan.pallares.me/getting-things-done</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://juan.pallares.me/getting-things-done/">&lt;p&gt;Do you have a TODO list? Have you ever used one? Do you remember that time you had so many things to do and the moment you wrote all down in a list you felt much more in control and relaxed? You can learn how to properly manage all your professional and personal life in the last book I read &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.es/Getting-Things-Done-Arts-Stresss/dp/0349408947/ref=sr_1_1?__mk_es_ES=%C3%85M%C3%85%C5%BD%C3%95%C3%91&amp;amp;dchild=1&amp;amp;keywords=getting+things+done&amp;amp;qid=1598698866&amp;amp;sr=8-1&quot;&gt;Getting Things Done The Art of Stress-free Productivity by David Allen&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to admit, the book feels old. It talks a lot about filers (who uses that?), trays with physical documents, bills and a lot of hand-writing. Well, it was 1st published in 2001 and, even if I read a more modern edition, the feeling is there. Having said that, in my opinion, the main learnings are timeless and universal. I will quote a quote (Inception) from the book that explains this better: 
&lt;em&gt;As to methods there may be a million and then some, but principles are few. The man who grasps principles can successfully select his own methods. The man who tries methods, ignoring principles, is sure to have trouble.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I added the quotes I picked while reading in &lt;a href=&quot;https://juan.pallares.me/books/getting-things-done/&quot;&gt;this section&lt;/a&gt;. Let me go in detail about the parts I liked more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/inception-meme.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Inception meme&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;write-everything-down&quot;&gt;Write everything down&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the key concept of the book. Write down every task, idea, concept that crosses your mind and you feel can/could be important. Our brain is meant to have ideas not  to keep all these reminders there. It will generate stress. Implementing this tecnique you will have three benefits:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Less stress.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Being present. Not trying to remember what you wanted to do.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Actually remembering things because they are written down.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-steps-capture---clarify---organize---reflect---engage&quot;&gt;5 steps. Capture - Clarify - Organize - Reflect - Engage&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/gtd-clarify-flow.png&quot; alt=&quot;Diagram of GTD flow, how to process tasks&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Capture.&lt;/strong&gt;
As mentioned before, capture everything. While reading this post has your mind wandered off into something not related? maybe it’s a pending task that you have not yet captured.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clarify.&lt;/strong&gt;
Is it really a task? What should be done?. At this moment you have more time to think about the tasks you captured.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Organize.&lt;/strong&gt;
Notice in this step the task can evolve to project (multi-task), can be done at that moment (less than two minutes), can be delegated or postponed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reflect.&lt;/strong&gt;
This should be done at least once a week (weekly Review). Analyze all your pending tasks, projects, etc and refine them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Engage.&lt;/strong&gt;
Do the tasks at the moment they have to be done. Call the mechanic!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;organize-tasks-depending-on-the-context&quot;&gt;Organize tasks depending on the context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The big secret to efficient creative and productive thinking and action is to put the right things in your focus at the right time. 
I loved the idea of organizing tasks depending on the context. Possible contexts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;At the computer.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;At the phone.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;At the job.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On a plane.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Doing chores.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Low energy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;…
Grouping them will help you tackle more in less time and increase focus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-the-next-action&quot;&gt;What is the next action?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often tasks get stuck because they are too vague. Can you spot the difference between “Fix car” and “Call XXXX to make an appointment to fix car tires”?.  It’s ok to add tasks/ideas in the capture phase a little bit vague. But once they are refined they should be clear actionable tasks.
The question forces clarity, accountability, productivity, and empowerment. 
This can be applied to meetings too. Once a meeting is coming to an end, “What’s the next action?” is a powerful question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;technology-double-sided-sword&quot;&gt;Technology double-sided sword&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Technology sure can help keep track on all information. But it’s so easy to use that it can evolve in what the author calls “write-only syndrome”:
&lt;em&gt;All they’re doing is capturing information—not actually accessing and using it intelligently. Some consciousness needs to be applied to keep one’s potentially huge digital library functional, versus a black hole of data easily dumped in there with a couple of keystrokes.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t feel overwhelmed with all the techniques. Applying just some parts is already a victory and a productivity improvement. I started using &lt;a href=&quot;https://todoist.com/&quot;&gt;Todoist&lt;/a&gt; and created some projects, tags depending on the context and filters to see tasks in the order and prioriy I want. I’m still far from being a pro GTDer but I’m liking it so far. David Allen recommends reading the book again or at least skimming through it after some time promising it will feel like a new book. I’ll sure try in a year or two. Are you using GTD methodology? Any recommended tools/experience?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Juan Pallarès</name><email>juan@pallares.me</email></author><category term="books" /><category term="productivity" /><category term="GTD" /><category term="TODO" /><category term="Todoist" /><category term="growth" /><category term="career" /><summary type="html">Great tips from one of the best books about productivity.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="es"><title type="html">Copia de seguridad de tu Mac (Time Machine) en una carpeta compartida de Windows</title><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/time-machine-en-carpeta-compartida-de-windows/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Copia de seguridad de tu Mac (Time Machine) en una carpeta compartida de Windows" /><published>2020-07-19T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-07-19T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://juan.pallares.me/time-machine-en-carpeta-compartida-de-windows</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://juan.pallares.me/time-machine-en-carpeta-compartida-de-windows/">&lt;p&gt;MacOS tiene un sistema de backup llamado &lt;a href=&quot;https://support.apple.com/es-es/HT201250&quot;&gt;Time Machine&lt;/a&gt; que funciona muy al estilo Apple, rápido y fácil pero siempre que tengas su hardware (Time Capsule) o un disco externo que tendrías que ir conectando. Si tienes un PC Windows a modo de servidor (como yo) y espacio libre, puedes utilizarlo como Time Capsule. El setup es un poco más difícil pero una vez hecho se harán las copias de seguridad en background mientras trabajas/procastinas tranquilo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/windows_shared_drive.png&quot; alt=&quot;Windows shared drive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He utilizado &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imore.com/how-use-time-machine-backup-your-mac-windows-shared-folder&quot;&gt;esta guía&lt;/a&gt; la cúal lo explica genial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-crea-una-carpeta-compartida-en-windows-como-time-capsule&quot;&gt;1 Crea una carpeta compartida en Windows como Time Capsule&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Esto debería ser fácil y seguramente ya tienes alguna compartida. En tú máquina Windows selecciona la carpeta disco a compartir: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Botón derecho &amp;gt; Propiedades &amp;gt; Pestaña Compartir&lt;/code&gt;. Recuerda darte permisos administrador a ti mismo. En mi caso he compartido un disco entero pero puedes compartir solo una carpeta dentro del disco si lo prefieres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/share_folder.png&quot; alt=&quot;Permisos carpeta&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-conecta-desde-mac-a-esta-carpeta-compartida&quot;&gt;2 Conecta desde Mac a esta carpeta compartida&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Desde el Finder: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ir &amp;gt; Conecta a Servidor&lt;/code&gt;. O más facil/pro &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Cmd + K&lt;/code&gt;. Como dirección debes poner &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;smb://servidor/carpeta&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/connect_server.png&quot; alt=&quot;Conecta a servidor&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Te pedirá usuario y contraseña y aquí pondras tus credenciales de Windows (justo las que les has dado permiso en el paso anterior). &lt;strong&gt;Marca la opción de recordar y así no tendrás que volver a introducirlos&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-crea-una-imagen-sparsebundle&quot;&gt;3 Crea una imagen sparsebundle&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Esta imagen será del tipo HFS+ que es la que necesita Mac para usarla como backup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Abre la Disk Utility y ve al menú &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Archivo &amp;gt; Nueva Imagen &amp;gt; Imagen en Blanco&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Renombrala como te parezca.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Escoge la carpeta compartida de Windows a la que te conectaste anteriorment como destino.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Renombra también el sparsebundle.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Escoge el tamaño, idealmente igual o más que el tamaño de disco de tu Mac.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Valida que el tipo de Formato es Mac OS Extended (Journaled)&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cuando grabes puede llegar a tardar horas en crear la imagen, dependiendo del tamaño&lt;/strong&gt;. Paciencia y déjalo trabajando. Quizá tenerlo conectado por red sea buena idea para acelerar el proceso.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-haz-que-se-monte-automáticamente&quot;&gt;4 Haz que se monte automáticamente&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Para que cada vez que reinicies el disco se monte, tienes que configurarlo como Login Item, el único problema es que solo funcionará para tu usuario.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Preferencias del Sistema &amp;gt; Usuarios y Grupos&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Escoges tu usuario y entras a la pestaña Login Items.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Añades la carpeta montada y el fichero.dmg&lt;/strong&gt; que hemos creado.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Esta parte me ha dado problemas, en cada login me pedía los credenciales aunque marcara que los guardara en KeyChain. Valida que no tengas varios logins sobre el mismo disco en KeyChain, cuando he eliminado duplicados me ha funcionado.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/login_items.png&quot; alt=&quot;Login Items&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-configura-timemachine-para-usar-esa-imagen&quot;&gt;5 Configura TimeMachine para usar esa imagen&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Por último, tenemos que comprobar que Time Machine puede ver esta imagen y usarla. En &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Preferencias del Sistema &amp;gt; Time Machine&lt;/code&gt; valida que la disco configurado es el sparsebundle que hemos creado.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/TimeMachine_disk.png&quot; alt=&quot;Disco Time Machine&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Para poder añadirlo sino aparece, con el disco montado, ejecuta el comando:
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ls /Volumes&lt;/code&gt;
y luego con el nombre de la imagen creada en el paso 3, en mi caso lo había nombrado sparsebundle, ejecuta:
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sudo tmutil setdestination /Volumes/sparsebundle&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/timemachine_image_name.png&quot; alt=&quot;Time Machine image name&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Puede que también tengas que utilizar &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sudo tmutil enable&lt;/code&gt; si no tienes Time Machine activado.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;6-disfruta&quot;&gt;6 Disfruta&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;La primera copia de seguridad será larga pero luego solo los archivos que han cambiado se guaradarán y todo se hará automáticamente en background.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Juan Pallarès</name><email>juan@pallares.me</email></author><category term="MacOS" /><category term="Windows" /><category term="timemachine" /><category term="shared" /><category term="drive" /><summary type="html">Configura una carpeta compartido de Windows como Time Machine poder hacer copias de seguridad de tu Mac.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="es"><title type="html">Que no te engañen con tu seguro de moto o coche</title><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/que-no-te-enganen-con-tu-seguro-de-moto-coche/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Que no te engañen con tu seguro de moto o coche" /><published>2020-07-05T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-07-05T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://juan.pallares.me/que-no-te-enganen-con-tu-seguro-de-moto-coche</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://juan.pallares.me/que-no-te-enganen-con-tu-seguro-de-moto-coche/">&lt;p&gt;¿Cuánto pagas por tu seguro? Si no lo sabes, revísalo. ¿Y el año anterior? ¿Y el previo? Te ha ido subiendo cada año? No te preocupes, no estás solo. Las aseguradoras por lo general te suben el precio cada año aunque no tengas ningún parte. Aunque envejezcas y estadísticamente salgas de la franjas más peligrosas. Da lo mismo, el precio subirá igual que el sol sale cada mañana.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Por qué hacen esto? Opino que aprovechan varios factores:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;El seguro es obligatorio.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;La gente no tiene un gran control de sus finanzas y no notan esa subida. No se dan ni cuenta.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;El más importante. &lt;strong&gt;Da pereza cambiar, igual que da pereza cambiar de banco, de compañía de teléfono, etc. Esto lo aprovechan sin piedad.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mi-caso&quot;&gt;Mi caso&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;En 2010 compré una moto 125cc que venía con seguro incluído, otro truco ya que te tienen atado y no te sueltan por los anteriores motivos. Cuando pasó el primer año, renovado automáticamente por la nada despreciable cantidad de &lt;strong&gt;242,05€&lt;/strong&gt; (no es que me acuerde, tengo el mail) con Allianz. Yo sabía que podía obtener el mismo seguro (terceros con asistencia) por &lt;strong&gt;menos de 200€ y así fue&lt;/strong&gt;. Devolví el recibo y contacté con una correduría para que me buscaran el presupuesto más bajo y me dieran de baja de la otra aseguradora. Además todo por mail, llámame asocial o llámame práctico.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;la-solución&quot;&gt;La solución&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Desde entonces, &lt;strong&gt;un par de meses antes de que caduque el seguro tengo una alarma de Google Calendar CADUCA SEGURO&lt;/strong&gt; y en ese momento decido si quiero tragar este año con la subida o cambio de compañía? si decido cambiar envío un mensaje así a la correduría que he venido usando estos años: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.peris.es/&quot;&gt;Peris&lt;/a&gt;, en concreto a &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:correduria@peris.es,motos@peris.es&quot;&gt;correduria@peris.es y motos@peris.es&lt;/a&gt;. Este es un ejemplo con mi actual moto, una 300cc:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Hola,

He gestionado varias veces el seguro con vosotros, soy Juan Pallarès Garbí con DNI XXXXXXXX y fecha de nacimiento 1985, 34 años en breve. Carné de conducir A2 con fecha de expedición XX/XX/XXXX (adjunto).

Mi moto es Honda Forza 300cc comprada en Octubre 2013 con matrícula XXXXXXX. Con permiso de circulación XXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXX (adjunto) y también adjunto tarjeta inspección técnica.

Mi actual póliza es con Mapfre a terceros con asistencia en carretera. Número de póliza XXXXXXXXXXXXXX
Llevo dos años con ellos, cobrando los siguientes recibos
2017 - 141,07€
2018 - 150,93€
Esta póliza caduca a 23 de Octubre 2019.

Me puede pasar un listado de posible pólizas que pueda contratar?
Comuníqueme si falta algún dato o documento

Saludos
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fíjate en las subidas que se van produciendo y la próxima iba a ser 160€. Lo sé porque esta vez quise darles una oportunidad, llamé a Mapfre y les expliqué educadamente que o me bajaban el precio o me iba…da igual, seguían empecinados en que “han subido los costes”. Llamé a otras aseguradoras, estilo Línea Directa, casi una hora al teléfono para ofrecerme algo más caro de lo que tenía. &lt;em&gt;“Por qué pensaste que habrían cambiado?”&lt;/em&gt; Me dije y volví a mi mail anual a Peris. Te responden con un mail donde adjuntan un presupuesto de este estilo:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/presupuesto_peris.png&quot; alt=&quot;Captura presupuesto Peris&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;132€ de coste, unos 30€ de ahorro.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;vale-la-pena&quot;&gt;Vale la pena?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Como te pones Juan por 30€!”&lt;/em&gt; Que es como si os oyera decirme. Eso ha sido solo un año, imagina el Juan incauto del pasado que sigue con el seguro de 242€ que aumenta año tras año. Y además que si nos le dais valor a 30€ os paso mi número de cuenta que yo si les daré todo el amor que merecen :smile:.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Opino que vale la pena, ya no solo económicamente sino también para no sentir que te están tomando el pelo. Todo se puede gestionar por mail y es enviar un par de mail una vez al año. Se ha dado el caso que he estado en la aseguradora AXA, he ido a Mapfre y luego he vuelto AXA. AXA podría haberme tenido como cliente todo el tiempo si hubiera accedido a darme un precio de mercado, no lo hacen. También he estado estos años en Generali y Allianz, siempre al mejor postor, cúal mercenario.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Después de leer todo esto, seguirás con tu actual compañía? Me encantaría que compartieras tu experiencia conmigo.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Juan Pallarès</name><email>juan@pallares.me</email></author><summary type="html">Paga el mínimo posible cada año</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Configure Jekyll to be multi-language without plugins</title><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/configure-jekyll-multi-language-without-plugin/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Configure Jekyll to be multi-language without plugins" /><published>2020-06-28T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-06-28T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://juan.pallares.me/configure-jekyll-multi-language-without-plugin</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://juan.pallares.me/configure-jekyll-multi-language-without-plugin/">&lt;p&gt;Almost 6 years ago I migrated from &lt;a href=&quot;https://juan.pallares.me/moving-to-jekyll/&quot;&gt;Blogger to Jekyll + Github Pages&lt;/a&gt; and I can’t be happier with the change. Still, something I wanted long ago is to make it multi-language. I have entries in mind that I have not written because the clear target is Spain and the average English level in my country is not high. This last weekend I finally comitted to it and here I present my m̵a̵s̵t̵e̵r̵-̵p̵i̵e̵c̵e̵ quick-fix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;requirements&quot;&gt;Requirements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No plugins.&lt;/strong&gt; Github Pages is not compatible with many &lt;a href=&quot;https://pages.github.com/versions/&quot;&gt;plugins&lt;/a&gt;. For example, I was unable to use &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kurtsson/jekyll-multiple-languages-plugin&quot;&gt;jekyll-multiple-languages-plugin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Compatible with Minimal Mistakes&lt;/strong&gt;. My &lt;a href=&quot;https://mmistakes.github.io/minimal-mistakes/&quot;&gt;Jekyll’s theme&lt;/a&gt; that I’m delighted with.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Show the entry if it is only in one language&lt;/strong&gt;. I have many old posts in Spanish or English that I will not translate, it has no value.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Link for language change in each entry&lt;/strong&gt;. If there are two languages ​​or more (I don’t think I will ever write in Catalan or Italian :smile:) a link to change language ​​will be displayed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Global Link language change&lt;/strong&gt;. This functionality has been dropped. The pagination plugin &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/docs/pagination/&quot;&gt;jekyll-paginate&lt;/a&gt; does not allow more than one page. Sure there are ways to do it, but I did not want to spend the time, it did not compensate me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/pagination_jekyll.png&quot; alt=&quot;jekyll-paginate disclaimer&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;implementation&quot;&gt;Implementation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Judging from Google’s results, many warriors have gone but few have returned victorious. There is no standard way to do it and I have used what was best for my requrements from each site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;configure-_configyaml&quot;&gt;Configure _config.yaml&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the _config.yml we set the language of the site adding the line &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;lang: en&lt;/code&gt;. Then we create a file inside the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_data&lt;/code&gt; folder, that I have called&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt; i18n&lt;/code&gt;, with the following content:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;in:
  label: English
  icon: 🇬🇧
  read_it_in: &quot;Read it in&quot;
it is:
  label: Spanish
  icon: 🇪🇸
  read_it_in: &quot;Read it on&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will allow us to access content according to the language as we will see later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;adapt-the-front-matter-of-the-posts&quot;&gt;Adapt the &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/docs/front-matter/&quot;&gt;Front Matter&lt;/a&gt; of the posts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In each post, specify your language &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;lang&lt;/code&gt; and unique identifier&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt; ref&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;-
title: RDP to Windows machine with PIN login
tags: [RDP, Windows, PIN, MicrosoftAccount, login, hacks]
excerpt: Don't lose the precious hour I lost
lang: in
ref: rdp
---
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If two posts share the same &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ref&lt;/code&gt; they are the same post in different languages. I’ve seen people grouping the posts by folders according to the language, I have not considered it necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;filter-by-language&quot;&gt;Filter by language&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My main page is a pagination of all blog entries. Now we want all of them to be displayed, but if they are in more than one language, they should be shown in English.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before it showed all the posts that came from the paginator:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;{% for post in paginator.posts%}
  {% include archive-single.html%}
{% endfor%}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then what I have done is to group by the field &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ref&lt;/code&gt;. This way you can know if there is more than one language for each entry since the group will have more than 1 item. If that’s the case, I take only the post that has the same language as the page (English in my case), otherwise I show the post regardless of the language:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;{% assign items_grouped = paginator.posts | group_by: 'ref'%}
{% for group in items_grouped%}
    {% if group.items.size&amp;gt; 1%}
        {% assign post = group.items | where: &quot;lang&quot;, page.lang | first%}
    {% else%}
        {% assign post = group.items [0]%}
    {% endif%}
    {% include archive-single.html%}
{% endfor%}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That beautiful code is &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/docs/liquid/&quot;&gt;Liquid&lt;/a&gt;, it may already be in the TOP 5 of my most hated languages. Keep in mind that I do the identation for clarity, it is not necessary. In order to display Liquid code in Jekill (escape it) you have to use &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;raw&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/show_liquid.png&quot; alt=&quot;Escape liquid code with raw tag&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;filter-by-language-1&quot;&gt;Filter by language&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the previous code, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;archive-single.html&lt;/code&gt; is called and this is what we are going to edit now. We will add a flag emoji with the language in case there is a translation of the post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;{% assign versions = site.posts | where: &quot;ref&quot;, post.ref | sort: 'lang'%}
{% if versions.size&amp;gt; 1%}
    {% for version in versions%}
        {% if version.lang! = site.lang%}
            &amp;lt;a href=&quot;{{ version.url }}&quot;&amp;gt;{{site.data.i18n [version.lang] .icon}} &amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
        {% endif%}
    {% endfor%}
{% endif%}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is again a similar concept to the previous one, the difference is that we now access the flag emoji that we put in the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_data/i18n.yml&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;link-to-other-languages-within-the-blog&quot;&gt;Link to other languages ​​within the blog&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And going from outside to inside, finally we have to edit &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;single.html&lt;/code&gt; which is the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;layout&lt;/code&gt; of my blog entries. Add where you think is most appropriate:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;{% if page.bookauthor == null and page.permalink == null%}
    {% assign versions = site.posts | where: &quot;ref&quot;, page.ref | sort: 'lang'%}
    {% if versions.size&amp;gt; 1%}
        {% for version in versions%}
            {% if version.lang! = page.lang%}
                &amp;lt;a href=&quot;{{ version.url }}&quot; class=&quot;{{ version.lang }}&quot;&amp;gt;{{ site.data.i18n[version.lang].read_it_in] }} {{ site.data.i18n[version.lang].icon }} &amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
            {% endif%}
        {% endfor%}
    {% endif%}
{% endif%}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;if&lt;/code&gt; I prevent other layouts from being affected and then practically the same. The difference is that I look for a different language than the current one and I show a text located next to the flag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;outcome&quot;&gt;Outcome&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are browsing on it right now. Feel free to swap between English and Spanish version. You can also see the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jpallares/minimal-mistakes&quot;&gt;code on Github&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dodge-the-black-hole&quot;&gt;Dodge the black hole&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All engineers who have a blog/landing page suffer what I call the black hole. This is dedicating all the time to improve the blog technically, now I use Gatsby, now I deploy in Vercel, wow! now I have Github Actions … but not writing any content. This multi-language update was the ideal breeding ground to start a technology change that would never have ended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.gifer.com/GVXn.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Black hole gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily I clearly defined the minimum requirements and now I have a basic multi-language blog instead of a last-tech half-baked project. &lt;strong&gt;Deliver value, that should be the focus&lt;/strong&gt;. It has helped me by forcing myself to a weekly blog post. What productivity-hacks do you have?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Juan Pallarès</name><email>juan@pallares.me</email></author><summary type="html">Basic multi-language hosted on Github Pages</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="es"><title type="html">Configura Jekyll para ser multi idioma sin plugins</title><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/configura-jekyll-multi-idioma-sin-plugin/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Configura Jekyll para ser multi idioma sin plugins" /><published>2020-06-28T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-06-28T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://juan.pallares.me/configura-jekyll-multi-idioma-sin-plugin</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://juan.pallares.me/configura-jekyll-multi-idioma-sin-plugin/">&lt;p&gt;Han pasado casi 6 años desde que migré de &lt;a href=&quot;https://juan.pallares.me/moving-to-jekyll/&quot;&gt;Blogger a Jekyll + Github Pages&lt;/a&gt; y no puedo estar más contento con el cambio. Aún así, algo que quería hace tiempo es convertirlo en multi-idioma. Tengo entradas en mente que no he escrito porque el target claro es España y como bien sabemos el nivel de inglés no es alto. Este último fin de semana me he decidio y aquí os presento mi o̵b̵r̵a̵ chapuza.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;requisitos&quot;&gt;Requisitos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sin plugins.&lt;/strong&gt; Github Pages no es compatible con muchos &lt;a href=&quot;https://pages.github.com/versions/&quot;&gt;plugins&lt;/a&gt;. Por ejemplo, no he podido usar &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kurtsson/jekyll-multiple-languages-plugin&quot;&gt;jekyll-multiple-languages-plugin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Compatible con Minimal Mistakes&lt;/strong&gt;. Mi &lt;a href=&quot;https://mmistakes.github.io/minimal-mistakes/&quot;&gt;tema de Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; con el cual estoy encantado.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mostrar la entrada si solo esta en un idioma&lt;/strong&gt;. Tengo muchísimos post antiguos en castellano o en inglés que no traduciré, no tiene valor.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Link para cambio de idioma en cada entrada&lt;/strong&gt;. Si hay dos idiomas o más (no creo que llegue a escribir en catalán o italiano :smile:) que se muestre un link para cambiar de idioma.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Link global cambio de idioma&lt;/strong&gt;. Esta funcionalidad se ha caído. El plugin de paginación &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/docs/pagination/&quot;&gt;jekyll-paginate&lt;/a&gt; no permite más de una página. Seguro hay formas de hacerlo, pero no he querido dedicar el tiempo, no me compensaba.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/pagination_jekyll.png&quot; alt=&quot;jekyll-paginate disclaimer&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;implementación&quot;&gt;Implementación&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A juzgar por los resultados de Google, muchos guerreros han ido pero pocos han vuelto victoriosos. No hay una manera estándar de hacerlo y he cogido lo que mejor me venía de cada sitio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;configura-_configyaml&quot;&gt;Configura _config.yaml&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;En el _config.yml seteamos el lenguage del site añadiendo la linea &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;lang: en&lt;/code&gt;. Y luego creamos un fichero dentro de la carpeta &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_data&lt;/code&gt;que yo he llamado &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;i18n&lt;/code&gt; con el siguiente contenido:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;en:
  label: English
  icon: 🇬🇧
  read_it_in: &quot;Read it in&quot;
es:
  label: Español
  icon: 🇪🇸
  read_it_in: &quot;Léelo en&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Esto nos permitirá acceder a contenido según el idioma como veremos más adelante.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;adapta-el-front-matter-de-los-posts&quot;&gt;Adapta el &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/docs/front-matter/&quot;&gt;Front Matter&lt;/a&gt; de los posts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Especifica en cada post su idioma &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;lang&lt;/code&gt; y identificador único &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ref&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;--
title: RDP to Windows machine with PIN login
tags: [RDP, Windows, PIN, MicrosoftAccount, login, hacks]
excerpt: Don't lose the precious hour I lost
lang: en
ref: rdp
---
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Si dos posts comparten el mismo &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ref&lt;/code&gt; son el mismo post en diferentes idiomas. Algunos agrupan los posts por carpetas según el idioma, no lo he considerado necesario.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;filtra-por-idioma&quot;&gt;Filtra por idioma&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mi página principal es una paginacioón de todas las entradas del blog. Ahora queremos que se muestren todos pero si están en más de un idioma que se muestren en inglés.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Antes mostraba todos los posts que venian del paginator:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;{% for post in paginator.posts %}
  {% include archive-single.html %}
{% endfor %}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Después lo que he hecho ha sido agrupar por el campo &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ref&lt;/code&gt;. De esta manera puede saber si hay más de un idioma para cada entrada ya que el grupo tendrá más de 1 item. Si ese es el caso, cojo solo el post que tiene el mismo idioma que la página (Inglés en mi caso), de lo contrario muestro el post independientemente del idioma:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;{% assign items_grouped = paginator.posts | group_by: 'ref' %}
{% for group in items_grouped %}
    {% if group.items.size &amp;gt; 1 %}
        {% assign post = group.items | where: &quot;lang&quot;,page.lang | first %}
    {% else %}
        {% assign post = group.items[0] %}
    {% endif %}
    {% include archive-single.html %}
{% endfor %}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ese código tan bonito es &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/docs/liquid/&quot;&gt;Liquid&lt;/a&gt;, puede que ya esté en el TOP 5 de mis lenguajes más odiados. Tened en cuenta que el sangrado lo hago yo por claridad, no es necesario. Para poder mostrar código Liquid en Jekill, escaparlo, hay que usar &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;raw&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/show_liquid.png&quot; alt=&quot;Escape liquid code with raw tag&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;filtra-por-idioma-1&quot;&gt;Filtra por idioma&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Desde el código anterior se llama a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;archive-single.html&lt;/code&gt; y ese código es el que vamos a editar ahora para añadir una bandera con el idioma en caso que haya una traducción del post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;{% assign versions=site.posts | where:&quot;ref&quot;, post.ref | sort: 'lang' %}
{% if versions.size &amp;gt; 1 %}
    {% for version in versions %}
        {% if version.lang != site.lang %}
            &amp;lt;a href=&quot;{{ version.url }}&quot; &amp;gt;{{ site.data.i18n[version.lang].icon }} &amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
        {% endif %}
    {% endfor %}
{% endif %}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vuelve a ser un concepto similar al anterior, la diferencia es que ahora accedemos al emoji de bandera que pusimos en el fichero &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_data/i18n.yml&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;link-a-otros-idiomas-dentro-del-blog&quot;&gt;Link a otros idiomas dentro del blog&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Y yendo de fuera hacia a dentro nos queda editar &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;single.html&lt;/code&gt; que es el &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;layout&lt;/code&gt; de mis entradas. Añade donde creas más oportuno esto:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;{% if page.bookauthor == null and page.permalink == null %}
    {% assign versions=site.posts | where:&quot;ref&quot;, page.ref | sort: 'lang' %}
    {% if versions.size &amp;gt; 1 %}
        {% for version in versions %}
            {% if version.lang != page.lang %}
                &amp;lt;a href=&quot;{{ version.url }}&quot; class=&quot;{{ version.lang }}&quot;&amp;gt;{{ site.data.i18n[version.lang].read_it_in] }} {{ site.data.i18n[version.lang].icon }} &amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
            {% endif %}
        {% endfor %}
    {% endif %}
{% endif %}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;En el primer &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;if&lt;/code&gt; evito que otros layouts se vean afectados y luego prácticamente igual. La diferencia es que busco el lenguaje diferente al actual y muestro un texto localizado al lado de la bandera.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;resultado&quot;&gt;Resultado&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Estás navegando sobre él ahora mismo. También puedes ver el &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jpallares/minimal-mistakes&quot;&gt;código en Github&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;esquivar-el-agujero-negro&quot;&gt;Esquivar el agujero negro&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Todos los ingenieros que tenemos un blog/landing page sufrimos lo que llamo el agujero negro. Esto es dedicar todo el tiempo a mejorar el blog técnicamente, ahora uso Gatsby, ahora deploy en Vercel, ojo que ahora tengo Github Actions…pero no escribir nada de contenido. Este update a multi-idioma era el caldo de cultivo ideal para venirme arriba y empezar un cambio de tecnología que nunca habría acabado.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.gifer.com/GVXn.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Black hole gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Por suerte, me definí claramente los mínimos y ahora tengo un multi-idioma básico en lugar de un proyecto con las últimas tecnologías a medias. &lt;strong&gt;Entregar valor, ese debe ser el foco&lt;/strong&gt;. Me ha ayudado el auto-obligarme a una entreda semanal. Que productivity-hacks tienes?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Juan Pallarès</name><email>juan@pallares.me</email></author><summary type="html">Multi-idioma básico alojado en Github Pages</summary></entry></feed>