<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-06-08T18:41:44+02:00</updated><id>https://juan.pallares.me/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Juan Pallarès Garbí</title><subtitle>Landing page.</subtitle><author><name>Juan Pallarès</name><email>juan@pallares.me</email></author><entry><title type="html">Browsing blocking ads and trackers</title><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/browsing-blocking-ads-and-trackers/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Browsing blocking ads and trackers" /><published>2020-06-08T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-06-08T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://juan.pallares.me/browsing-blocking-ads-and-trackers</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://juan.pallares.me/browsing-blocking-ads-and-trackers/">&lt;p&gt;For the last months I have been using Brave as my browser for all my devices. The idea of having a Chrome fork that blocks ads and trackers seemed perfect. But Brave is not reliable at all:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://davidgerard.co.uk/blockchain/2020/06/06/the-brave-web-browser-is-hijacking-links-and-inserting-affiliate-codes/&quot;&gt;The Brave web browser is hijacking links, and inserting affiliate codes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not directly affected since I don’t use criptocurrency but a browser that markets itself like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It begins with giving you back power. Get unmatched speed, security and privacy by blocking trackers&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can not do this actions. The power to choose my affiliate code is taken away :unamused:.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since &lt;a href=&quot;https://clark.com/technology/google-chrome-do-not-track/&quot;&gt;Chrome and all his tracking&lt;/a&gt; is a no-go. I looked for a browser that cared about privacy and could have Dashlane and uBlock add-ons installed and I decided to go back to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mozilla.org/es-ES/firefox&quot;&gt;Mozilla Firefox&lt;/a&gt;. It was my browser years ago before Chrome arrived but before I continue let’s see what happens when you don’t block anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;ads&quot;&gt;Ads&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an sports website I usually visit with a browser that has no blocking configured:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/marca_browser.png&quot; alt=&quot;marca.com no block&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost 50% of the website real-state are ads, apart from being annoying it also makes the loading slower and uses more data (concerning if you pay per MB like some data plans). If you are wondering if in a portable devices gets better, let me tell you it does not:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tablet&quot;&gt;Tablet:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/marca_ipad.png&quot; alt=&quot;marca.com iPad&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;phone&quot;&gt;Phone:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/marca_phone.png&quot; alt=&quot;marca.com phone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used this site because the ads are really big and painful and I have even seen full screen ad-popups with a blurry X to close.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;trackers&quot;&gt;Trackers&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only the ads should worry you, you are also being tracked, for example in the same page we have:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/trackers.png&quot; alt=&quot;marca.com trackers&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“But Juan you are starting to be paranoid! Why do you worry about it? I don’t have anything to hide”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also thought this way in the past, but once I read about the experience of an Egyptian guy during the Arab spring and how his “Facebook likes” were used against him and detained and sent to prison. Charge? Political dissidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me quote this &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2013/feb/11/riot-software-tracked-online-social-networks&quot;&gt;The Guardian Article&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Today, it’s so easy that mass-surveillance is feasible – and so-called “big data” makes it seem tempting and innocuous.
The “big data” theory works like this: by grabbing hundreds or thousands of datapoints on millions of people, we build a systematic picture of how everyday people act. By analysing these by machine for “outliers”, or suspicious activity, we can catch the bad guys – and it’s OK, because only at that stage is another human being looking through your personal info.
&lt;strong&gt;This is, by and large, fantasy. For one thing, any algorithm will generate hundreds if not thousands of false positives&lt;/strong&gt; (innocent people who hit a red flag). Given how rare, say, terrorism is, the vast majority of people bothered by these systems will be ordinary people facing previously unbelievable intrusion.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trust me, better to block as much as possible. There is an area between living in a mountain like a buddhist monk and browsing with no block at all, find it and start making more difficult for them to spy on you. I say “more difficult” because I want to emphasize, is impossible not being tracked, even if you did not have an smartphone and use only Internet only for work purposes, the people around you would do the tracking for you, for example with the photos you appear in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-solution&quot;&gt;The solution&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here you have the same web with Firefox and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/ublock-origin/&quot;&gt;uBlock Origin&lt;/a&gt; add-on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/marca_adfree.png&quot; alt=&quot;marca.com ad free&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It loads faster and you get to see just the real content and good news, Firefox and uBlock can also be installed in iOS and Android. You can specify how strictily Firefox should block tracking. Another step to prevent tracking is using &lt;a href=&quot;https://duckduckgo.com/&quot;&gt;DuckDuckGo&lt;/a&gt; as default search engine. It comes already as an option in Firefox.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-next-level&quot;&gt;The next level&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You want to go to the next level? What if I told about &lt;strong&gt;network-wide ad blocking and faster browsing&lt;/strong&gt;? Meet &lt;a href=&quot;https://pi-hole.net/&quot;&gt;Pi-Hole&lt;/a&gt; .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/f9Rrghj6TDckb5nZZR/giphy.gif&quot; alt=&quot;next level funny gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://juan.pallares.me/raspberry-pi-hole-vpn/&quot;&gt;As I mentioned in the past&lt;/a&gt;, if you have a Raspberry Pi lying around this is one of the best uses you can do of it. Is a very active project, they recently released the &lt;a href=&quot;https://pi-hole.net/2020/05/10/pi-hole-v5-0-is-here/&quot;&gt;v5.0&lt;/a&gt;. For the screenshots with all the ads above I had to disable temporarily the PiHole apart from using Edge browser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are you blocking any ads? What is the browser you use? Don’t tell me the google analytics script running on this page will tell me this and more :smirk:.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Juan Pallarès</name><email>juan@pallares.me</email></author><category term="adblock" /><category term="ad" /><category term="tracking" /><category term="browser" /><category term="brave" /><category term="firefox" /><category term="chrome" /><category term="pihole" /><category term="ublock origin" /><summary type="html">Why and how I browse blocking ads and trackers</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Acknowledge your privilege</title><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/acknowledge-your-privilege/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Acknowledge your privilege" /><published>2020-06-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-06-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://juan.pallares.me/acknowledge-your-privilege</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://juan.pallares.me/acknowledge-your-privilege/">&lt;p&gt;This last days going through my Twitter timeline was really shocking. I hated what I was watching and I couldn’t stop watching it. How is it possible that in year 2020 in the most important country of the world, a reference for a lot of developing countries, a policeman can kill a man that is totally surredendered and saying that he can’t breathe…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I honestly don’t know what to do or say. I’m a white man, heterosexual, from a middle-class family in a developed country, tall (at least for Spanish standards) and even blonde with blue eyes (more on why this can be a privilege later). If you are phisically like me you should acknowledge how privileged we are, minorities are in clear disadvantage to us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe this couple videos can explain much better what I try to say:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/4K5fbQ1-zps&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Mqrhn8khGLM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the US, years of slavery and discrimination to black people create a gap that is really difficult to overcome, I believe this is one the reasons provoking  the recent events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why did I mention blonde and blue eyes before? What is standard of beauty (or has been until recent years)? white, blonde, straight hair, green/blue eyes. 
Think about it. Why are blue and green contact lenses sold? Why so many people dyes his hair blonde and straightens it? Only one very specific race is considered beautiful and the rest have to adapt! Check out the media, is changing I agree but some years ago it was impossible to a see a non-white actor with a leading role, even at latin american countries with most non-white population the TV was all white people, well sure you could have the black servants. This is a problem, you are placing a lot of people below by birth. Come on, even the band aids have the color of white skin! How come Jesus is so white being from the Midle-East? Last time I checked people over there were darker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going back to my environment, software engineers. Check out the results of the latest &lt;a href=&quot;https://insights.stackoverflow.com/survey/2020#developer-profile-gender-all-respondents2&quot;&gt;Stackoverflow 2020 survey&lt;/a&gt; released some days ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/developers-race.png&quot; alt=&quot;Race and Ethnicity&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have a long way to arrive to equality everywhere. We (white) have it really easy, just acknowledge it, as a first step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;police-brutality&quot;&gt;Police brutality&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something I don’t want to miss is police brutality and the people that justifies it just because: &lt;em&gt;“Hey! they have been insulted and had objects thrown at them for hours, what would you do?!”&lt;/em&gt;. I don’t mind! They have to be able to put up with all of this and more, nothing justifies the atrocities seen in some videos. Somebody breaks the law? Just handcuff him and take him away. How can they be so violent with people just walking? It reminds me of recent events in Barcelona where we had also our take of police brutality. Again, I will quote someone that explains better what I mean:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;I’m perplexed by the replies defending police actions because of some “other side” doing something.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;If someone commits a crime, that doesn’t mean it’s okay for the police to start punching random peaceful people on the street. They don’t get to be “annoyed”, that’s their job.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Dan Abramov (@dan_abramov) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/dan_abramov/status/1267151390578749441?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;May 31, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple movies I saw recently that can help understand the problem, both based in true stories:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imdb.com/title/tt6285944/&quot;&gt;The Banker&lt;/a&gt; - In the 1960s two African-American entrepreneurs hire a working-class white man to pretend to be the head of their business empire while they pose as a janitor and chauffeur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imdb.com/title/tt4916630/?ref_=tt_sims_tt&quot;&gt;Just Mercy&lt;/a&gt; - World-renowned civil rights defense attorney Bryan Stevenson works to free a wrongly condemned death row prisoner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally I want to send all my support and love to the protesters #BlackLivesMatter&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Juan Pallarès</name><email>juan@pallares.me</email></author><category term="blacklivesmatter" /><category term="white" /><category term="privileges" /><category term="george" /><category term="floyd" /><summary type="html">My humble opinion about George Floyd killing and white privilege</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Automate your email processing with Google Apps Script</title><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/automate-email-processing-google-apps-script/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Automate your email processing with Google Apps Script" /><published>2020-05-24T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-05-24T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://juan.pallares.me/automate-email-processing-google-apps-script</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://juan.pallares.me/automate-email-processing-google-apps-script/">&lt;p&gt;Bill Gates is often credited with the quote, &lt;em&gt;“I will always choose a lazy person to do a difficult job because a lazy person will find an easy way to do it.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hate doing manual tasks that a machine would do faster and with less errors. I keep track of expenses (water, electricity, etc.) in a Google SpreadSheet that I fill every month, this way I can see my average cost, year cost…I love data, what can I say?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently I discovered &lt;a href=&quot;https://developers.google.com/apps-script&quot;&gt;Google Apps Script&lt;/a&gt;. It allows you to create javascript code that can automatize all the apps under Google Apps. You can even create a chat bot, but I wanted just to parse data from an email and write it in a sheet, far-less ambituous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something that can be improved is the online editor…I would love to edit the script locally and then push it (repo style) but it only works with an online editor. I ended up coding a Node app and the copy pasting the code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;reading-email&quot;&gt;Reading email&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To read email, after going through the &lt;a href=&quot;https://developers.google.com/apps-script/reference/gmail&quot;&gt;Gmail Service Reference&lt;/a&gt; I started tagging automatically the emails I wanna read in the script so later they are easy to find:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;var label = GmailApp.getUserLabelByName(&quot;TAG_NAME&quot;);&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I just pick the unread threads:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;var threads = label.getThreads().filter(t =&amp;gt; t.isUnread());&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I iterate through all the unread emails, get the first email in the thread (there is only one when you receive a bill from your company) and then I get the date, get the plain text and split the lines.:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;threads.forEach(thread =&amp;gt; {
  var message = thread.getMessages()[0];
  var date = message.getDate().toLocaleString('en-us', {year: 'numeric', month: '2-digit', day: '2-digit'});
  var body = message.getPlainBody();
  var bodyLines = body.split('\n');
  ...
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once here it’s all your choice, I use &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;findIndex&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;replace&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;filter&lt;/code&gt; to get the data and create a little object with date, money and consumption (kWh).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a final step, to prevent the script to get the same email again and again I mark it as read and archive it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;thread.markRead();
thread.moveToArchive();
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;adding-row-to-spreadsheet&quot;&gt;Adding row to SpreadSheet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://developers.google.com/apps-script/reference/spreadsheet&quot;&gt;Spreadsheet Service Reference&lt;/a&gt; is very similar. First we have to open the Spreadsheet and then the sheet, &lt;a href=&quot;https://developers.google.com/apps-script/reference/spreadsheet/spreadsheet-app#openbyidid&quot;&gt;the spreadsheet id can be retrieved from the URL&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;var spreadSheet = SpreadsheetApp.openById(SPREADSHEET_ID);
var sheet = spreadSheet.getSheetByName(SHEET_NAME);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then you have to create and array with the data you got in previous email step and add it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sheet.appendRow([DATA,DATA2,DATA3]);&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will add a row in the first empty row of your sheet. If you wanna leave empty cells before the data, you can use empty string &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;''&lt;/code&gt;, here I have 3 empty cells before a cell with data: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;['','','',DATA]&lt;/code&gt;. In the reference you have methods available for inserting the row in a specific position if needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;triggers&quot;&gt;Triggers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the script is ready, you have to configure when you want to run it. In the &lt;a href=&quot;https://script.google.com/home/triggers&quot;&gt;triggers view&lt;/a&gt; I configured it to run daily at 5am.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any ideas for more scripts?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Juan Pallarès</name><email>juan@pallares.me</email></author><category term="google" /><category term="apps" /><category term="script" /><category term="javascript" /><category term="gmail" /><category term="spreadsheet" /><summary type="html">How to read your bill email data and create a row in an Spreadsheet automatically.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Attending SoCraTes UK remotely</title><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/Atteding-remote-Socrates-UK/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Attending SoCraTes UK remotely" /><published>2020-05-10T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-05-10T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://juan.pallares.me/Atteding-remote-Socrates-UK</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://juan.pallares.me/Atteding-remote-Socrates-UK/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-socrates&quot;&gt;What is SoCraTes?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I always heard good things about &lt;a href=&quot;https://socratesuk.org/&quot;&gt;SoCraTes&lt;/a&gt;, a friend attended 4 times in a row to the SoCraTes UK version and told me it was his favourite event of the year. This is not the typical conference, in fact they define themselves as an unconference or retreat:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;International Software Craft and Testing Unconference UK
SoCraTes UK is a non-profit, international Software Crafters retreat for open-minded crafters who want to improve their craft and the software industry as a whole&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;remote-version&quot;&gt;Remote version&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to COVID-19 the normal retreat was cancelled and an online version was held during last Friday, it was a good opportunity to attend and see how it worked. I have to admit I was really suprised by how well it was organized, I didn’t have any problem knowing what was the schedule, the changes, how to switch room, it was fast and easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tools used to make it work were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://discord.com/&quot;&gt;Discord&lt;/a&gt; for written communication. Some days before the workspace was created and some help provided if needed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://zoom.us/&quot;&gt;Zoom&lt;/a&gt; for video conferencing. There were several zoom rooms mapping to some rooms I imagine exist in the real house where the conference is usually held.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mural.co/&quot;&gt;Mural&lt;/a&gt; for sharing the schedule and then making diagrams, postits etc from each one of the talks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have a &lt;a href=&quot;https://socratesuk.org/code_of_conduct.html&quot;&gt;Code of Conduct&lt;/a&gt; that enforces a safe environment for everybody to participate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/socrates_schedule.png&quot; alt=&quot;SoCraTes schedule in Mural.co&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m used to check the conference schedule of the ones I attend, what are the subjects they are going to talk and then decide where to go during the day. In SoCraTes it works totally different, the talks are dedided the very same day and they are not the expert talking and the others listening, is more a like a conversation, a collaboration between all the attendants, sharing their experience. Somebody says “I wanna talk about DDD and how we are struggling in our company”. In fact, according to the organizers the best talks come from people asking open questions that they need help with. Example: “How can we improve in pair programming?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;learnings&quot;&gt;Learnings&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I attended just two talks and both were related to the subject of remote pairing and &lt;strong&gt;remote mob programming&lt;/strong&gt;. I’m &lt;a href=&quot;https://juan.pallares.me/remote-working-tips/&quot;&gt;used to do pair programming&lt;/a&gt; but working remotely has become harder to do it and as a result we do it less often than we would like. What was something new for me is mob programming, I just heard it once when the whole team was looking at one screen trying to solve a problem but I didn’t know it was a thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/mob_programming.png&quot; alt=&quot;SoCraTes Mob Programming&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned we do pair programming in a very loose way, which does not have to be bad but is good to know how the strict way is and what other people in the community is doing. I was suprised that some guys mentioned they were switching the keyboard every 3 minutes when they were collocated and that they always use the driver and navigator role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found confort in listening that we are not the only ones struggling with remote pairing. Everybody shared which tools were using for pairing, Liveshare, Teams, Zoom, Tuple but agreed that nothing is as good as being collocated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regarding mob programming, I learned a lot of teams are doing it daily. Imagine a big group (8 people?) working all together in the same code, only one writing (driver) one speaking (navigator) and the rest giving input when asked for, then rotating roles frequently. Very interesting topics were raised like, how can we ensure everybody is engaged? How often and for how long are you mobing? What are the reasons to use it? The main benefits are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Knowledge share accross whole team&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Less WIP&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Quality and diversity of ideas&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Less errors and less time finding them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find it like pair programming on steroids, all the benefits of pair programming multiplied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you attended any remote conference recently? How was your experience?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Juan Pallarès</name><email>juan@pallares.me</email></author><category term="unconference" /><category term="socrates" /><category term="uk" /><category term="craft" /><category term="software" /><category term="remote" /><summary type="html">My experience attending to SoCraTes UK in this new remote version.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Investing in index funds. Why I became a boglehead</title><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/why-i-became-a-bogglehead/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Investing in index funds. Why I became a boglehead" /><published>2020-05-02T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-05-02T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://juan.pallares.me/why-i-became-a-bogglehead</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://juan.pallares.me/why-i-became-a-bogglehead/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-passive-investing&quot;&gt;Why passive investing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently I read a couple books that triggered and investigation in blogs and forums that was eye-opening:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Simple-Path-Wealth-financial-independence/dp/1533667926&quot;&gt;The Simple Path to Wealth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Four-Pillars-Investing-Building-Portfolio-ebook/dp/B0041842TW/ref=tmm_kin_swatch_0?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1587285907&amp;amp;sr=8-1&quot;&gt;The Four Pillars of Investing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key idea for me is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nobody can beat the market so you can’t and neither a professional investor. It doesn’t make sense to pay anybody to handpick you investment. How do we invest then? passive investing (index funds)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An easy way to convince me is to show me data:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/activevspassive.png&quot; alt=&quot;Active vs passive investing&quot; /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.betashares.com.au/insights/passive-investment-cyclical/&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/fundsVSmarkets.png&quot; alt=&quot;Funds agains S&amp;amp;P 500 index after 5 years&quot; /&gt;
Source: The Four Pillars of Investing&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this graphic we can see how for the last 15 years if you invested directly in the S&amp;amp;P500 Index passively you would have beaten all the actively managed funds. Take into account that they have to beat the market consistently and with a margin that allows them to earn their fees and still provide you some benefits. Index funds fees are really low since they just have to replicate the index. Do you research, look for bigger periods of time, the same pattern appears.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ok-how-can-i-do-it&quot;&gt;OK, how can I do it?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me introduce you &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_C._Bogle&quot;&gt;John C. Bogle&lt;/a&gt;. He is the creator of this type of investment:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bogle’s innovative idea was creating the world’s first index mutual fund in 1975. Bogle’s idea was that instead of beating the index and charging high costs, the index fund would mimic the index performance over the long run—thus achieving higher returns with lower costs than the costs associated with actively managed funds.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He created &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Vanguard_Group&quot;&gt;The Vanguard Group&lt;/a&gt; which provides differents types of investments, index funds between them, but they key here is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vanguard is owned by the funds managed by the company, and is therefore owned by its customers.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is great, this means your investments are not filling the pockets of a bunch of chairmen that want more and more benefits each year. You are the owner, that explains why they have the lowest fees in the market, the bare minimum to have everything up and running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If investing in index funds, you have to use Vanguard. In US they are easily available, in Spain at the time of writing the best option IMHO is &lt;a href=&quot;https://myinvestor.es/&quot;&gt;myinvestor&lt;/a&gt; since they don’t have minimum amount of investment needed and don’t have extra fees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vanguard not available in your country? Look for a similar option, main focus, low fees. Maybe Amundi?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may be thinking: “Juan you are going to far, it doesn’t matter to pay 2 or 3% per year in costs…let me quote a fragment of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Simple-Path-Wealth-financial-independence/dp/1533667926&quot;&gt;The Simple Path to Wealth&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;People underestimate the drag of costs to investing.
Paying fund and/or advisor fees of 1-2 percent seems low, especially in a good year. But make no mistake, these annual fees are a devil’s ball and chain on your wealth. As a point of reference, the average mutual fund ER (expense ratio: the fee funds charge investors) is ~1.25%. The ER for VTSAX is .05%. As Bogle says, performance comes and goes but expenses are always there, year after year. After year. Compounded over time the amount lost is breathtaking.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Consider this: Once you begin living on the returns from your portfolio you’ll be able to spend roughly 4% of your assets per year. If 1% of your money is going to management fees, that is a full 25% of your income.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;asset-allocation&quot;&gt;Asset allocation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a really difficult topic, I’ll try to summarize.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When investing you should not invest all the money in equity (more benefit, riskier), a part of it should go to fixed-income (less benefit, safer). What are the percentages? The two main factors are &lt;strong&gt;AGE&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;RISK-AVERSION&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a rule that says 100 minus your age should be the percentage of equity investment_. Me being 34 years old should have 66% equity and 34% fixed-income. Why? the older you are the more difficult will be to recover from a market downside, you won’t have time. If you have most of your invesment in fixed-income, the market downs will be much softer (also the highs). Being in your early twenties is a totally different story, you should welcome the market downs and invest happily since in the long term the market should go up and will have bought cheap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from the age, you never know how “risk-averse” you are until you see that your investment having 50% less value, are you really ready for it? This is something you have to take your time to think about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can provide my current asset allocation, is really simple, remember &lt;em&gt;a good investment strategy does not have to be super complex&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;70% - Vanguard Global Stock Index Fund&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;10% - Vanguard Emerging Markets Stock Index Fund&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;20% - Vanguard Global Bond Index Fund&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I have an 80 - 20 allocation which is pretty risky, in fact in the books above I read that does not make sense having less that 20 in fixed-income assets.
I go for global index funds to be really diversified and with 10% of emerging markets I cover some markets that are not present in Global Stock Index.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;personal-experience&quot;&gt;Personal experience&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have done my share of mistakes in investing. I started having just stocks of two Spanish companies handpicked, after a couple years I bought some more, this time technological companies since I’m software engineer I should now! omg…at least I could sell them all with an insignificant benefit. Then the last investment was in funds, but actively managed what made me have much less profit that the one I could have had (I did and Excel file with the possible benefits with smaller fees, also compared with Vanguard index funds for the same years…reality check).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well if I can prevent you from doing my same mistakes and trigger in you some willing to get informed about how to invest better, mission accomplished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;closing&quot;&gt;Closing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To wrap up, two contrasting ideas that are important to remember:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Past performance is no guarantee of future results.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Historically market always goes up in the long term.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the bogglehead decalogue:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Live Below Your Means&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Invest Early And Often&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Never Take On Too Much Risk, Or Accept Too Little&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Diversify&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t Time The Market&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use Index Funds&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keep Costs Low&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Minimize Taxes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keep It Simple&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stay The Course&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>Juan Pallarès</name><email>juan@pallares.me</email></author><category term="investment" /><category term="john bogle" /><category term="index funds" /><category term="money" /><category term="boglehead" /><summary type="html">A good investment strategy does not have to be difficult.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Merge request handling via slack channel</title><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/merge-request-handling-remotely-via-slack-channel/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Merge request handling via slack channel" /><published>2020-04-26T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-04-26T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://juan.pallares.me/merge-request-handling-remotely-via-slack-channel</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://juan.pallares.me/merge-request-handling-remotely-via-slack-channel/">&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned in the previous post, in my team &lt;a href=&quot;https://juan.pallares.me/remote-working-tips/&quot;&gt;we are very used to be colocated and interact frequently&lt;/a&gt;. Also since we do pair programming the amount of MR that needs to be accepted by a third person was low, but then we started working fully remote and it all changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team slack channel was flooded with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Guys! I have a new MR!”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Sure but first look at mine, the one I posted this morning”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Hey but I already had a look at this MR!!”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And all this conversations lost in the middle of other valuable conversations that we have in our channel. It was starting to be a chaotic, and we software engineers don’t like chaos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if we create a channel specific for the teams MRs? oh even better let’s handle the status with the reactions/emojis so it’s more visual and faster. This was the agreement we made:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/mr_channel_topic.png&quot; alt=&quot;MR channel topic&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The flow is the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A team member writes in the channel with a link to the MR and notifying the team with @here&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Whenever somebody starts having a look sets the eyes reaction&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When finishing reviewing:
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If there have been some comments. Sets the timer icon&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;When comments are addressed, the author sets the glasses icon (not very related but is my favourite one)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When the reviewers feel the MR is ready to be merged, they set approved reaction.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Finally, when the creator merges (or closes) the MR. Sets de check reaction.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is how the channel looks after some time adapting to this new flow. Conversations about the MR go in a thread so there are only MR links in the messages in the channel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/mr_channel_example.png&quot; alt=&quot;MR channel&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we restored the order and peace in our beloved team channel. What are the challenges you are facing these days?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Juan Pallarès</name><email>juan@pallares.me</email></author><category term="merge request" /><category term="slack" /><category term="emoji" /><category term="remote working" /><category term="channel" /><category term="covid-19" /><category term="tips" /><category term="job" /><category term="cofinement" /><summary type="html">How we decided to manage the MR now that we work remotely</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Remote working tips (COVID-19)</title><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/remote-working-tips/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Remote working tips (COVID-19)" /><published>2020-04-11T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-04-11T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://juan.pallares.me/remote-working-tips</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://juan.pallares.me/remote-working-tips/">&lt;p&gt;Before this pandemic my experience working remotely was almost non-existent. Maybe half a day because I had a personal matter to attend…or one day the whole team works remotely just to see we are able. But then, suddenly, we are forced to work 100% of our time remotely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;colocation---i-miss-my-team&quot;&gt;Colocation - I miss my team&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the beginning it was hard for us, &lt;strong&gt;we are the kind of team that is in constant communication&lt;/strong&gt;, we sit right to each other, we do pair programming often and we are used to just turn ourselves and ask: “Hey guys this functionality is driving me crazy, can somebody help me?” or “I just created an MR, can somebody take a look?” and now if I turn around I just see my room wall and some old books. Apart from my own team, another teams or the business is also very close, like 5 to 10 meters distance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How did we tackle this issue? we do a &lt;strong&gt;sync call every morning via &lt;a href=&quot;https://zoom.us/&quot;&gt;Zoom&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; (which was our default tool for video calls way before this crisis started) and during the day we may do one or two more depending in our needs. We tried having a zoom call all day open with everybody muted and just unmuted and talk if you need help, it didn’t work for us. We also communicate via &lt;a href=&quot;https://slack.com/&quot;&gt;Slack&lt;/a&gt;, every team member notifies when he starts to work and when they are leaving, and also the lunch break. It may feel too strict and I know that &lt;strong&gt;companies that work 100% remote follow a much more async style of working, but remember we are used to work together you can see our way of working as a trade-off between being fully remote and a colocated team pair programming most of the day&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;working-hours&quot;&gt;Working hours&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a &lt;strong&gt;double-edged sword&lt;/strong&gt;. Working remotely can provoke that you &lt;strong&gt;procastinate&lt;/strong&gt; too much, you are at home ad you have much more distractions around or on the other hand, you &lt;strong&gt;never really stop working&lt;/strong&gt;, maybe the only computer you have is the work computer so you get notified about something in slack is difficult to disconnect.
What I do, and I can do this because I’m not a parent (people in this situation with children are real heroes) is working as close as possible to the schedule I had before. I’m a creature of habit and I’m trying to use this to my advantage, so aproximately I work from 9am to 6pm with a 1h lunch break and if helps me focus much more than working some hours scattered through the day. Anyway, this depends a lot on the person and I’m saying only what worked for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;home-office&quot;&gt;Home office&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were lucky our company allowed us to take home the screens, keyboard, etc. everything we would need to work from home. You need to be comfortable and ideally as close as possible and to the desk you have at the office. Anyway is also good to switch the place you work during the day, you gonna stay at home all day at least switch the place you are staying inside home. Half an hour in the balcony now that is sunny?
My setup is two QHD screens connected a MacBook Pro and external keyboard and mouse I’m pretty comfortable, what I’m struggling with is the placement of the webcam, I want have it in front of my face so people can feel I talk to them but I used to set the laptop on the side, anyway not a big problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sports&quot;&gt;Sports&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a normal situation I do sport almost daily and twice per week I do it at lunch time, me and some coworkers do a 45 minutes HIIT training and then get a shower and eat in front of the computer. This is something I really miss, it helped disconnect a lot and often I was stuck on something and after training I saw clearly what was the issue. What I’m doing now is traying to train everyday too, even if less motivated and just want to be on the sofa I force myself. How to train? there are plenty of videos now in Youtube, I recommend &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vc1E5CfRfos&quot;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;. Even if you weren’t training before I believe now is a good time to start, otherwise being confined we almost don’t move and being sedentary can impact your health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What has been your experience so far working from home?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Juan Pallarès</name><email>juan@pallares.me</email></author><category term="remote work" /><category term="covid-19" /><category term="tips" /><category term="job" /><category term="cofinement" /><summary type="html">Sharing my experience after 4 weeks of working remotely (and confined)</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Raspberry Pi 3 III Pi-hole PiVPN</title><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/raspberry-pi-hole-vpn/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Raspberry Pi 3 III Pi-hole PiVPN" /><published>2017-09-03T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-09-03T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://juan.pallares.me/raspberry-pi-hole-vpn</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://juan.pallares.me/raspberry-pi-hole-vpn/">&lt;p&gt;In this final post I will talk about things you can do with an always running pi not related to media. That’s why is a bonus track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pi-hole---block-ads-in-your-local-network&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pi-hole.net/&quot;&gt;Pi-hole&lt;/a&gt; - Block ads in your local network&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m used to have always installed an ad-blocker on my browser, the web ads got out of hand long time ago with giant banners that block all the screen so it’s more like a survival thing. The problem comes with the phone browser, there are no good blockers there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So imagine a software that blocks the ads but not once they are in the browser, before, they don’t even arrive to your network, your network performance improves, this is Pi-Hole. It even blocks the ads you get on the phone games, amazing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The installation is very easy and once you have done you can access to manager web with all the info about what’s being blocked, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;curl -sSL https://install.pi-hole.net | bash
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/pihole.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;Pi-hole&quot; title=&quot;Pi-hole&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pivpn&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pivpn.io/&quot;&gt;PiVPN&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s really useful to have a VPN available if you need to use internet in a typical airport “free wifi”, the ones that are not recommended to use with sensible data. PiVPN installs &lt;strong&gt;OpenVPN&lt;/strong&gt; on your raspberri in a very simple way. It all starts with a curl command like with pi-hole&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;curl -L https://install.pivpn.io | bash
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once installed you can create clients for windows/mac/android/iphone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;free-dns&quot;&gt;Free DNS&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only totally free dns provider I found, that does not even send an email monthly to reactivate your account is freedns.afraid.org. You can refresh the IP with a cron job (later more detail about that)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;backup&quot;&gt;Backup&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can create a backup (.img) of your SD card to a network / USB drive while the card is inserted in your pi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Create an image of the card currently in the pi to a network drive / USB drive using the dd command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo dd if=/dev/mmcblk0p2 of=/home/pi/networkdrive/my.img bs=1M
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(replace &lt;strong&gt;/dev/mmcblk0p2&lt;/strong&gt; with your own SD card and &lt;strong&gt;/home/pi/networkdrive/my.img&lt;/strong&gt; with your own network drive / USB drive + image file name)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if we want this to run periodically? keep reading&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;self-maintenance-with-cron-jobs&quot;&gt;Self maintenance with cron jobs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last but not least, since the raspberry will be running 24/7 it’s a good idea to run some commands from time to time to have everything running smoothly. I do it with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cron&quot;&gt;cron&lt;/a&gt; jobs. If you run this command&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo crontab -e
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll see the jobs that need root rights to run. I have the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;@daily dd if=/dev/mmcblk0p2 of=/home/pi/networkdrive/rasp-`date +\%Y\%m\%d\%H\%M\%S`.img bs=1M

0 3 * * * /usr/bin/apt-get update &amp;amp;&amp;amp;  /usr/bin/apt-get upgrade -q -y &amp;gt;&amp;gt; /var/log/apt/myupdates.log

0 5 * * 0 reboot
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well the first one is the command that makes the backup but the name depends on the date and time so I can have backups of several days in the same folder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second one is simply and update and an upgrade that writes a log for debug purposes. It runs daily at 3am. The third is that once a week I want the raspberry to do a reboot at 5am.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now if I run this other command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;crontab -e
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can see more jobs I have, one is the free DNS to work&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;0 5 * * * find /media/netdisk/backup/ -mindepth 1 -type f -mtime +3 -delete
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only one left deletes the backup files older than 3 days, otherwise my HD was full very easily and I had to delete the backups manually, no way!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Juan Pallarès</name><email>juan@pallares.me</email></author><category term="ad" /><category term="block" /><category term="VPN" /><category term="raspberry pi" /><category term="openvpn" /><category term="pi-hole" /><category term="pivpn" /><summary type="html">Filter all the ads in you local net (Pi-Hole) and create VPN server (PiVPN)</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Raspberry Pi 3 a.k.a the 24/7 auto downloader II</title><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/raspberry-pi-autodownloader-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Raspberry Pi 3 a.k.a the 24/7 auto downloader II" /><published>2017-05-03T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-05-03T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://juan.pallares.me/raspberry-pi-autodownloader-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://juan.pallares.me/raspberry-pi-autodownloader-2/">&lt;p&gt;Following the guide to have a Raspberry hadling all the media downloads at home, let’s continue:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bittorrent-client&quot;&gt;BitTorrent client&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several options available for downloading torrents. The one I chose is &lt;a href=&quot;http://deluge-torrent.org/&quot;&gt;Deluge&lt;/a&gt; because of being free, light-weight and ad-free. It also has a “client-server” mode very useful for head-less raspberry and some plugins available that make it very flexible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://tektab.com/2015/11/10/running-a-always-on-torrent-box-with-raspberry-pi-deluge-on-raspbian/&quot;&gt;installation&lt;/a&gt; is pretty straightforward and after it you will be able to control it from a client you can install on windows/mac/linux. Also a webUI is available. In case your are intesred, here you have some &lt;a href=&quot;http://dev.deluge-torrent.org/wiki/UserGuide/Service/systemd&quot;&gt;useful data&lt;/a&gt; for a more advanced installation. Remember to configure it to download the torrents to the disk we mounted in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://juan.pallares.me/Raspbery-pi-aka-the-247-auto-downloader/&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, unless you want to run out of space in the pi very fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tv-shows---sonarr&quot;&gt;TV shows - Sonarr&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/sonarr1.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;Sonarr&quot; title=&quot;Sonarr&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sonarr.tv/&quot;&gt;Sonarr&lt;/a&gt; will handle all the TV shows downloads. I’m in love with Sonarr and the moment you start using it you will feel the same. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.htpcguides.com/install-sonarr-raspberry-pi-mono-310/&quot;&gt;installation&lt;/a&gt; is a little bit more tricky since it involves Mono. Once you have it running, remember to configure it to use the deluge client you installed before (or any other you chose).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;notice&quot;&gt;Skip the configuration about moving/renaming in Sonarr and CouchPotato. Filebot will handle it&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also you need to set up some indexers for the content (rarbg in my case at the time of writing). After that is easy, just add the shows you are interested in and the quality you want and they will be downloaded automatically when released, skip the part about moving/renaming for the moment. A calendar will be created:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/sonarr2.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;Sonarr calendar&quot; title=&quot;Sonarr calendar&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it wasn’t enough you can also configure notification in “Connections”. In my case I have pushbullet telling me when a TV show has been grabbed. Later you will see this is not necessary with Filebot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;movies---couch-potato&quot;&gt;Movies - Couch Potato&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My love doesn’t go only to Sonarr, &lt;a href=&quot;https://couchpota.to/&quot;&gt;CouchPotato&lt;/a&gt; is also deep in my heart, I guess I have “software polygamy”. Downloading movies will become very easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/couchpotato.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;Couch Potato&quot; title=&quot;Couch Potato&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a very easy installation, the configuration is similar to Sonarr, set you downloader (deluge), indexers and were to download the movies. Skip the part about moving/renaming like before. Once configured what CouchPotato will do for you is download the movies you are interested in the moment they are available in a good enough quality (can be configured), add them to your wanted list and go to the cinema only when really necessary. You can also automatically add movies that have more than an 8 in IMDB….boom!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;moving-and-renaming-media-and-getting-subtitles---filebot&quot;&gt;Moving and renaming media and getting subtitles - Filebot&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the last part, we got the movies, the shows but they have strange names, you still need subtitles and the media is placed in a downloads folder….&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.filebot.net/&quot;&gt;Filebot&lt;/a&gt; “the ultimate tv renamer / subtitle downloader” comes to rescue you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, it’s true, Sonarr and CouchPotato can do the renaming and moving on their own but what about the subtitles? and what about having a software specialized for that? much better isn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.filebot.net/forums/viewtopic.php?t=3974&quot;&gt;Installation on the pi&lt;/a&gt; has some difficulty but if I did it you can. Remember to set it up with you OpenSubtitles user.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After it, I use Filebot with commands, scripts I configured, not the UI. In Deluge you need to install the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.filebot.net/forums/viewtopic.php?t=3974&quot;&gt;Execute plugin&lt;/a&gt;. This plugin allows you to run a script after downloading a file, and that’s what we will do:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#!/bin/bash&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;torrentid&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;torrentname&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$2&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;torrentpath&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$3&lt;/span&gt;

/usr/share/filebot/filebot.sh &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-script&lt;/span&gt; fn:amc &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;--output&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;/media/netdisk/PlexMedia&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;--log-file&lt;/span&gt; /home/pi/amc.log &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;--action&lt;/span&gt; move &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;--conflict&lt;/span&gt; override &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-non-strict&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;--def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;subtitles&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;en,es &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;artwork&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;y &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;clean&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;y &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;reportError&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;y &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;gmail&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;esbroma:XXXXXXXXXXX &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;pushbullet&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;XXXXXXXXXXXX &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;ut_dir=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$torrentpath&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$torrentname&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;ut_kind=multi&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;ut_title=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$torrentname&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically, the script.sh is moving the media to the PlexMedia folder, there will create a folder for Movies and other for Tv Shows, inside them a folder per movie/tv show and inside TV shows a folder per season. It will also rename it, grab subtitles (if available) in this case in english and spanish. It will also notify me by email and by pushbullet. As you may have noticed, a log is created to track possible issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another possible script you can configure is one that looks for subtitles from time to time. It can be necessary because very often you will download media freshly released and the subtitles won’t be available yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#!/bin/bash&lt;/span&gt;

/usr/share/filebot/filebot.sh &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-script&lt;/span&gt; fn:suball &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;/media/netdisk/PlexMedia&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;--log-file&lt;/span&gt; /home/pi/subtitle.log &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-non-strict&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;--def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;maxAgeDays&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;7 &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;subtitles&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;en,es &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;ignoreTextLanguage&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;en,es &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;reportError&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;y &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;pushbullet&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;XXXXXXXXXXXX
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this example, I’m looking for missing subtitles in media that is one week older at most.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;playing-the-media---plex-on-the-pi&quot;&gt;Playing the media - Plex on the Pi?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, now that we have everything, we want to play it, I prefer Plex over Kodi, because of my own needs but feel free to use any player you want, even DLNA would work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried to &lt;a href=&quot;https://raspberrypi.stackexchange.com/questions/50031/raspberry-pi-3-as-plex-media-server-local-without-transcoding&quot;&gt;use Plex on the raspberri pi&lt;/a&gt;, and did some &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.raspberrypi.org/forums/viewtopic.php?f=35&amp;amp;t=151924&amp;amp;p=999730#p999730&quot;&gt;research&lt;/a&gt; to see if it was possible. But no luck, only with media that is not too high quality. At the end I run Plex on another computer that uses the media on the net disk. Is in this Plex server where I installed SubZero channel, it will help you download subtitles too (yes I hate searching and adding subtitles manually).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s it regarding auto-downloading media, but I still have a couple things to show you about the Raspberry Pi, you will have to wait for next post though.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Juan Pallarès</name><email>juan@pallares.me</email></author><category term="auto" /><category term="download" /><category term="movies" /><category term="raspberry pi" /><category term="tvshow" /><summary type="html">Series of posts in which I’ll explain how the raspberry downloads automatically all my tv shows and movies, also the subtitle and the media in an unattended ...</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Raspberry Pi 3 a.k.a the 24/7 auto downloader</title><link href="https://juan.pallares.me/raspberry-pi-autodownloader/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Raspberry Pi 3 a.k.a the 24/7 auto downloader" /><published>2017-03-18T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-03-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://juan.pallares.me/raspberry-pi-autodownloader</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://juan.pallares.me/raspberry-pi-autodownloader/">&lt;h3 id=&quot;why&quot;&gt;Why?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently bought a Raspberry pi 3, it was improvised I had bought a Pine A64 but it was taking ages to arrive, then the new powerful version of the Pi appeared and I could not resist, Amazon and in couple days at home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/raspberrypi.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Raspberry Pi 3&quot; title=&quot;Raspberry Pi 3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My plan for it was basically replicating the automatic downloading of torrents (movies and tv shows mainly). I had it in a PC so I had powered on all day. This way I would take advantage of the Pi low consumption. Also I would take the chance to refresh my unix knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ingredientes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Raspberry Pi&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.es/gp/product/B00J2BU7WO/ref=oh_aui_search_detailpage?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;psc=1&quot;&gt;SD Card&lt;/a&gt; - 16Gb is more than enough, we will use an external disk for video storage&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.es/gp/product/B00W7S1BFG/ref=oh_aui_search_detailpage?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;psc=1&quot;&gt;Case&lt;/a&gt; (optional)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.es/gp/product/B01DDW0P1U/ref=oh_aui_search_detailpage?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;psc=1&quot;&gt;Power cable&lt;/a&gt; (optional, you may have a spare one but I wanted a quality one with enough amperage)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;first-steps&quot;&gt;First steps&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you already know the Pi works with linux, there are all kind of images available to download but I choose the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.raspberrypi.org/help/videos/&quot;&gt;recommended one&lt;/a&gt;, Raspbian, looking for flexibility. The installation is very easy but keep in mind you will need a monitor with HDMI connection and a keyboard plugged in the Pi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have Raspbian up and running, next thing is to configure the Pi to be able to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.raspberrypi.org/documentation/remote-access/ssh/windows.md&quot;&gt;work remotely with SHH&lt;/a&gt;, then you can leave it somewhere hidden just connected to the power and the network (I recommend using the ethernet even if the Pi has wifi and the ethernet port is 10/100Mb only, I guess I’m old school)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mounting-external-drive&quot;&gt;Mounting external drive&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For media storage I used a 1TB USB external drive connected to the router, the process is a little bit more complicated than it if you have it directly connected to the Pi, but easy anyway. I followed the steps &lt;a href=&quot;http://raspberrypi.stackexchange.com/questions/40974/access-network-samba-share-from-pi-client&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Basically these commands (for anonymous access):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;apt-get install  samba-common smbclient samba-common-bin smbclient  cifs-utils
mkdir /mnt/abc
mount -t cifs //server/share /mnt/abc
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also configured a cronjob so in every reboot it automonts the network disk&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;@reboot sleep 10 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; mount -a
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rpi-monitor&quot;&gt;RPi-Monitor&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To close this first post about the Pi, I want to talk about the RPi-Monitor, as the name says it’s a monitor that tells you basic information about the status of the Pi:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/rpi-monitor.png&quot; alt=&quot;RPi-Monitor&quot; title=&quot;RPi-Monitor&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s perfect to detect if suddenly the CPU is under heavy load or it’s becoming too hot. It also helps track if you have the latest software installed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;this-is-only-the-beginning&quot;&gt;This is only the beginning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next post we will start installing a torrent client, Deluge and software like Couch Potato and Sonarr, you will love it ;)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Juan Pallarès</name><email>juan@pallares.me</email></author><category term="auto" /><category term="download" /><category term="movies" /><category term="raspberry pi" /><category term="tvshow" /><summary type="html">Series of posts in which I’ll explain how the raspberry downloads automatically all my tv shows and movies, also the subtitle and the media in an unattended ...</summary></entry></feed>